First published in 2024 by John Wiley & Sons Australia, Ltd

Level 4, 600 Bourke St, Melbourne, Victoria 3000, Australia

Typeset in Plantin Std Regular 11.5pt/15.5pt

© James and Natascha Millard and related entities 2024

The moral rights of the author have been asserted

ISBN: 978-1-394-24889-6

All rights reserved. Except as permitted under the Australian Copyright

Act 1968 (for example, a fair dealing for the purposes of study, research,

criticism or review), no part of this book may be reproduced, stored in

a retrieval system, communicated or transmitted in any form or by any

means without prior written permission. All inquiries should be made to

the publisher at the address above.

Cover design by Wiley

Cover Image: © DisobeyArt/Adobe Stock

Finance icons (figure 2.2, p69): © Icons-Studio / Adobe Stock

Disclaimer

The material in this publication is of the nature of general comment only,

and does not represent professional advice. It is not intended to provide

specific guidance for particular circumstances and it should not be relied

on as the basis for any decision to take action or not take action on any

matter which it covers. Readers should obtain professional advice where

appropriate, before making any such decision. To the maximum extent

permitted by law, the author and publisher disclaim all responsibility

and liability to any person, arising directly or indirectly from any person

taking or not taking action based on the information in this publication.

***

The information contained in this book is general in nature and does

not take into account your personal situation. Before acting on any

information, you should consider the appropriateness of the information

for your objectives, financial situation and needs.

All client names and a bunch of other identifying details have been

changed in this book for privacy reasons.

Insufficient Funds

xii

always be obvious. You may not be swimming in debt or have a $0

bank account. Perhaps it’s just a feeling that you’re not on track, or

you find yourself comparing your life to your friends’ or family’s,

and wishing it was different. It could be you’re not happy with your

financial progress or direction, you’re overwhelmed by options and

decision fatigue. Perhaps you’re uncertain about how your current

financial decisions will impact your and your family’s future.

My goal in this book is to guide you far away from this place and

ensure you never return.

The true meaning of Sufficient Funds

Most people we meet in our financial advice business are struggling

to align their money decisions with their lives in a way that ensures

they have ‘sufficient funds’. Often this is because they haven’t

defined sufficient as it applies to them and therefore are chasing

their tails. Even if they have a financial plan, it’s destined to fail

if they haven’t stopped and asked themselves the all-encompassing

question: What really matters to me?

We all strive for financial wellbeing. While this will look different

for each of us, essentially it could be defined as ‘having sufficient

funds for your chosen lifestyle at a given point in time’.

Sufficient Funds doesn’t mean being restricted to a low-cost, meagre

existence and just getting by. Sufficient for you is about defining

what your ideal life looks like then creating and implementing a

plan to make it happen!

Introduction

xiii

This involves giving yourself permission to give society’s norms

the big middle finger. For too long society’s expectations have set

the rules for us: get an education, get a job, get married, buy a

house, have kids, work 9 to 5 for 40 years, take two to four weeks’

holiday a year, retire … then die. Not cool. Life should be way more

fun than this!

Life isn’t like golf where the quality of the dot points don’t matter

and the only thing that counts is the number on the card at the end

of the game. You could land one shot in the water, the next in the

bunker and still sink one from 100 metres out for par. Our lives are

defined by the time we spend between the dots, not the scorecard.

You make micro money decisions every single day, but do you ever

stop to think about the impact of these decisions on the life you’re

striving for?

Your ability to live the life you dream of is dictated by two

core components:

1. making sound financial decisions

2. aligning these decisions with your ideal life.

In our work, we meet lots of people who have a fairly good handle

on number 1, but almost no one truly gets the second part. Sound

financial decisions mean little in the long run if you’re not happy.

So these two elements go very much hand in hand. You need to

be able to cut through to the core of what makes you tick, then be

strategic about how you put it all in place. It’s tough, but I’m about

to show you how.

Insufficient Funds

xiv

I spend my days helping people see what’s possible with their

finances and in this book I’m going to share all this with you and

more. It’s time to live on your own terms, with a good stash of cash

to create your dream life, whatever that means to you.

Let’s roll on and see how you’re going to take your life from

Insufficient to Sufficient Funds.

The ATM slip and one all-time road trip

At 20 years old, during my time at university, I was lucky enough

to do a semester in Canada. I studied for four months at UVic on

Vancouver Island in BC. I surfed in a 5mm  wetsuit in 6-degree

water, had a season pass at Whistler, partied five nights a week,

and passed all of my subjects with flying colours (read: a consistent

50 per cent!). I made friends for life with a bunch of peeps who had

a lust for living the likes of which I’d never seen. Maybe it was the

mountains, or the Fireball! At the end of that semester I met up

with G-Rod, Sammy and Jezza, three of my best mates from home

who had also been ‘studying’ in North America, and we pulled off a

dream road trip on a shoestring budget.

A few weeks before we left on this adventure we’d been out drinking

at Customs House, one of the usual hangs in Newcastle. It was

student-night $1 drinks, four at a time — a standard Wednesday

really for campus-living uni students. One of the boys, who had sold

his body board for $40 just to come out for a night, returned from the

ATM with ‘Insufficient Funds’ obtrusively highlighted on his receipt.

We all lost it! But as the laughter died a terrible idea was hatched.

Insufficient Funds would be an awesome band name! Jezza had mad

skills on the piano, but given the rest of us had little to offer in the

Introduction

xv

way of musical talent we reluctantly concluded that this wasn’t going

to be our path to fame and fortune. The Customs’ drinks flowed

and the plans continued to gain momentum. We would start a surf

brand instead! A week later we had 50 trucker caps and T-shirts with

Insufficient Funds printed and we sold these to our mates, as well as

a few on eBay. We were gaining notoriety around the Newcastle Uni

campus. Fuelled by the dream of our future multimillion-dollar baby,

we flew out on our overseas exchange with grand visions of surfing,

travelling and partying without strings.

For a thousand bucks US we bought a beat-up old Chrysler LeBaron

station wagon, the one with the wooden panels. It was a shocker,

so luckily for us we had our accents for currency. We drove this

beast around the US for two months, covering 10 865 miles across

18 states. We basically tracked a horseshoe from Vancouver,

Canada, down the west coast to Baja, Mexico, over to Florida, up to

Ontario, Canada, and back to New York City. We dumped the car

in the Bronx — keys in the ignition — and flew home. The car was

registered in Sammy’s name and years later his poor mum was still

getting holding and towing fines in the mail from Yonkers Police

Department. Sorry Louise.

The road trip was long, the tales we still tell even longer. Here are a

few (more or less PC) highlights:

•

bungee jumping in Nanaimo, Vancouver Island — free on

Valentine’s Day if you went nude

•

the Southern Oregon coast — one of my favourite places

in the world: surfing with sea lions chased in by the great

whites on a remote beach near Florence, and scaring the

shit out of a local fisherman in the process

Introduction

xvii

•

ending up on the ‘don’t-ever-fucking-go-there’ side of town

everywhere we went — special mentions include nearly side-

swiping a car in Compton, getting stuck doing a 10-point

turn as we woke up locals at midnight in New Orleans, and

me being chased by a drug dealer with a knife through the

back streets of Charleston, SC (don’t ask)

•

staying in a billionaire’s mansion on a lake in Ontario,

thanks to our well-connected Canadian buddy Blake

•

seeing Ben Harper and Jack Johnson live at Jones Beach

Theater on Long Island, NY.

We literally drove that poor car into the ground. For the last

week or two smoke poured from the back as a waterfall of power-

steering fluid leaked onto the muffler. Every time we filled up on

gas we needed another bottle of fluid — another reflection on the

Insufficient Funds life we were living!

Before setting off on this road trip, still in Canada and gaining some

traction in our small community of newfound buddies, we printed

a bunch more Insufficient Funds shirts, hoodies and caps and set

off down the west coast. We funded some of the trip by selling our

merch to randoms along the way. We’d strike up a conversation

with almost anyone. They’d be drawn to us because of the accent,

and we’d do deals out of the boot in all sorts of dodgy places.

We were going to be the next Hurley, who sold to Nike for $60 million.

We’d cash in and never work a full-time job in our lives!

But … life got in the way. We went back to uni, finished our degrees,

put on our sensible shirts and ties, and got our full-time jobs. At the

Insufficient Funds

xviii

time we didn’t have the balls, maturity or foresight to really give it

a crack.

The implications of ‘Insufficient Funds’ never lost traction though.

In hindsight the philosophy of our little movement revolved around

freedom, living day-to-day without a care in the world, having the

means — just — to do everything we wanted. That was our life as

20-year-olds, the first wave of Millennials, and it was so relatable.

Insufficient Funds offered a different, droll way of looking at that

dismal $0 balance on the ATM slip.

Our journey to Sufficient Funds

My name is James, and I have Sufficient Funds.

Hold up, who is this wanker?

Before you exercise that faved Aussie tradition of trimming the

poppies, let me share a bit more of my story. With a British dad

and an Aussie mum, I had an interesting and fortunate upbringing.

Born in England, but moving to Australia when I was two years old,

I spent most of my youth in and around Grafton in the Northern

Rivers. My nanna lived 40 minutes up the Pacific Highway in the

then sleepy coastal village of Yamba.

Grafton was an amazing place to grow up and I wouldn’t have

traded it for the world. In a country town, people’s views on money

are a bit different from those in the city, and the bar for financial

success is set fairly low. I remember being labelled ‘rich’ by the boys

at cricket one Saturday because Dad dropped me off in a late-model

Ford Territory.

Introduction

xix

My parents were, and are still, comfortable but certainly not rich.

They are a great example of people who spend money in line

with their values. They’re also proof that the idea of ‘experiences not

things’ was around long before it was meme’d and made Instapopular.

We were very lucky to have seen a good chunk of the world as kids,

mostly on a shoestring, but we weren’t rocking the new Nikes and

I’m pretty sure I was in high school before I finally got my first pair

of Quiksilver school shorts.

Some of these parental decisions were torture for me at the time,

but looking back I came to see that without big incomes they did

a cracking job of setting themselves up and giving my sister Kate

and me a fantastic start. So from a young age I understood what

Sufficient meant.

Fast forward a decade, with my university degree in hand, I ended

up in finance. Initially I donned the suit and tie, sat in the corporate

office looking over Sydney Harbour and embraced the wisdom of the

suits who surrounded me. Over time, though, the pull of creating

something more meaningful took over in me. The idea of focusing

on what was truly Sufficient and being true to who I really was led

me to ditch the suits and ties for boardies and T-shirts — and I never

looked back.

Since then I’ve done a few more things to work towards both

defining my version of Sufficient and achieving it. For the past

two decades I have been working in the money world, helping

individuals, couples and families with their money decisions and

financial planning. Looking back on these years, I know I was

absolutely destined to be where I am right now and I don’t regret a

thing. My wife Tash and I have built a business, Sufficient Funds, that

serves people in a way that truly makes their world better. In turn,

Insufficient Funds

xx

Tash and I have created the freedom we’ve always dreamed of by

running a super-lean operation that has been entirely virtual since

way before COVID made it cool. We have an amazing team, with

great systems, and as a family we now have complete freedom of

location if we want it.

Talking about travel, we’ve also had a lot of fun along the way.

I’ve travelled internationally on average at least once a year since

a high-school exchange to Dachau, Germany, in 1999. I’ve surfed

and snowboarded on four continents, made it to overseas weddings,

thrown our own wedding, and visited friends and family wherever

they happen to be in the world.

This is all part of our version of Sufficient Funds.

Could we have achieved many financial goals sooner?

Absolutely!

But it’s never just about ‘financial’ goals for us, neither should it be

for you.

You may be saying to yourself, ‘That’s all cool, James, but why is this

book important to me?’ Well, it wasn’t all about making this work

for us personally. As a professional, I’ve clocked over 10 000 hours

of one-on-one with clients, helping them do this in their own lives.

This heavy devotion to repetition, improvement and feedback

is what Todd Herman refers to in his book The Alter Ego Effect

when talking about reaching a level of mastery in your field. This

field for me is not just about providing financial advice, as my

Introduction

xxi

profession would define it, but in focusing on helping people make

a successful connection between money and life and use it to truly

live out their dreams.

I’ll return to our journey to Sufficient Funds in later pages. Achieving,

and reaching beyond, Sufficient Funds is exactly what you’ll be doing

if you read and implement the suggestions in this book.

How this book works and why it’s

important to you

This book is not a guide to escaping from work. The idea of

retirement as a life goal is flawed. It is based on the notion that you

work in a job you don’t love with people you can’t stand and your

sole aim is to get out the other end. Putting too much emphasis on

retirement as the source of all happiness will likely leave you feeling

short-changed when you discover it isn’t the light at the end of the

tunnel you dreamed about.

Achieving Sufficient Funds is not about retirement planning. It’s

something that can bear fruit much faster than that, and it’s way

more powerful.

It starts with acknowledging that you will always need some form of

income to allow you to live.

Defining what is Sufficient for you is covered in chapter 1, and it all

flows from there. You’ll learn very quickly that the more you align

your money decisions with the outcomes you want, the more clarity

you’ll gain over your future, the more confidence you’ll have, the

Insufficient Funds

xxii

more momentum you’ll build and, ultimately, the happier and more

fulfilled you’ll be!

Following the steps I outline will allow you to take action now

towards living life on your own terms, spending money according

to your values, and always having money for the experiences and

things that seriously matter to you, now and forever!

I share a fair bit about me in these pages in the hope you can relate.

This book gets far more personal than most (sorry to Tash, who puts

up with my unabashed storytelling even though she is a much more

private person). I share a lot about our lives here, as well as stories

from people we’ve worked with, so you can see you’re not alone in

the challenges you face and that the solutions are very much within

your reach.

With my training, hands-on experience, lust for adventure and

no-holds-barred attitude to giving new things a crack, I’ve made

that connection in my own life and we’re now making it flow for

our clients.

This book will give you the skills and strategies needed to implement

your money plan in a way that allows you to live your ideal life.

Once you’ve worked out your life plan, you need to implement your

money plan. You also need to know how to reassess and adapt when

the shit hits the fan.

There’s plenty of information out there about the money side, but

very little about how to make that much-needed connection to your

life, which means you may struggle to implement your plan.

Insufficient Funds

xxiv

By the end of chapter 4: Defend, you’ll be fully equipped to shield

yourself and your family from the inevitable bumps in the road.

You’ll discover how to bounce back after depleting your emergency

buffer, strategies for sudden shifts, the interesting role of perspective

and how to insure against the unforeseeable.

Finally, in chapter 5: Deliver, we bring it all home and discuss what

comes next. If you have implemented everything in this book up

to this chapter, you’ll be well on your way to achieving Sufficient

Funds. The trick now is to stay motivated and on track. Loaded with

practical tips, and with a clear picture of how you can consistently

redefine Sufficient, you will be unstoppable.

You’ve achieved Sufficient Funds, when you’re clear and confident

about your future, you have a protection plan and suitable buffers

in place, and you’re building mad stacks in all the areas you need to

achieve all the big goals you’ve set for yourself.

I am seriously pumped about the results you’ll get, but before we rip

into it, a quick note about retirement.

Fuck F.I.R.E. — why retirement is

NOT the goal

You may have heard of the FIRE movement? Investopedia describes

it as follows:

a movement dedicated to a program of extreme savings … By

dedicating up to 70% of income to savings, followers of the FIRE

movement may eventually be able to quit their jobs and live solely

off small withdrawals from their portfolios decades before the

conventional retirement age of 65.

Introduction

xxv

Firstly, to make FIRE work, you need to be one very ‘special’ human,

someone who thrives on frugality, because you will spend years,

even decades, spending next to nothing, saving like crazy, likely

working a job you don’t enjoy, to eventually quit and live off the

pennies you’ve managed to squirrel away.

It might surprise you, but even as a financial guy, most extremely

frugal people irk me. If you can live a low-cost life and be happy

doing all the things you want to do, that’s truly amazing. Good

for you, but for the most part frugality is about extreme sacrifice.

Spending nothing and as a result having no fun, is not a pathway

I’m chasing. I’ve found too many fun things I love to do — think

heli-skiing, mountain biking and regular travel — things that cost

money and that I don’t want to wait until I’m 65 to enjoy.

If you spend the best part of your work life saving a high percentage

of your income, you’ll actually find it difficult to unwind from this

behaviour when you’re finally able to stop and enjoy it. Look at Jack

Welch, storied president of General Electric. He had a heart attack

that nearly killed him at age 70. He said his biggest regret was how

tight he’d been with his money. Growing up without much meant

he squirrelled it all away. Even with his huge income and assets, he

still wouldn’t allow himself to stop and enjoy it, until it was almost

too late. For your sake, I sincerely hope this isn’t you, but if it is, this

book will be insanely helpful in showing you how to achieve your

version of Sufficient while allowing you to live now .

Another issue with FIRE is that you must rely heavily on consistent

investment returns. The spreadsheet you downloaded from Mr Money

Moustache’s site — Google him, he’s a bit of a hero, but not someone

99 per cent of us are likely to be able to emulate — is tracking your

daily, weekly, monthly progress towards Financial Independence.

Insufficient Funds

2

We park the money for this part because money is a repeat offender

in creating limiting beliefs. When money is involved upfront it

causes us to worry at the outset that we can’t achieve our goals or

won’t ever be able to afford something we want. So right now please

forget about the dollars, park your worries about debts and savings

for a while. It’s time to focus on your dreams.

The power of positive thinking

for financial wellbeing

Before we launch into defining your ideal life, I want to address the

importance of having your mindset right.

I’ve never been criticised for not thinking big enough. I’m a dreamer.

I’ve also never had a problem with convincing myself that whatever

I want is achievable. According to CliftonStrengths, ‘futuristic’ and

‘positivity’ are among my top strengths. Someone once told me

that I’m too positive. I’m not convinced that’s possible as long as

you channel it into action and back it up with an occasional dose of

realism, though not too much of the latter.

In my experience, self-

belief and positivity are the keys to getting

started and jumping all the hurdles along the way.

When you have something massively meaningful to work towards

you’ll move mountains to make it happen. Even more so when you

experience small wins and feed off the positivity of those wins when

aiming towards your bigger goals. You’re not only kicking goals,

you’re carving out your mindset.

Define — the missing step

3

Before we get stuck into your definition of Sufficient and how to get

there, I want to share with you some achievements in my life where

positive thinking and self-

belief were required above all else.

I think back to my early days at university, planning for my exchange

to Canada, where the seeds for this book first germinated. At the

time, leaving behind all my friends and family for six months felt

huge, but the excitement and enormity of what lay ahead made me

save harder and put in the additional hours to organise myself and

make it happen. The cost, the time to plan and prepare, and all the

unknowns that scared me so much seemed like massive hurdles.

But I passed all my classes, the trip happened, and I made friends

and memories for life. Positive thinking and action turned those

six months into a life-

changing experience and one of the best and

most memorable experiences I’ve ever had.

Fast forward to December 2006. Tash and I were recently engaged

and on relatively low incomes. It was no Kim Kardashian rock, but

I spent 80 per cent of two years’ savings on the ring. For a 25-

year-

old in a low-

level corporate position, I’d majorly splashed out. The

bank balance was bleak and we had just over 12 months to save

from scratch for a wedding and honeymoon, while also wanting to

buy our first home. We were working our butts off to get ahead so

we could make the life we wanted. Although we’d already travelled

extensively both separately and together, we were determined to

reward ourselves with a honeymoon that blew all our other trips

out of the water.

Our challenge was to save 80 per cent of our combined after-

tax

income. After rent it left us with about $200/month to live on. This

was a massive stretch for us, both financially and mentally. For the

Insufficient Funds

4

first time in our lives we were starting to earn decent money but we

couldn’t enjoy any of it.

Understand that all life decisions have

a money aspect to them.

This is one of those cases where money and life intersected in a big

way, but more important than money was the positive thinking and

self-

belief needed to make it work. It required a focus on achieving

our small goals and positively reinforcing that self-

belief that we

could get there.

As we saved hard for our wedding we also had to plan for it, book

venues, send invites and book the honeymoon. We also started

searching for our first home. I was negotiating simultaneously

with real estate agents and cake decorators. I quickly learned the

geography of Sydney as I visited clients who lived anywhere within

100 kilometres of where we lived, often arriving home very late at

night. Tash was completing her Master’s in Medical Science full

time as well as climbing the ladder in her 10-

to 12-

hour-

a-

day job.

These challenges taught us to be organised, support each other,

make the most of any spare time and not to sweat the small stuff.

More importantly, it taught us self-

belief and positivity. Without

these key ingredients, all the planning, efficiency, saving and

support in the world wouldn’t have meant squat.

Everyone longs for Sufficient Funds, but few actually achieve it,

mainly because they don’t believe in themselves, and small obstacles

turn into more couch time and less action.

Define — the missing step

5

We’ve had challenging times when mindset was just as crucial,

including fertility and health challenges, stepping through surgeries

and IVF, and helping our premmie newborn through major health

challenges in the first few months of his life. Mindset, above all else,

is what’s left when everything else is depleted.

From these real-

life experiences, here are my three super-

basic but

proven tips for framing your positive mindset for financial wellbeing:

1. Avoid negativity. You’ve heard this a thousand times. If

they’re not building you up, they’re bringing you down.

Remove the people in your life who bring you down or don’t

believe in you.

2. Keep your head up ( literally). Okay, hear me out on this

one. Without delving into any of the science behind this,

stand tall as a giraffe and keep your posture like that of a

soldier reporting for duty. Not only will it make you look

like you’re ready to take on the world, but it will also give

you the mindset of a champion. Because when you stand

tall and confident, you’ll feel like you can conquer any

challenge that comes your way, and achieve all the goals

you’ve set for yourself.

3. Create a series of small wins . Celebrate your small

financial victories and use these as fuel to propel yourself

towards the bigger goals. We’ll dive into your big goals

shortly. When we get there you’ll have a list. The first step

is to break that list down into much smaller daily tasks. Do

one thing every day to build momentum. Do this for a full

fortnight and it will blow your mind how far you’ve come.

Insufficient Funds

6

Self-

belief and positive thinking will give you the combination of

confidence and motivation you need to nail this chapter. Combine

this with a desire to learn and grow, and you’ll be unstoppable.

How to spend a billion dollars: find your

purpose and stay on it

Before you write down your big list you need to get clear on why

you’re on this Earth. Make sure you get the path right first, before

you set off chasing the dollars.

There’s a lot of content out there about finding your purpose in

order to live successfully. Simon Sinek made it famous through

the brilliant book Start with Why , and every guru out there now

trumpets doing what you love as a top tip for success.

So now we’re all fully aware that loving what you do means you’ll be

better at it, I want to share with you the fluff-

free way to find your

purpose and stay on track with it.

Start by getting crystal clear on your innate drivers. Take money off

the table. In fact, take any constraint off the table and allow yourself

to think about what you really want to do with the years you have on

this Earth. Big-

thinking billionaire Peter Diamandis says the way to

find your purpose is by answering these two questions:

1. What did you really want to be when you were a kid? (This

is what I mean by your innate drivers … )

Define — the missing step

7

2. If someone gave you a billion dollars, how would you spend

it and what would you do to improve the world? ( … and this

is removing the constraints.)

I believe the day you accept that you’ve become an adult and you

need to get realistic about your future endeavours, dial back your

dreams and live the life society has planned for you, is the day you

die inside. A bit dramatic? No way!

Diamandis explains that thinking about what you wanted to be as

a child and what you would do with a billion dollars can help you

identify your passions and the things you care about. By exploring

these questions, you gain insight into what drives you and what kind

of impact you want to make on the world. He is relating this to the

business world, and specifically to what kind of company you might

start to solve a big-

world problem, but we can apply this equally at a

personal level for our own achievements in our own lives.

The real kicker is question number 2. Pause on this for a second. A

billion dollars is more than you could spend on all the things you’ve

ever dreamed of. It’s more than you’d need for the house, jet, yacht,

all the travel, cars, and to never work again. You can have all of

this if you want it, but popping bottles and dropping thousands on

blackjack and private jets will get boring real quick, and you’ll still

have millions in the bank.

ACTIVITY

Find your purpose

Stop here and think about these two questions. Ultimately,

when money is no longer an issue, how will you keep yourself

( continued )

Insufficient Funds

8

Next, learn to live your life with an undying focus on this.

Once you find your purpose, the hard part is keeping it always front

of mind. Here are my tips for remaining on track:

1. Control your social media addiction

‘Social media is like crack,’ says Gary Vaynerchuk, ‘—

immediately

gratifying and hugely addictive.’ I admit, social media has taken a

lot of my time. It’s a bit of a catch-

22 for me, as I need it for business

and I enjoy it. We use it to build a community around what we’re

doing at Sufficient Funds, elevating our brand, sharing our clients’

stories and reaching more people.

interested, motivated, alive? Block some time in your calendar,

free yourself from all distractions, even go off grid to get clear,

then dive in and answer these questions. Some people find this

comes straight to them; others will need to do a massive brain

dump first. If that’s you, grab a pen and paper and let the stream

of consciousness flow.

Grasp that childhood dream or whatever is burning you up inside

and channel it. This is the fuel that will have you jumping all the

hurdles to create the life you want to live. Cast back to when life

and your dreams were completely free of money constraints.

Once you have your list, tidy it up and put it somewhere so you

can refer to it often. When we work through Defining Sufficient

with our clients we like to add images that relate to their goals 

— 

if

you’re a visual person absolutely do this and create yourself a

vision board that will help you stay on purpose.

Define — the missing step

9

I also waste a lot of time on it.

These platforms are built to pull you in and keep you there.

Understand that when you take your phone to the loo, or just have

that quick squiz at Insta to see if you’ve got any more likes on your

baby spam (guilty!), you lose more than just that short amount of

time. You lose your train of thought on the work you were doing and

drain some of the remaining focus you have for the day, making it

far more difficult to get back to the big stuff.

2. Say it out loud

Public accountability with the right people is hugely valuable.

Ever signed up for a fun run, told everyone you’re doing it, then had

to pull out? If you’re anything like me, you’d bend over backwards

to make sure you keep your word. Same goes for big goals. Tell your

friends, tell your family, tell your neighbours. Go ahead and tell

the barista at your local cafe. The last thing you need is to have to

change up your local coffee spot because you’ve made exactly zero

progress towards your goals. The more you say it out loud, the more

likely you are to follow through.

A word of warning: if you have a big crazy idea, don’t let it out of the

bag too early. Most people won’t yet be on your wavelength. Trying

to paint the vision of something that doesn’t exist yet to the wrong

people (who are probably your nearest and dearest) is a fast way to

having it shut down before you get started. You need at least a few

success points and a sense that it’s going to work to get you past the

naysayers when they hear about your secret mission.

Insufficient Funds

10

3. Learn to say no

If you’re anything like me you’ll see an opportunity to help, a new

business idea or something that seems like a lot of fun, everywhere

you look. You’ll find it incredibly challenging to have eight careers

or start multiple businesses all at once.

I’ve had to train myself to avoid shiny object syndrome by pausing

and holding the mirror up to see if it aligns with my values. Saying

no to anything that doesn’t align is imperative.

Remember that when you find your purpose, you’re working towards

the most fulfilling life you could possibly live. Anything that draws

you away from this needs to be treated with the kind of disdain

you’d direct at a used bandaid in a public pool.

4. Don’t compare

When you find your purpose, you gain the opportunity to live a life

true to that purpose. Nothing in the world is more valuable and

fulfilling than this.

We’ll dive into this in chapter 2, but be careful not to look next door

to see what your neighbour’s life looks like. They don’t have your

skills, your ideals or your purpose. What ultimately makes them

tick won’t be the same as what does it for you. Do yourself a favour

and leave them out of it!

Define — the missing step

11

Three steps to setting bigger

adventures (and how we get there

with our clients)

Constantly striving for bigger adventures is what makes me tick,

and helping others achieve this for themselves is why I do what I do

ACTIVITY

Start your Defining Sufficient list

Create a list of everything that’s coming up for you, and build this

into your grand list of goals and values for the foreseeable future.

My hot tip: keep it old school and use a pen and paper. It’s

crucial to have a physical copy that you can pin on a note board

or stick on the wall somewhere you’re going to see it regularly.

Add to this list as you read and work through the rest of

this chapter.

Note that this list is never set in concrete. It will need to remain

flexible as you grow and life happens, but starting now is crucial.

Note for couples: you will have individual goals as well as joint

and perhaps family goals. If you’re a couple who are planning a

life together I strongly recommend you join forces on this list.

But first spend 20 minutes individually making your list and then

use the time together to discuss it all. This is an important step

to ensure that each of you retains your individuality but that

you also have a chance to discuss upfront where your views

and values differ. This is an important step for jointly working

towards achieving Sufficient Funds.

Insufficient Funds

12

for a living. Here I want to give you some insider tips on how to do

this in three key steps.

When we kick off one of our Defining Sufficient sessions, I ask open-

ended questions about what you’re striving towards, with the goal

of understanding what makes you tick. It’s also a great way to gauge

how you feel about your current situation, as well as how confident

you are about your future and your ability to achieve the targets

you’ve set yourself.

These are not always easy questions to answer and over the years I’ve

noticed a strong recurring theme: we are uneasy talking about our

big ideas and far more comfortable listing the usual goals society

tells us we should strive for.

It starts with what you think I want to hear, which is usually one of

these four bad boys:

•

Pay off debt.

•

Save more.

•

Reduce tax.

•

Start investing.

Through no fault of your own, and mainly because our profession

has created this perception, this is the default position of almost

every new client. ‘He’s a financial adviser, so I’d better tell him

something financial.’

Define — the missing step

13

Often people start with the goal of buying a property. This is a

great goal to have if it really matters to you, but so often clients

can’t tell me why they want to do this. ‘Well, everyone does it, so

shouldn’t we?’

There’s that word: should .

Next comes the lesser material things: a new car, wardrobe, kitchen,

fence, coffee table …

These can be really important, and even impact your quality of life.

Typically you notice the things that are closest to you first. They are

okay as immediate needs and often take some deliberate saving to

acquire. Note that ticking some of these items off the list can also

help remove a few distractions and give you greater clarity on the

mindset you need to tick off the big things, but do it understanding

the impact of this on your overall financial situation, and again

ensure you are truly going to value it.

We’ve now made a shopping list of the relatively small items that

have been hanging around for some time. They’re a very valid part

of the conversation but we’re far from the gold at this point.

I mentioned my parents’ philosophy of ‘buying experiences, not

things’. Well, this meme has been overshared for a reason. Material

acquisitions don’t necessarily make us happy. They usually fulfil

a short-

term need and are quickly devalued, to be thrown out or

replaced down the track.

We’re usually about 25 minutes into the meeting by this point, and

this is where the discussion typically falters. I’ve got the financial

Insufficient Funds

14

stuff and your latest shopping list, but what comes next often takes

some serious prompting.

This is where the magic happens. Some would challenge the idea

that true goal-

setting is beyond the realm of financial advice but I

call total BS on this. Once you’re clear on your purpose and you’ve

put all thoughts of the dollars aside, you start to remember all of

the things that are important to you. If you don’t do this first, any

money plans will eventually fall over, or will not lead you to where

you really want to be.

To help you think past your immediate shopping list, I want to show

you what I’d typically suggest to clients when the time is right.

Here are my three steps to helping you achieve bigger adventures

and get more out of life.

Step 1: Deal with ‘you’

It can be uncomfortable imagining ourselves in a better position.

Over time the inevitable hurdles of life can chip away at our

confidence and ability to dream.

The good news is that this is temporary and reversible.

Make a short list of what you would call your strengths and

weaknesses; aim for three of each. Start with strengths, as these

are usually easier to bring to the surface. With weaknesses, think

about recent times you’ve failed to achieve something. Maybe you

thought about starting a business but didn’t get it off the ground, or

you failed to reach a weight-

loss goal or a savings target for a holiday

and you’re still paying off the credit card. What is it about you that

Define — the missing step

15

made these goals difficult? You don’t need to fix these areas in your

life but you need to be aware of them and to be honest with yourself

so you can work around it when the time comes.

This might make you uncomfortable, but if you don’t know yourself

well enough the next two steps will be fruitless. Take out your phone

or a pen and get started! If you get stuck, ask someone close to you,

your partner or a good friend, to help out.

I used the CliftonStrengths Top 5 Talent Assessment to find my

strengths. This test is used by the biggest companies in the world

to help their staff understand their talents and maximise their

potential. It’s not expensive and is well worth doing when you

consider the positive impact. You’ll wind up with a ranked list of

your top five strengths and plenty of detail on what it all means. You

can pay a bit more and get a full list of 34.

Far better to amplify your strengths than to get too caught up in

your weaknesses. Be aware of them, certainly; create strategies to

work around these weaknesses, work to complement your skills

and move on. You’ll already know your shortcomings, and rubbing

it in isn’t overly helpful. Put your strengths in the spotlight and

go for it!

Every time I see my list of strengths, they strike a chord. I know

they’re 100 per cent accurate, which also confirms why I love the

work I do.

You’ll find they’re relevant not only in your career or business, but

in everything you do. The process will give you massive confidence

when it comes to learning more about yourself and preparing you for

the next steps in this book. Remember, a key element of achieving

Insufficient Funds

16

Sufficient Funds isn’t stopping work forever, but enjoying the work

you do so you don’t feel the need to escape it.

Step 2: Think bigger

Now you have at least some of your key strengths down on paper

and you’ve thought about the weaknesses you want to avoid, it’s

time to leave the small things behind. Clear the runway, it’s time to

chase down your biggest ever hopes and dreams.

In his old-

school but still relevant book The Magic of Thinking Big ,

David Schwartz suggests, ‘Look at things not as they are, but as they

can be. Visualization adds value to everything. A big thinker always

visualizes what can be done in the future.’

This could be anything. I’m not going to tell you what to aim for,

but when you’re thinking about this stuff, it has to get the heart

pumping. Make sure it excites you. I might not roll out of bed for a

wet weekend caravanning in Tamworth, but I’d consider trading my

first-

born for a week heli-

skiing in the Canadian Rockies.

Your goals need to be big enough to give you the motivation to chase

them down. A good yardstick for this is, when you tell your family

about it, expect to get answers such as, ‘Why would you want to do

that?’ or ‘That sounds hard’ or ‘That’s too dangerous — you’re not a

risk taker’ or ‘How could you afford to do that?’

To prime your thinking, here are some examples I’ve loved hearing

from my clients:

•

Buy a yacht and sail the world for 12 months.

Define — the missing step

17

•

Rent an apartment in Barcelona for three months, become

fluent in Spanish and enjoy long weekends in Paris and the

Swiss Alps.

•

Take a family road trip around America in a Winnebago.

•

Take a career break to test out my dream of

becoming a chef.

•

Build a side-

hustle online based on my passion for

collecting Lego.

When you start to think bigger, you become wired that way. You

train your brain to challenge society’s norms and become a free

spirit, an individual (or couple or family) on a mission to smash

your goals.

Don’t forget to write these down too. If it’s not written down, it

won’t happen!

Step 3: Take action NOW

Take one of your big dreams and break it down. What is the one

thing you can do right now to move this forward? Do a five-

minute

web search for second-

hand yachts and get some quotes. Subscribe

to various airline sites to get across their upcoming sales or use a

Google flight hack (Google it!). Or find a blog about someone else

who has already done what you want to do, and reach out for advice.

For all the list makers out there, ask ChatGPT to make the list

for you. Feed it the goal (with all the specifics you already know)

Insufficient Funds

18

and ask it to provide you with a detailed 10-

step list of how to get

started. You might need to tweak it slightly for you, but it’s a great

place to start.

Do one thing each day for three days in a row, then watch the magic

happen. Momentum will build and before you know it you’ll be on

track to become the world’s first family to climb Mount Everest in

matching onesies!

‘The path to success is to take massive, determined action.’ Who

doesn’t love a good Tony Robbins quote? But don’t just think about

it — it’s time to act.

ACTIVITY

Three steps to bigger adventures

Stop now and take 30 minutes to work through the following

three steps:

1. Make a list of your strengths and weaknesses.

2. Write down one big goal that really sets your

heart pumping.

3. Take one small action right now to move you towards

this goal. Once done, set your intention for the next

small actions that you’ll complete tomorrow and the next

day. Continue this for a full fortnight and you’ll be well

on your way!

Add this new big goal to the Defining Sufficient list you started in

the previous activity.

Define — the missing step

19

Experiences or things — why can’t

I have both?

We’ve touched on this already, and it’s guaranteed to pop up as

a recurring theme as you continue to define your Sufficient life.

‘Buy experiences not things’ is a popular meme for good reason.

Choosing materialism (more possessions) over experiencing what

the world has to offer is a terrible waste. Minimalism is trending

and no one wants to be the hoarder on the block.

Most people tend to naturally favour one over the other, and many

couples I work with are learning the art of compromise to allow

for both in their lives. Of course, experiences and things are not

mutually exclusive, and sometimes you need to just chill out and

run with whatever gets you going at that point in time.

One thing I’ll never do is tell you there is only one way to live your

life. What tickles you in all the right places is none of my business.

I can provide all the guidance in the world and ask challenging

questions to help you get there, but in the end it’s all about you.

The best financial advisers and life coaches I know always remain

impartial. When it comes to experiences and/or things, you do you.

Following this process, either solo or with a partner, will demand

that you consider where your values lie. Just remember that wherever

you end up is fine.

Knowing this will help you navigate the twists and turns on the road

to Sufficient Funds and accelerate towards your goals with confidence.

Insufficient Funds

20

The case for experiences

It’s hard to hide my bias here. We are well and truly sold on

the case for experiences, and I’m sure many of you are as well.

Experiences are number one for me. They’re the stuff my dreams

are made of.

My objectives are heavily oriented towards experience, and they

are broad. From trying something new on the weekend and mixing

up our family activities, to as much global travel as we can get, we

find our eyes are opened by experiencing all that comes with a new

destination, seeing different ways of life and points of view.

Experiences don’t have to relate to travel. They could involve

learning a new skill, like cooking or a foreign language, trying your

hand at painting or photography, or spending six months building

towards a fitness goal, like competing in a triathlon.

Note some of the above involve the purchase of things, but these

purchases are a means to an end, rather than the goal itself.

The rise of the sharing economy allows the more hardcore on this

side of the fence, which we are not, to forgo owning a house, car,

bike or boat, instead directing all funds to real-

life moments. These

are interesting times we live in.

The case for things

Friends of ours recently purchased an obscenely expensive sound

system for their house. They have other goals, a mortgage and

Define — the missing step

21

a love for travel, but being musos and spending a lot of time at

home, a high-

quality sound system was just the thing to enhance

their lifestyle.

The message here: don’t let the meme screw with your reality.

Our family spends 75 per cent of our lives eating, sleeping, living and

working in the ‘thing’ that Tash and I saved to purchase together.

We’ve upgraded our home twice since that first purchase and we

wouldn’t have it any other way. Don’t hesitate to allocate funds

towards things that enhance your quality of life. The only caveat:

make sure there’s a purpose, a clear benefit, and that it fits with

everything else you want to achieve.

For many, working towards their goals accounts for a big chunk of

their time. If, like us, you have bigger targets for yourself, chances

are you’ll do better if home is a place of comfort where you can wind

down and enjoy all the things that make you happy. There’s nothing

wrong with that.

Spending funds on material things that enhance your life

experience — the home itself, car, backyard office/granny flat for

working from home, an infrared sauna, a serious mattress to ensure

quality shuteye — these are totally cool. As I said, if it makes your

life more Sufficient, go nuts.

For the most part, experiences and things go together. Give yourself

permission to run with or against the herd, or dangle your legs

either side of the fence for a while. Just make sure you’re doing it for

you and no one else.

Insufficient Funds

22

It’s not meant to be

easy — be prepared to work

Sometimes I think back to our story of selling Insufficient Funds

T-

shirts and dreaming of it becoming our multimillion-

dollar baby.

It was all about the fairy tale of what success looked like.

I was in Yamba with family sometime after the big US road trip. The

founder of Billabong had recently built a mansion up the road in

Angourie. I imagined his life of surfing, partying and travelling the

world with mates, not the work he did and continued to do to get

there. The idea of selling T-

shirts to create the world we wanted to

live gave me chicken skin (yep, that’s the emotional side that helps

me dream big).

What I’ve learned since 2004, though, is that action beats

everything, and dreams alone won’t get you far. In fact, they’ll cloud

your judgement if you let them take over. It took me a long time to

figure this out.

In my early career I spent several years grinding it out and learning

the ropes. I realised very early on that there was a big difference

between those who made it to a management role and those who

settled in the trenches and were destined for minimal pay rises for

the rest of their lives.

Simon Sinek hadn’t yet given his famous TED talk, YouTube and

life-

hacking hadn’t arrived, so we were stuck with ‘work hard, learn

lots, get promoted, earn more’.

Define — the missing step

23

I was straight out of uni and there were people in their 40s being

managed by those in their 20s.

I knew where I needed to be.

Set lofty goals and maintain a strong work ethic

Tash and I had set ourselves some fairly lofty income goals when

we first moved in together in 2005, including six-

figure salaries

by 30. It became a bit of a competition. I now see this with clients all

the time. Starting out on $35k each after uni, 3 per cent p.a. wasn’t

going to cut it.

Tash completed her Master’s while working full time. I was driving

up to 100 km from the office to meet clients, sometimes getting

home well after midnight, before starting back in the CBD at

7.30 am the next day.

We started climbing the ladder and both of us achieved our income

goal by age 27. We didn’t set out with an intentional work ethic, but

looking back, our work ethic was a key factor in getting us there.

Work smarter AND harder

These days, as I build my financial services businesses, I’m looking

for all the shortcuts available to streamline processes and become

more efficient.

As advisers, our strength is in talking to clients, building

relationships with them so they have the confidence to share their

Insufficient Funds

24

dreams and we can then work together with them on their biggest

money decisions. This is what we enjoy, and we’re very good at it.

It’s easy to get bogged down in all the paperwork that is inherent in

this type of work. I’ve learned that the best way to avoid this is by

practising pseudo-

laziness: ‘How can I remove myself from this to

make it better.’

If my strength is in working directly with my clients, coaching my

team and promoting the amazing work we’re doing, I need to look

at everything else as a complete waste of my time. This is why our

clients don’t just get to know me, or our other financial advisers; they

get to know our team members. There are obviously many benefits

to us and our clients because of this, none more so than my not

getting bogged down in the tasks that are not in my list of strengths,

allowing me to focus on the value-

adding conversations and Money

Action Plans (MAP) ™ that we’re privileged to be delivering.

Here are my tips for being smarter when it comes to tackling tasks

on the way to achieving Sufficient Funds:

•

Leverage technology. Good tech is cheap — often

free — and allows us to automate repetitive tasks. Just as

you will learn to do with your money in the next chapter,

automation helps you free your time for more impactful or

creative work.

•

Prioritise. Not all tasks are created equal. It’s good to

have a to-

do list but ensure that it’s leading you to the big

outcomes you’re seeking to achieve. Then, crucially, break

the tasks into 15-

to 20-

minute items and work on only one

thing at a time.

Define — the missing step

25

•

Embrace ‘no’. Learning to decline requests that don’t align

with my biggest goals or with my values remains an ongoing

challenge for me. I’m partial to bright, shiny objects, but

I’ve pushed myself to be better in this area and protect

my calendar as ultimately it’s the only way to progress as

quickly as you’ll need to when setting meaningful and

significant goals.

•

Plan your downtime. This is my favourite. When on a

mission, whether it’s building a business or striving for

other massive milestones in your life, you need to have

regular breaks to ensure you stay fresh and energised. You

know that feeling you get at the start of January, ready to

tackle a new year? Well, regular breaks throughout the year

will help you rinse and repeat so you’ll never simply flop

into Christmas again.

As you hack your way to freedom, don’t forget that this isn’t about

becoming idle; it’s about creating time and the headspace to double

down on your strengths.

Combining this with hard work will mean you leapfrog those who

haven’t figured this out yet, or are too stuck in their ways to act on

it, and move swiftly towards the outcomes you seek.

Push the boundaries

Walt Disney said, ‘If you can dream it, you can do it.’ Don’t

settle. Don’t assume what you were capable of achieving last year is

all you will be able to achieve in the year ahead. Be prepared to take

risks and get comfortable being uncomfortable.

Insufficient Funds

26

Forget everyone else, be the tall poppy — this is about your personal

growth. These ideas are relevant to business owners and employees

alike. If you don’t embrace the importance of having a strong work

ethic early, you’ll miss all of the upside of being young and the

opportunity to set yourself up for Sufficient Funds sooner.

This is your time to take risks and push the boundaries of what you

think you’re capable of, but none of it will pay off without periods

of consistent hard work and long hours in pursuit of your dreams.

Get stuck in.

Buying happiness in Kuwait, and why you need

challenge in your life

One time at a conference I had the pleasure of hearing a keynote

from peak performance researcher Adam Fraser.

During his talk Dr Fraser spoke about how he was hired by the

Kuwaiti government to help make the country happier. The talk

had a number of focus points but this one stuck out, so I did

some digging.

It turns out that Kuwait has had an amazing history of resilience

and innovation. At the same time, they have amassed great wealth

from their three main industries, banking, telco and of course oil.

It’s well understood that in recent times their solution to almost

every problem has been to throw cash at it, the prime focus being

keeping the Kuwaiti nationals happy. Citizens enjoy many benefits

(not available to foreign nationals), including interest-

free housing

Define — the missing step

27

loans, free education and healthcare, and low-

cost land. In 2011

they were given free food for 13 months!

This all sounds pretty good, right?

Wrong. As Dr Fraser explained, one result of their extreme privilege

was a deep sense of entitlement. He recounted how it’s not unusual

to see families hanging out at the beach on a mid-

week afternoon

instead of working, and to see 18-

year-

olds cruising around in Rolls-

Royces and Bentleys. They are given or can purchase whatever they

need or want yet despite this overall happiness levels have declined.

It turns out that removing life’s challenges, imagining this would

make everyone happier, has in fact had the opposite effect.

There are some key lessons we can all take away from this on the

road to Sufficient Funds.

BEING TOO COMFORTABLE MAY HAVE A NEGATIVE IMPACT

If you’re left not wanting for anything, you are unlikely to try very

hard. It is for this reason that wealthy parents need to teach their

kids how to grow their own wealth and make their own way in the

world, regardless of what they may be set to inherit.

HAVING A CHALLENGING GOAL TO STRIVE TOWARDS IS KEY

TO REMAINING MOTIVATED

This is why I’ve highlighted the need to think big when setting

your goals. Set them at a level that will really push you. If you’re not

motivated, you’re unlikely to jump any hurdles as they arise.

Insufficient Funds

28

YOUR SENSE OF SELF-WORTH DEPENDS ON OVERCOMING

CHALLENGES

Toddlers are great for highlighting this. Their rate of growth is

exponential. We watch them learn to crawl, walk, talk, feed them

selves, swim, ride a bike and countless other new tricks, it’s crazy to

see them gain the confidence they need and move on to the next thing.

Our kids as toddlers had bumps and bruises all over as they were

constantly falling over, colliding with the furniture and throwing

things at each other. This is really tough but we’ve always tried not to

be ‘helicopter parents’ in the hope of building their resilience. Even

before they hit three years old we were seeing massive confidence

building as a result. Sure, they fall down and cry every now and

then, but a few scratches are only going to strengthen them for the

years to come. It’s kind of cool to see this playing out as they grow,

especially in their willingness to try new things and not shy away

from challenges. As Tony Robbins puts it, ‘progress equals happiness’.

This is true for adults too, but as we ‘settle down’ (urgh!), our growth

can be much slower and we’re more likely to become set in our ways.

This is why so many people who win the lotto end up struggling.

They skipped all the hurdles that are part of accumulating

financial assets.

The Kuwait example shows us how unhappy we could become if

we were to rely on someone else to dictate our future. If you think

someone else will do it for you, or that is your plan, it will likely

end in tears.

The major lesson here: you create your own future. Use this chapter

to do exactly that.

29

Sufficiently Defined

In this chapter:

■

■

You’ve set your positive mindset for financial wellbeing,

including setting your series of small wins to build

momentum around good financial decisions. Do one thing

every day for a full fortnight.

■

■

You’ve started and built on your very own Defining

Sufficient list! Remember it’s a moving beast, so keep it

close and keep building on it.

■

■

You’ve weighed up what you’d do if you were totally

financially free and asked yourself how those dreams fit

with your purpose in life.

■

■

You’ve identified one big adventure or goal you’re planning

to tackle first, and you have set this in motion by ticking off

the first few simple steps to make it happen.

■

■

You’ve taken time out from your day-to-day to define

what a fulfilling and successful life looks like to you, and

you have a clear list of what goals will make up your

Sufficient life.

You’ve now worked through some important steps that so many

unwittingly skip on their financial planning journey. This is where I

see so many fail and why our clients, who always start here, get

off to a flying start!

Massive congrats! You now have a solid understanding of your

definition of Sufficient Funds. Keep this front of mind as we step

through the next steps of decluttering your finances.

Insufficient Funds

32

crap to get in the way right when we’re ready to leap. Life’s much

better when our finances are fully decluttered.

In this chapter we’ll first explore the critical importance of having

a clear mindset, then you’ll get super practical with some easy-

to-

follow steps to gain a better understanding of your financial position

and ensure it all flows. Follow these steps and you’ll be well on your

way to achieving financial clarity and taking control of your money.

Clarity: attitude and focus

It’s widely reported that money is the biggest source of stress in

the world. The American Psychological Association (APA), and the

Australian Psychological Society (APS), which produces the annual

National Stress and Wellbeing in Australia Survey, report that

personal finances and concern around rising costs of everyday items

is leading to significant stress and more serious health issues. The

APA reports that money concerns were even higher than concerns

around global uncertainty in 2022, despite its being a year full of

pandemic stress and nuclear threats.

If you’re constantly stressed about money, you’ll find it difficult

to be motivated and positive about your future, and without this

motivation you won’t get far. To reach Sufficient Funds and beyond,

you need clarity and confidence. After many years of working with

clients to create this, I’ve seen the magic that ensues once you get it

right, and I want to share this with you.

Clarity gives you confidence, which builds momentum and puts you

in your flow state, where you are untouchable. We want you to create

a system for your money that will free you from distraction, one

Declutter — clearing the path

33

that ensures you can navigate difficult times, changes in markets

and family emergencies seamlessly. In turn, it will help you build

towards the good times that you’re striving for: more free time,

the opportunity to explore the world, do meaningful and fulfilling

work, start a family, help those in need …

This money system is free of clutter, because it remains focused

solely on what it needs to do, so your money plan starts to facilitate

the life you want to live. The core of your system is what we call

Cruise Control: Your Spending Plan.

We’ll get to this shortly, but first it’s important to get your head

in the game.

Attitude: when it comes to income, it’s not size

that matters

There’s a big difference between earning lots and having lots.

I’ve been self-

employed since 2015. I resigned from my well-

paid

corporate gig right after we bought our dream home and took out a

mortgage that really stretched us. I then started a business with no

clients. Looking back on it, we didn’t have a fucking clue what we

were doing at the start, but we survived.

I think a lot in terms of business, but the truth of the matter is that

a business and your personal money flow aren’t all that different.

Even though revenue (think total sales or total income) is often

a measure of success for a business, it’s a false measure as it

tells only part of the story. A better yardstick is profit, or even

better, cashflow. You can generate lots of income but if you aren’t

charging appropriately or you have a bloated staff base or other

Insufficient Funds

34

cost inefficiencies, there’ll be little to no profit left and your

business will run out of cash.

Think about your personal money life in the same way. Your salary

is your revenue. Your profit is the money left over after all your

spending. Success isn’t in your $50k, $150k or $300k salary. This is

only part of the equation. Many of the people I work with earn half

as much as the big earner and still save more.

There’s a tunnel vision that takes over when life revolves around

‘make money, spend money’, and there’s not much light at the end

of it. But once you’re in the tunnel, it can be hard to find the exit.

It’s addictive. Why? Because the act of spending itself becomes the

‘reward’. So you put in the hard yards just for the joy of spending

the big bucks, not necessarily for what you are left with at the end

of the day.

When Tash and I were in our late 20s we were working long,

stressful hours but the money was good. Those Insufficient Funds

ATM slips were a distant memory and we’d made the shift from our

uni days when it was all time and no money to the polar opposite.

After funding the wedding we made a great start by purchasing our

first home and an investment property within 18 months, but we

didn’t have the mental capacity or, more important, the systems in

place to make good financial decisions.

We did a fair bit of what I would call binge spending. There were

expensive overseas trips, business-

class flights, luxury resort stays,

and lots of eating out and takeaways. With no time to think, we

made money decisions on the fly, with little or no consequences if

we overspent as we could rely on being paid again next fortnight.

Declutter — clearing the path

35

Some would think we had it made, we were walking on air, but in

truth we look back on those times and think, geez we’re glad we

woke up when we did. We had to shift our mindset from head in

the sand, spend every dollar to really understanding what we valued

and consciously not allowing ourselves to ‘waste’ any excess.

Shifting this mindset changed our world. Being aware of the money

coming in and money going out sounds like a simple concept, but it’s

less so when you remove time and consequence from the equation.

As in an episode of Hoarders , it’s scarily easy to create such a mess

that you truly have no idea what lies beneath the surface.

Working hard, earning lots and having an abundance of financial

resources is a great objective, and will let you do some pretty cool

shit, but this only works when linked to your definition of Sufficient

and when your spending aligns with this.

On the flipside, if you’re already truly enjoying the work you do,

then you should recognise that the grass is usually not greener on

the other side. You may not be earning all the money in the world,

but that’s okay. You have something that a lot of people can only

ever dream of. Stop and reflect on this. It’s worth a lot more than

you might think.

Focus

I meditate most days, and have done for the past few years, often

using the Headspace app. This app is split into a bunch of different

sections based on what you’re trying to deal with at the time

(confidence, stress, appreciation, anxiety, balance and so on). One

I find myself frequently returning to is called ‘Finding Focus’. In

this part, the instructor, Andy, talks about the idea of innate focus

Insufficient Funds

36

always being with us. My take on this is that instead of having to

create this for yourself and then struggle to ensure you don’t lose it

again, you can have the confidence to accept that it’s always there for

you to tap into. As Andy says, it’s kind of like knowing that the blue

sky is always there and although it can become hidden or distorted

by clouds, if you always remember it’s there, then you instantly feel

better and it’s easier to manage distractions.

This concept can be readily applied to decluttering your finances.

If the definition of declutter is to remove unnecessary items

from an untidy or overcrowded place, it can equally apply to

your overcrowded mind when you need to focus: right now that

overcrowded place is where you are making your day-

to-

day money

decisions. Think about your bank accounts, credit cards and any

debts. By simplifying your money and decluttering you free up

more headspace and reduce stress.

A sustained focus is key to remaining on track. Understand that you

have an innate ability to focus with clarity on your money decisions.

You just need the time, space and willpower to do it.

To be clear, by decluttering I’m not saying you need to remove

money from your world. Quite the opposite. You need a system that

ensures that every cent you earn flows into the right place with as

little effort as possible.

Decluttering every aspect of your life allows you to be more

productive and creative. You waste less time, spend more time on

things that are meaningful for you and feel healthier.

Now let’s get practical!

Declutter — clearing the path

37

Build your financial launchpad

Let’s put the LeBaron in the garage for a hot minute — it’s time to

talk rockets.

When building a house you don’t start with all the fancy bits. As

nice as it might sound, all the good stuff, like putting the pool in,

dropping the free-

standing bath into the new ensuite, or kicking

back with a Corona by the fire pit and sliding freshly kneaded

dough into the outdoor pizza oven, doesn’t come first. These are the

cherries on top once all the work has been done.

Basics first. It’s time to build your financial launchpad!

For most of us, school didn’t teach us a single thing about money

and sadly, for the same reason I’m writing this book, a lot of parents

aren’t equipped to teach their kids either.

The money stuff tends to get messy quickly. It’s not uncommon for

us to see a 25-

year-

old with a bit of personal debt here, some savings

over there, a micro-

investing account, some random shares, and of

course plans to buy property. In fact, it’s quite rare to meet someone

who hasn’t gone straight for the pizza oven, before laying the bricks

and putting the roof on.

A side note: You’re never too old to get this part right, so even if you’re

55 and don’t have it all sorted and working for you yet, do not skip this!

Your launchpad is your starting point, your clear runway. It’s the

foundations of your money house that support everything else you’re

going to do. A robust launchpad will also help you accelerate anything

else you build on top.

Insufficient Funds

38

Here are the three components of your launchpad:

1. Dealing with debt. Start with a new rule: no personal debt .

This includes credit card and lifestyle debt; some loans

(such as for car and house) are okay.

2. Cruise Control: Your Spending Plan. We’ve been using

this system personally and with our clients for many years

now. Done right, it will put your basic money sitch on

steroids and help you keep more of what you earn and make

far more confident day-

to-

day money decisions. This one is

a game changer.

3. Protection plan. WTF is this? It’s life insurance and

income protection. Chapter 4 covers this in more detail,

but I’m dripping this one in slowly to save you from

closing the book, skipping away and burying your head

in the sand.

Once you have these sorted you can then run out and tackle all the

big things. Go nuts!

I’m keeping this light but it will give you the tools and a few ideas on

how to get there more quickly.

Dealing with debt

Let’s face it, personal debt can be overwhelmingly stressful. I’m

referring here to what is loosely known as ‘bad debt’. Whether it’s

credit cards, personal loans or both, the feeling of owing money can

leave us feeling trapped and anxious. The good news is there are

Declutter — clearing the path

39

steps you can take to get back in control of your finances and start

feeling confident again.

In this chapter we explore some practical tips and strategies that can

help you tackle your debt and keep rolling towards Sufficient Funds!

The good ol’ snowball vs avalanche

There are two commonly known methods for smashing multiple

debts such as credit cards and personal loans. The debt avalanche

involves making minimum payments on all debt, then using any

remaining money to pay off the debt with the highest interest rate. The

debt snowball involves paying off the smallest debts first to get them

out of the way before moving on to the bigger ones (see figure 2.1).

The best method for you depends on whether you’re driven

by behaviour and reward (snowball) or pure financial benefit

(avalanche). Chances are it’s the former. You’ll save more interest

with the avalanche but this doesn’t help if you feel like you’re getting

nowhere chipping away at what might also be the biggest debt and

therefore the slowest to kill.

SNOWBALL

AVALANCHE

Figure 2.1: Smashing debt: snowball vs avalanche

Insufficient Funds

40

The snowball will work better if you’re an achiever who likes to

tick off milestones. Hitting the smallest debt first will remove

it from your life, and you’ll have fewer payments to worry about

moving forward.

If I had to lean in one direction, I’d opt for the snowball as most

money issues stem from behaviour and, fundamentally, just staring

at the numbers and relying on this only works for a select few of us

(definitely not me!).

Debt disruption strategies: creative

ways to pay off debt

If you’ve taken the approach with your bank accounts that so long

as you don’t log in all will be fine, make today the day you lift up

the bonnet and take a look. Ignorance is not bliss when it comes to

your money, or lack thereof. I’ve seen this all too often. You’re far

better off dealing with it now, so read on. I’m confident this chapter

will provide you with the rocket fuel to smash any debts. No more

boring debt reduction plans. Time to get creative and, I dare say,

even enjoy the process of smashing those bills!

There are plenty of traditional methods and advice for paying

off debt, most of which have some value. You’ve heard them

all before: create a budget, spend less than you earn, cut up that

inessential credit card, earn more, make higher repayments, set up

forced savings, pay the highest interest rate first, automate your

repayments, consolidate your debts … 

I’ve spent more than a decade helping people with these types of

strategies, and with the right mindset and consistency they do

Declutter — clearing the path

41

work, but none of them are very exciting or creative. Often the best

strategy for paying off debt is to keep it interesting, to shake things

up. I want to show you some ways to make this happen.

This is by no means an all-

encompassing list, but here’s some

less conventional, sometimes even controversial ways to get you

thinking more creatively about paying off debt and freeing yourself

from this mess.

Find some quick wins

Quick wins give you a feeling of accomplishment and this positive

reinforcement helps you to develop positive habits. They keep

you motivated to continue along your path and push through

difficult barriers.

Develop a habit with a series of quick wins. This will help you

build the foundations of staying on top of your finances and make

it seem effortless.

Foil the fraudsters

This is huge yet most of the peeps aren’t doing it. Check all

your credit and debit card statements for bank or merchant

errors as well as fraud. I usually do this about once a month. I

go back through every item and make sure I know what it was.

I’ve wrongfully (generously?) paid for all sorts of things on my

credit card, from a women-

only gym membership in Brisbane to

a Chinese restaurant in Mexico City and, most recently, someone

else’s phone bill. It’s happened to me at least 10 times over the past

few years, and this checking exercise alone has helped me claw

back more than $4000.

Insufficient Funds

42

Quick search for double-ups

List your regular payments. Okay, I threw in one really boring

one for good measure. I suggest you painstakingly go through the

past three months of all your accounts. List all the regular debits/

payments. The main objective here is to get an idea of how much is

really leaving your account every month and becoming conscious of

what those items are.

Chances are you’ll find items in the same category that you’re

doubling up on. For example, I was given a free Apple Music

subscription for 18 months last time I upgraded my phone (thanks

Telstra!). However, we were already paying for Spotify, which offers

a very similar service. The same goes for Foxtel, Stan, Netflix, Apple

TV and Disney+! What other apps are you paying for that you

don’t use?

Start a side-hustle

You’ve got 24 hours a day. Time to turn off the Kardashians and

hustle like a momager! Do some freelance writing, drive for Uber,

be a maths tutor or an online dating consultant (they exist!) — there

are millions of ideas here. Get off the couch and use the time you’ve

been given. Any extra cash can go straight to paying off your debt.

Lose the gym membership

This is one of the biggest but most underutilised expenses in my

clients’ budgets. There are cheaper ways to exercise. The ocean is

my gym but if that’s not your vibe, go for a run, use the gym at the

park or Google outdoor or home gym exercise ideas. For some people

the gym is non-

negotiable, which is cool. But if you choose to spend

Declutter — clearing the path

43

money in one particular area, make sure you seriously value it.

Ramit Sethi, who’s a true genius when it comes to personal money

coaching, advocates saving mercilessly on the items that don’t mean

anything to you, so you can then spend wildly on the one or two

that do. If the gym is your solace and safe place for staying fit, then

go for it! Just make sure it’s intentional and you review it every

now and then.

Utilise the sharing economy

Airbnb your home, even if you’re renting. If you have a spare room or

two, make the most of it. Do this permanently, or at least whenever

you go on holidays, even if it’s just a long weekend visiting family.

You have to be a bit organised but it’s all worth it. We’ve done this

with our place a few times. One year it funded almost an entire

three-

week trip to the US!

Share your car. There are a bunch of great sharing sites like Uber

Carshare (previously Car Next Door) that are super easy to use and

a great way to earn some extra coin from your gas guzzler. Better

still, sell your car and use Go Get or another sharing service. I have

a few clients who use this and absolutely rave about it.

If you haven’t written out all your expenses, scan the QR code on

page 48 and we’ll send you our template. It will prompt all of this

and be the starting point for your spending plan, coming up soon.

Move back home

Your parents will kill me, but I have definitely seen many people

create this win to avoid rising rents and allow for enough surplus

Insufficient Funds

44

either to significantly reduce debt or to build up a savings buffer.

Just make sure it’s a temporary move. I didn’t write this book for

45-

year-

olds who enjoy sitting on their arses. Your independence

matters more in the long run, but paying off debt is a short-

term

issue so deal with it first. Plus, who doesn’t love Mum’s lasagne!

Negotiate a remote/virtual work arrangement and

drop the commute

At Sufficient Funds we run what Matt Mullenweg of Wordpress

fame would call a distributed business. We’re not strictly ‘remote’, as

this would imply we have a head office with staff working remotely

from HQ. These days I have no interest in having a shiny office in

the big smoke. Our team of awesome humans all work from home,

some globally, and we freakin’ love it. We’re now conducting 100

per cent of our meetings via video. This allows us to work with

driven young peeps all over Australia, and they don’t need to leave

their homes!

It also means we can live wherever we want to and still be doing

the work we love, simultaneously showing our kids how others live,

letting them learn from these new ways, and giving them an insight

into the amazing diversity on this planet.

Businesses globally were forced by the pandemic into being open to

this concept. You get more done in less time, save on travel costs and

create more flexibility around important family tasks like childcare.

What’s more, you’re allowed to open the windows without being

concerned about someone else’s climate-

controlled nightmare, and

PJs (even pants off Fridays!) are fully permitted.

Declutter — clearing the path

45

Money nerd talking: you might also get to claim some of your rent

or mortgage as tax deductible, but get appropriate tax advice from

a good accountant.

We live in a global society. Just as many others have done before

you, embrace it and see where it takes you.

Live somewhere cheaper

City living is ridiculously expensive in comparison to regional areas.

Either commute further (and spend the travel time on your side-

hustle or listening to podcasts!), work remotely or set up a virtual

business like ours, so you can be location independent and remove

the impulse spending distractions that are so prevalent in big cities.

Don’t cut the holiday — turn it into a savings

opportunity

Everyone needs regular breaks to relax, dream bigger and reset. In

line with your definition of Sufficient, think about what you need

for a holiday to be enjoyable and tick your true value boxes. This

might involve finding cheaper places to travel, getting away from

the five-

star resorts that may have got you into this mess in the first

place. Staying in hostels can be a great way to meet people and see

the world.

Planning ahead and booking your holidays 12 to 18  months in

advance can score you some serious deals, leaving more money in

your pocket to spend on experiences and creating memories that last

a lifetime. Time to lock in that Icelandic adventure. Thank me later!

Insufficient Funds

46

ACTIVITY

Disrupt your debts

Take one hour to act on the practical tips above. Grab your laptop

and review all of your transactional bank account statements,

focusing on ‘foiling fraudsters’ and ‘finding double-

ups’. This

will give further insight into any other expenses you could be

removing from your life.

I’ve given you a few other ideas to help you get creative around

this. Spend some time thinking about how all of these or other

ideas specific to your life could work to disrupt your debt and

bring you back onto the path to Sufficient Funds.

Note: If you’re in a serious mess financially and you’ve tried all

of the above, then it’s time to speak to a financial counsellor.

There are some free options out there that do amazing work and

can definitely point you in the right direction. In Australia, start

with the Commonwealth Government’s Moneysmart site or the

National Debt Helpline. You can also try local councils in metro

areas or many charities who are set up to assist, such as the

Salvation Army or the Smith Family.

Cruise Control: Your Spending Plan

Your spending plan is hands down the most crucial part to get

right. An effective spending plan has two key elements: the right

behaviour and the right system.  In Atomic Habits , author James

Clear notes, ‘You do not rise to the level of your goals, you fall to the

level of your systems.’

Declutter — clearing the path

47

When striving for flow we need as little friction as possible. This

means building systems for money decisions and maintaining pure

clarity on how those decisions link to your best life. It also means

you don’t second guess a thing. You need the tools to make quick,

confident, intentional decisions, and move on.

There’s no room here for dwelling on the past and getting stuck on

the negatives. Your success is predicated on your ability to progress.

I’m going to show you a structure and foolproof system that works

for all the awesome clients we get to work with every day, and why it

is the basis of all successful financial plans.

The four key components to ‘Cruise Control: Your Spending Plan’ are:

•

Budget

•

Categorise

•

Accounts

•

Automate.

Budget

It starts with that dirty B word. There’s no doubt this is the reason so

many people fail at the first hurdle of sorting their money out. Don’t

sweat, I’m on your page with this! I’ve already made my disdain for

extreme frugality very clear and I promise I’m here to make this

palatable for you. So stay with me, because this is the next crucial

step to achieving Sufficient Funds.

Insufficient Funds

48

A budget  allows you to understand your ‘cost of living’. To be

financially successful, and to fast-

track your journey to Sufficient,

you need to know what it costs to be you. One thing’s for sure:

when I keep a budget I have more money, even though I’m not

earning any more.

I’ll never tell you what to spend your money on; however, it’s

about being conscious of what’s coming and going, and more than

anything it’s about aligning your spending with your values.

One benefit of spending the time upfront defining Sufficient and

encouraging you to think bigger is that motivation and clarity

make the whole idea of budgeting so much easier to stomach. Once

you nail this part you’ll see how to build the plan that brings it

all together!

ACTIVITY

Complete your budget template

Scan the QR code to download the budget

template. This will prompt everything for you.

Spend 20 to 30 minutes completing this. Most

of it will be fixed costs that you will already

know or can easily find in your statements; the

rest you’ll need to give some thought to.

Bonus tip: Here’s exactly what we tell clients when they com

plete this with us:  fill this with everything you think you’re

spending at the moment, plus anything you wish you could

be spending money on! If there’s anything missing in your life that

you want more of, add it into the budget and let’s work together

to make it happen! We can always reduce it later if needed.

Declutter — clearing the path

49

Categorise

I’m not a fan of over-

engineering things. You’re here to declutter

and you don’t need 1000 bank accounts.

At the same time, though, the super-

simple, one account for all

income, expenses and savings is just as bad in my opinion. One

account and one credit card generally isn’t enough. You want clarity

over your costs and an easy way to see how you’re progressing

between pays without tracking every cent you spend.

ACTIVITY

Get comfortable talking about spending

money … like, today!

If you’re a couple and have shared income, bank accounts,

expenditure, make sure you have made the time and effort to

get on the same page about money.

Ideally this came up naturally when you defined Sufficient, but

if you’re just now starting to get on the same page with your

budget, you’re going to want to start with aligning your spending

philosophies. I have seen people avoid completing their budget,

revisiting their budget or even looking at their bank accounts as

they don’t want to either start arguments or divulge spending

they think their partner might not be on board with. We’re all

human and we all have different wants and needs. Talk it out and

don’t let this be the thing that sets you back.

If all else fails, agree to disagree on selected budget items,

but know what that means for your financial position and your

ongoing comfort level. As Jim Carrey said, ‘Behind every great

man is a woman rolling her eyes.’

Insufficient Funds

54

specific advice like this to a very diverse readership is that it will

inevitably miss the mark with most.

A Sufficient emergency fund has just enough. Too little is risky, too

much means you’re missing opportunities to invest or enjoy more

of your hard-

earned.  If you’re single with a secure income, two

months of living costs might be fine. If you’re newly self-

employed

or in a highly volatile contractual role, with young kids and a solid

mortgage, you might want to up it to six months or even a whole

year of expenses.

I like nice round numbers, so whether it’s $5000 or $100 000 make it

an easy number and don’t overthink. Crucially, I want you to adapt

a mindset around your emergency fund that it’s not your money!

Please understand what this fund represents: it’s money you never

touch except in a real financial emergency. Don’t think of it as

future investment funds or some extra dosh for the next furniture

upgrade. Tuck it away, even at a separate bank if you need to, so it’s

well and truly out of sight, out of mind.

A real emergency might be that you lose your job, you face big and

urgent medical costs, the family business slows right down, you find

yourself between contracts for much longer than expected, or your

parents or kids find themselves stuck overseas.

For us, our son Eden spent his first three months in and out

of hospital. He was born only 11 days after our SF business was

launched. Tash had deferred her employer’s parental leave (for tax

purposes, of course) and we had to park everything, lay low and

spend another three months picking up the pieces before it all

started to flow again.

Declutter — clearing the path

55

Chapter 4 dives into events like this, but for now, completing this

step sets you up to return to the good times much faster.

I’ve spoken about the importance of mindset. Setting up an

emergency fund is one key way to gain peace of mind. It gives you

comfort and clarity around your buffer, so you can progress more

confidently and swiftly towards Sufficient Funds.

Here’s a super-

common new client conversation.

Me: So tell me about what you’re dealing with at the moment.

Do you have debts, savings? What does this all look like for you?

You: I’m debt free now apart from HECS, so I’m building my

emergency fund and saving for my next holiday. I invest $200 a

month in ETFs (more on these in chapter 3), oh and I have about

$10 000 in a separate account for other savings.

Me: Okay, so what’s your ‘other savings’ for specifically?

You: Nothing really, it’s just there in case I need it.

Me: So where is your emergency fund up to now?

You: I have $3200 right now, and I want to get it to $10 000.

It’s very common for new clients to tell us they’re squirrelling

funds away for a higher purpose before they have built a full

emergency fund. If you don’t have any personal debt (such as Buy

Now Pay Later (BNPL), credit card or unsecured personal loans),

but your emergency fund is not yet at a level you’re comfortable

with, my general rule is you should not focus on anything but

filling this up!

Insufficient Funds

56

Day-to-day accounts

Let’s break down all the accounts you’re going to need day-

to-

day.

2. BILLS AND EXPENSES

This is the new engine room for your finances!  Ideally, whether

you’re single, a couple or have a massive family, keep one account

for bills. Everyone should have debit card access. Label your cards

and remember which is which for tapping your phone, as you’ll also

have one or two more cards for the fun stuff.

All income goes in here (your salary and any dividends or rental

income). All living expenses go through here. If you have a credit

card, pay it off, ideally in full, from this account each pay. Tap, EFT

or BPAY all living expense bills from this account.

Working on combining finances for the first time? This is a great

place to start as you’ll find a lot of these are joint costs. If you’re not

ready to have both incomes coming into the same joint account and

want to keep things ‘even’, try agreeing on a fixed amount each pay

that is transferred into this one for all joint costs. Don’t force it. If

you’re not both ready to do this, it’s not urgent. You’ll know when

the time is right.

Card access required: YES

Starting balance before pay lands: One month’s ‘living’ costs

(from Tab 2 in the budget template, not lifestyle).

3. LIFESTYLE

All lifestyle costs, as previously categorised. No bills.

Declutter — clearing the path

57

Card access required: YES

For couples/families: JOINT

Starting balance before pay lands: $0

4. PERSONAL SPENDING (FUN)

Skip this one if you’re single or in a relationship and comfortable

having everything joint. This is about decluttering! Don’t confuse

yourself with extra accounts if you don’t need them.

Having said that, however, a lot of couples we work with choose

to have a separate ‘fun’ or ‘personal spending’ account each. This

allows complete guilt-

free spending at a pre-

agreed level. It also

means you can sneak in presents for each other without it being

too obvious!

If you’re at the pub together or out for a nice romantic dinner, you’re

spending from the joint lifestyle fund above. Heels on and running

solo with the ladies? Use this one.

I’ve seen anything from $50 to $1000 a week go into this account.

It will come down to your income level and how expensive your

definition of fun is. Again, if it’s affordable, and everything else

is flowing in the right direction, then I won’t judge you here. Just

remember to align it with your values.

Card access required: YES

Starting balance before pay lands: $0

Insufficient Funds

58

Upcoming accounts

5. TRAVEL

Our favourite pot of gold! Maybe you have a massive European or

US trip coming up, or perhaps you’re more of a homebody targeting

the occasional weekend away. Whatever this is for you, I suggest you

keep it separate and when you transfer in here, it is ‘assumed spent’.

Gone. This allows for 100 per cent guilt-

free travel! Don’t mess with

this, as for most of the legends we work with, this is highly valued,

away-

from-

work, get-

creative, reset, realign, relax time … you get it!

Separating out this money forces you to align your behaviour with

your goal. When you’re living day-to-day and have had a few extra

splurges, you’ve been a bit loose with your spending and your day-

to-

day accounts are approaching $0, or you need to pull money

from your ‘Niseko powder’ or ‘Barossa with the girls’ stash, you’re

definitely going to think twice about blowing those extra funds. This

is why we ‘Define’ first. Ensure your goals are motivating enough to

keep your money plan on track!

Card access required: NO. (I repeat, NO!) There is no way you

want to be able to access this stash on a whim without taking a

good, hard look at yourself.

Starting balance before pay lands: $0 if not travelling for

12 months.

Here’s the real trick if you’re up for it. You’ve heard people talk about

booking a holiday from a holiday? Well, here’s how. Loosely calculate

your next 18 to 24 months of travel plans and begin with however

much you need for the current year’s spend. That way you’re now

saving for next year’s holidays and really getting ahead!

Declutter — clearing the path

59

Coming out of COVID-

related lockdowns with a fully stacked

travel fund felt pretty good. One of the benefits of a less adventurous

two years.

6. GIFTS

This is without a doubt the most commonly underestimated item in

our clients’ budgets, and it was a surprise for us personally until we

stopped and made our own list. Tash and I tend to be fairly generous

when it comes to buying presents. I think this is fine, but it adds up

quickly, especially if you have a big family, a bunch of nieces and

nephews, or if you’re in the 25-

to 35-

year-

old ‘wedding zone’. Typically

I suggest you list everyone you’d like to be buying for, break it down

by birthdays and holidays, then add the other likely ad hoc items like

engagements, weddings and other specific cultural celebrations.

If you think you spend only $1000 a year on gifts, my guess is you

may need to more than double that. When we first did this, our list

quickly added up to more than $5000 p.a. Totally fine if you can

afford it, and it’s something you value, but worth a squiz just in case.

Card access required: NO

Starting balance before pay lands: $0 (or 50 per cent of your

annual spend if it’s past June and the holiday season is approaching)

It may help to have other ‘Upcoming’ or ‘Squirrel’ accounts (we’ve

seen it all, and some of these may be very relevant to you!):

•

Baby. Saving to start a family — more on this in chapter 4.

•

Family support. Helping parents or other family members

financially.

Insufficient Funds

60

•

Car. Paying the balloon/residual value on a car loan and

keeping the car.

•

Home renovations. For minor upgrades, not major renos

where you’re generally extending the home loan.

•

Shooting-

through fund. Sadly this will be a reality for

many, including those suffering financial or domestic abuse.

Having a back-

up account in your own name outside of the

emergency fund could be critical.

•

Financial freedom fund. Helping you leverage your time to

spend it aligned to your definition of Sufficient — more on

this in chapter 3.

For some people, keeping separate accounts for each of these extras

works best. Others are comfortable storing at least some of the

different squirrel funds in one account. This is quite common if

you’re using an offset account with your home loan and are trying to

achieve a higher interest saving. Again, though, if combining funds

becomes confusing and more time-

consuming, you’ll be more

likely to overspend, so don’t get stuck chasing the interest saving

when structure, which drives behaviour, beats interest saving every

day of the week. When in doubt, silo your money, name accounts

accordingly and keep it flowing!

Automate

Got the accounts sorted? Time to make it FLOW! You are human,

don’t let this fact ruin your big plans. The point of automating is to

remove you from the system by following these steps in order:

Declutter — clearing the path

61

1. STARTING BALANCE TO BILLS ACCOUNT

Wait until you’re about to get paid and add your starting balance to

the Bills account. This starting balance gives you a full month’s buffer.

2. DIRECT DEBITS FOR EVERYTHING WHERE POSSIBLE

Use your budget to question every single expense: can this be

automated?  This includes the obvious ones like rent, mortgage

and utilities, but also those sneaky quarterly bills like council and

water rates. Complete a direct debit application on the provider’s

site (for some regional councils you’ll need to call or email). If you

find it easier to manage shorter billing cycles, split these up into

monthly payments.

You’ll find almost all of your direct debits come from your Bills

account, which is why you have a month’s buffer here and it receives

all of your income.

3. AUTOMATIC TRANSFERS TO EACH OF YOUR OTHER ACCOUNTS

From your Bills account, you now need to set up automatic transfers

to each of your other accounts according to your budget and goals.

Line up the frequency of transfers with your pay cycle and set up

the auto-

transfer to leave Bills the day after your pay lands just

to be sure.

If you’ve downloaded our budget template, this is easy. Tab 2 gives

you all of the numbers required here for weekly, fortnightly or

monthly cycles. Otherwise, simply take your total annual spend and

divide by 52 (weekly), 26 (fortnightly) or 12 (monthly).

Insufficient Funds

62

4. AUTOMATE YOUR INVESTMENTS

Hopefully you’re now starting to see the cascading effect of

this process — making your money truly flow.  From here you

can start to make direct automated payments into your chosen

investments, so not only are all your spending bases covered,

but you are intentionally making your money work for you in a

hands-

free way.

We’ll talk about investing in chapter 3.

You’re killing it! Everything is now automated and you’re creating

some incredible habits that will set you up for financial success.

Before you move on … CELEBRATE! It’s time to celebrate your wins.

It can be hard work to get in the mental zone to sort your money

out. Be super proud of what you’ve achieved and acknowledge it

with high fives, tequila shots or whatever works for you!

FAQs

But I use my credit card for everything!

I’m not against credit cards, but they’re not for everyone and I’ve

seen them ruin some of the best-

laid plans. If you’re just getting

started with your spending plan and are not yet in full ‘cruise

control’, I’d be leaving the credit card right out of the equation.

Put yourself on L-

plates for now, and gain full confidence over

using your money in your day-

to-

day accounts. The learned

behaviour and habits you develop from this are crucial to achieving

Sufficient Funds.

Declutter — clearing the path

63

Be very careful with the ‘spending for points’ argument too.

Rewards points are not worth what they used to be, and even the

slightest amount of overspending chasing status or points bonuses

very rarely translates into a smart financial decision and will undo

some of the other great work you’re now doing.

When might a credit card for rewards points actually be helpful?

Usually when it’s already part of a mortgage package where the

fee you’re paying is outweighed by the benefit of at least one offset

account. It may also be useful when you spend on it for large items

you’ve already saved for, such as international travel, and you

immediately transfer from your travel account (or other relevant

account) to pay off the purchase, without paying interest. This can

work as long as you’re in cruise control with the rest of the above. If

in doubt, leave it out.

Can’t I just invest already?

Not everyone we start working with is super engaged with their

money, and that’s totally normal. However, lots of our SF clients

are. What can result from this is a burning desire to do everything

at once. Everyone wants the spicy, exciting part, but TBH you need

to hit your emergency fund target first and lock it away in a separate

cash account removed from your day-

to-

day accounts. Get this

done before you start dripping your surplus into investments or

saving for your property deposit.

What if I start with cruise control and leave the debt for now?

Please don’t. You’ll feel a much greater sense of achievement if

you tick off this all-

important, and annoying AF pain in your life.

Insufficient Funds

64

This is your chance to change the course of your life forever, and

putting in the hard yards now will make all the difference. Also,

investing without an emergency fund means if an emergency does

occur in your life, you’re then at the mercy of having your cash in

a higher-

risk environment and of it not being there the day you

desperately need it.

Can I start with zero dollars?

Starting with $0 is perfect. You’re not alone. It’s the structure that’s

so crucial here, not the amounts in it. If close to $0 is your current

reality, this new system for your money will help ensure you’re

giving yourself every chance of future financial success, even if

you’re not feeling it right now.

ACTIVITY

Get off the couch and get money fit by doing

one or two of these each week:

■

■

Automate your bills, including quarterly and annual bills.

■

■

Make sure bills are emailed not posted.

■

■

Turf all the paper, scanning the important things

using Evernote.

■

■

Close unnecessary bank accounts.

■

■

Consolidate debts.

Declutter — clearing the path

■

■

Consolidate super, but don’t do this without being certain

you don’t need the insurance inside your super funds. If

in doubt, seek financial advice here before acting. This is

a common error we see, and generally not one that can

be undone.

■

■

Automate your savings.

■

■

Review insurance policies.

■

■

Review bank statements for unnecessary memberships or

subscriptions you no longer use.

Sufficiently Decluttered

By the end of this chapter:

■

■

As in every other area of life that matters, you understand

the importance of clarity and focus when dealing with

your finances.

■

■

You have a list of all your debts and have begun to

snowball or avalanche these the hell out of your

life forever!

■

■

You’ve completed your budget with your net income and

every possible weekly, monthly and annual expense, as

well as any additional spending in line with your new list of

goals from chapter 1.

■

■

You’ve set up an emergency fund and have a good grasp of

exactly how much money you need in this account.

65

Insufficient Funds

68

as possible, understanding that this was the key to earning more

and building the life we wanted. But we also needed to be super

strategic as the financial elements started to come together.

We needed to understand our own appetite for risk, both as

individuals and as a couple, and we needed to have enough

financial literacy to make sure we were channelling funds into

smart investments.

In chapter 3, I’ll cover a bunch of areas you will need to be on top of

in order to build your money life in a way that puts you on the fast

track to Sufficient Funds. We’re accelerating from bank accounts to

investment options; I’ll debunk a major tax myth that has so many

treading water; and I’ll introduce a new way of thinking about your

super fund.

Before we get stuck into investment options, it’s time to blow the

lid off one of the core elements of our work with clients at Sufficient

Funds and explain the concept of the four stacks of Sufficient Funds.

Note: I’ve aimed to break down most of the technical stuff in

this book. You will already know that the financial industry is like

any other, wittingly or unwittingly confusing everyone through the

massive overuse of acronyms, abbreviations and other jargon.

One thing we avoid at all costs in our business is using these

bewildering terms with our clients. We get it. It’s hard enough to

build up the courage to approach a financial planner and open up

to the opportunity ahead of you without the fear of being ‘talked

at’ about your own damn money and left more confused than

when you started.

Develop — big plans, growth and mad momentum

69

The ‘mad stacks’ strategy:

introducing the four stacks

of Sufficient Funds

Now you’ve decluttered your finances, you should be very familiar

with what’s coming in and what’s going out. If you have a decent

chunk of money left over after each pay, congratulations! You

probably look financially similar to most of our clients when they

first engage with us. You’re also likely to face the issue of knowing

what to do with the extra funds.

Of course, having options is a great challenge to have; in fact, it’s one

we all strive for, but it is still a challenge, and one that should not

be taken lightly. One wrong step could cost you tens of thousands

of dollars, more years of work or, worse, the inability to achieve

Sufficient Funds and the goals and dreams you set out in chapter 1.

Even if you do all the research and spend the time to understand the

technical aspects of the financial choices available to you, there’s

still the matter of getting out of your own way and making the right

decision — or rather, all the right decisions. And you need to get the

sequence of these decisions right too.

Fortunately, there’s an easy way to think about this, and it involves

the idea of four stacks .

This is where the rubber really hits the road for our clients, and

where we add massive value to their lives. I’m going to lay it all out

for you right here.

Insufficient Funds

70

The four stacks are very simple. They are:

1. Debts

2. Savings

3. Investment

4. Super.

At any point in time you would rarely be targeting only one stack.

In fact, I would argue that unless you’re swimming in the types of

debts we discussed in chapter  2 (credit cards, personal loans or

BNPL), you’re likely to need at least two or three of the stacks at all

times. Think of this as literal stacks of cash on the table in front of

you, but with very specific rules and purposes for each.

Those on a decent income with HECS/HELP or a mortgage, a chunk

of spare cash and 20 to 30 years before retirement will probably want

to make use of all four stacks of Sufficient Funds, just like Nicola.

A client example

Nicola is single, 32 years old, a medical doctor on an income of

$220   000 with $150   000 in savings.

•

Stack 1 (Debt): She made a large payment to her significant

HELP debt last year, saving a one-

off indexation of 7.2 per

cent. She also extinguished some annoying Afterpay debt

that she didn’t realise was costing her a heap, even on a low

balance of approximately $2000.

Develop — big plans, growth and mad momentum

71

•

Stack 2 (Savings): Nicola is funnelling $1500 per month

into her travel fund. Her number one ongoing priority

is what she calls ‘adventure’, and she is actively spending

this in one to two epic trips per year. She also just finished

saving $8000 to fund freezing her eggs (more on this in the

next chapter), as well as funding some of her future home

deposit with savings in the bank.

•

Stack 3 (Investment): With her work, Nicola has the ongoing

need to be flexible around which city or state she lives in.

She wants to stay open to all opportunities, but renting

and being debt free are key flexibility factors. She is saving

approximately $5000 a month, and to help fund her house

deposit she is now investing 50 per cent of this in a parcel of

managed funds (read more about different ways to invest in

the share market later in this section). The idea here is she

is spreading her surplus cash between share investment (a

growth asset with more risk, but likely more return over five

to seven years or more) and bank savings (cash is a defensive

asset, with little or no risk but a likely lower return).

•

Stack 4 (Super): The final portion of her cash is now being

utilised in the First Home Super Saver Scheme (FHSS). As

a first home buyer, she is able to contribute $50 000 under

the FHSS, at a maximum of $15 000 per annum. She is

going to make concessional (pre-

tax) contributions to super

of $15 000 for the next three financial years, and one final

contribution of $5000. She is doing this as soon as possible,

rather than spreading it over five or more years, because

the deemed rate of return inside super under the FHSS is

higher than the savings rate paid by banks and therefore a

more attractive yet still very safe option for her.

Insufficient Funds

72

A note on super contributions

There are two ways to contribute to super: concessionally

or non-

concessionally, each with its own limits and tax treatment.

Concessional contributions are pre-

tax. These include both

personal contributions you make before tax and Superannuation

Guarantee Contributions (SGC 

— 

the ones the government

makes your employer do, is 11.5 per cent of your income as of

July 2024, before rising to 12 per cent from July 2025).

To make a pre-

tax contribution you can either instruct your

employer to start a ‘salary sacrifice’ to super for you, which

will come out of each pay before tax is taken out, or you can

do this manually by using the BPAY details provided by your

super fund. If you make a manual contribution to super, you

will need to complete an ATO form called a notice of intent,

which is lodged with your super fund to ensure you get the tax

benefit. Concessional contributions are taxed at a lower rate

inside super (15 per cent, or 30 per cent for income earned over

$250 

000) than most people’s marginal tax rate and currently

have a limit of $30 

000 per annum including SGC.

Non-

concessional contributions are made after tax, meaning you

have already paid tax on it before you choose to add it to super.

There is no tax on this money when it lands in super. The current

limit to these contributions is $110 

000 per annum. If you have

a larger amount to contribute you can send a whole three years’

worth, or up to $333 

000, using what is known as the ‘bring-

forward rule’. This strategy is more common with those closer

to retirement or for younger peeps after the sale of a significant

asset like a business or property and less pressure on the other

three stacks (usually own home, debt-

free, cash-

sufficient and

investments solid).

Develop — big plans, growth and mad momentum

73

As soon as Nicola has maxed out her $50 000 contributed towards

the FHSS she plans to continue contributing at a lower rate to max

out her concessional (pre-

tax) contributions cap. At that point her

debt stack will become the mortgage, and super will be utilised

solely for a long-

term, tax-

free retirement income. More on super,

and why it should matter a lot to you right now, soon.

You may have picked up on the fact that Nicola is currently putting

more into super than her annual concessional contributions cap allows.

At the time of writing the cap is $30 000 and her employer pays her

Super Guarantee Contributions of $24 420 simply because she earns

$220 000 and this is currently legislated at 11.5 per cent. So when she

adds $15 000 of her own contribution to this she is blowing the annual

cap out of the water by $9420. The good news is that she is able to

benefit from the ‘carry-

forward’ contribution rules. As she doesn’t yet

have $500 000 in super, and her income increased significantly recently,

she has a lot more room to move with her previous year’s caps, which

she can now utilise to top up her super fund for the FHSS and still

benefit from the tax deductions available as a result. WINNING!

Remember, you don’t need to extinguish all debts before you start

investing!

Bad debt should absolutely be zeroed before tackling anything other

than creating a small emergency fund. Other debts, however — in

particular any educational loans such as HECS/HELP, your

mortgage and any investment loans — and the decision to pay these

down faster than the contracted minimum repayments, should

become part of your greater strategy and one of your options in

terms of where you direct surplus funds each pay cycle. Just because

you have a mortgage doesn’t mean you shouldn’t be investing or

potentially contributing to super.

Insufficient Funds

74

Of course, the specifics of how this applies to you, compared with

the next individual, couple or family, will vary dramatically based

on your goals, your target timeframes for these and the flexibility of

these if something goes wrong.

One way to think about it is as ‘return on investment’, or ROI as

we money nerds know it. Your ROI is most easily thought of as a

percentage. If I invest $100 today, and it’s worth $107 in 12 months’

time, I’ve made an ROI of 7 per cent for the year it’s been invested.

When it comes to adding cash to your debt stack, I want you to

think about your ROI as how much you will save, and for the other

three (savings, investment, super) as how much you will make. You

can then use the resulting percentage as a way of comparing the

benefit. Let’s go a bit deeper. Your ROI for directing your spare cash

to debt is equal to the interest rate on the debt you are paying off;

for example, if you have a home loan with a rate of 6 per cent, then

adding cash to this (paying it down) saves you 6 per cent. With

investments your ROI is either the income or the growth (increase

in value over time), or both. For example, the ROI of cash in the

bank is equal to the interest rate received; however, the ROI for an

investment in shares is equal to the growth in value plus the income

received (more on income from shares, or dividends, coming up).

If it’s HELP/HECS debt, then the ROI is a little more unpredictable.

In Australia this debt is indexed each year at the start of June for all

debt that has been outstanding for more than 11 months. Indexation

means the government applies a percentage increase to the debt,

just as a bank applies interest to a loan. Therefore, when thinking

about paying off HELP/HECS your ROI is equal to the indexation

percentage, announced each year around April or May.

Develop — big plans, growth and mad momentum

75

Note that tax implications also need to be taken into account when

calculating ROI. I cover tax in more detail later in the chapter, but

for now, just know that the interest on a debt used to purchase an

asset that generates investment income, for example an investment

property loan, may be tax deductible to you. So your ROI of paying

off an investment debt vs an owner-

occupied home loan with no

tax benefits is going to be different. Your ROI for paying off the

investment debt will be reduced by the amount of tax benefit you

miss out on, where for the owner-

occupied loan your ROI remains

at the interest rate of the loan itself.

Investment returns are also taxable. Income is generally taxed in

your annual tax return, where tax on growth is paid in the year that

you sell an asset and realise a ‘capital gain’ — hence the term capital

gains tax (CGT).

It would be nice if all you had to think about when it comes to

building your stacks is the ROI. There’s a bit more to it, though!

Another important factor in deciding which stack to target, especially

for the savings, investment or super stacks, is the timeframe you have

until you need the cash. If your goal is to retire with stacks of tax-

free

income available to you, and there are no other major goals standing

in your way, then you’ll be okay to pump your super fund as hard as

possible, ensuring you do this in a tax-

effective way.

For our clients, most of whom are between 25 and 45 years old, major

goals are a fact of life! They commonly include more pets, starting a

family, multiple and significant adventures, buying their first home,

supporting kids with big purchases and education, flexible work,

starting a business, home upgrade and early retirement.

Insufficient Funds

76

Finally, your need for cash will depend on the flexibility of the goal

itself. If your goal is to upgrade your home to a nicer suburb closer

to the beach, you might say that ideally this goal will happen in the

next three years, but if it was to happen in year four or five, that

would also be okay. However, the goal of putting your child

through private schooling for high school does not have a flexible

timeline. You can’t delay when the beginning of year seven comes

flying around!

The right amount in each stack!

I’ve already covered this in theory, but here’s the detail. Your key

to achieving Sufficient Funds is having your money decisions fully

aligned to the life you want to live and to be confidently on track

for all of it!

Take our client Nicola. In six years, with a new home and a

mortgage, and likely a long-

term partner in her life, here’s how this

could play out:

•

Debt : She will extinguish her new home loan within

15 years. A simple online mortgage calculator allowed her

to set the goal of paying it off during this time, allowing

a buffer for higher interest rates, and she has automated

the additional repayments.

•

Savings : With the help of our mortgage broking team, she

found a loan structure that allows multiple offset accounts,

which means she can save cash according to Cruise

Control: Your Spending Plan, and have every cent she

Develop — big plans, growth and mad momentum

77

accumulates offsetting interest on her mortgage. This is one

way to make your money really work for you.

•

Her emergency fund is full. Her adventure fund is also full.

In fact, not only has she prepaid her upcoming month in

Argentina, but she’s a year ahead with this. This allows her

to book her next adventure from the last one so she always

has something to look forward to.

•

She and her partner Jake are actively planning to start a

family. They’re jointly saving to their baby fund, allowing

them enough to get through the income fluctuations

of having two children and each of them going back to

working four days a week (see chapter 4 for how you

can do this).

•

Investment : As soon as she had enough money in her

house deposit fund, she shifted her thinking around

her investment portfolio to the longer term. This has

become her future financial freedom fund, allowing

flexibility around how much she works from age 50 or 55

onwards. This stack will reach sufficient height when it

can generate an annual $500 000 of additional income,

so she’s investing enough to get this to $1 million. This

allows her to significantly reduce her work hours, or even

stop work if she wants to, once the mortgage has been

paid off, and it gets her safely to her preservation age

(In short, when she can access super, discussed later in

this chapter).

Develop — big plans, growth and mad momentum

79

you should be considering additional contributions to Super.

If you’ve maxed out super contributions, then go back to Investment

and go bananas! This is where true legacy starts to build and you’re

creating long-

term, intergenerational wealth. For many, this is part

of their definition of ‘Beyond Sufficient’.

Most of our clients have at least $500 to $1000 per month to deploy,

as they’re not spending it all, and have a few ‘options’ in terms of

how to utilise this extra cash. This is a key reason why they seek

financial advice.

At least for us at Sufficient Funds, financial advice is not only about

investment returns, although these are important; it is also about

everything else in your life, and how you align your money decisions

with your desired life. Our goal is to ensure you have the best chance

of squeezing every bit of fun, joy, experience, love, happiness and

fulfilment you possibly can out of the time you have left. Money is

no more than a facilitator for this.

You’ll find more in chapter 5 about how and why financial advice

might be super valuable to you right now. For now, hopefully you’re

on your way to DIYing a lot of this, so let’s keep pumping!

Note: Before you take this step make sure you understand that

this is general rather than personal advice. What works for one

person might not work for you for a bunch of reasons. Please

don’t act without seeking professional advice.

Insufficient Funds

80

Goal-focused investment for the win!

Link your investments back to your goals and your definition of

Sufficient Funds. At the core of this book, my goal is to help you

make the connection between money and life. When you get this

right, achieving Sufficient Funds is just around the corner. Aside

from aligning your day-

to-

day spending with your values, and not

burning cash on crap you don’t care about (tick!), the next time this

concept becomes invaluable, and something you cannot skip over,

is when you’re ready to begin investing.

Investing without a plan is like starting a road trip without checking

if the car is roadworthy. You’ll enjoy the ride, until you’re stuck in the

bottom of Death Valley, California in 52 degrees Celsius, squatting

among the scorpions in the cacti, dealing with a bad burrito.

You need to know what you want to achieve (chapter 1), and your

investment choices need to link back to these specific goals. That’s

how you’ll make sure your investment strategy stands the test of

time and doesn’t fall apart when the markets momentarily tank, or

other external events intervene.

So what kind of plan should you have? It should be specific to your

goals and flexible enough to account for the unknowns that life

throws at you. For example, let’s say your goal is to save up for a

house deposit. In that case, your investment strategy should be

tailored towards that specific goal. You might be tempted to invest

in the share market, thinking it’ll give you higher returns than other

types of investments. But before you go down that path, ask yourself

if it’s the best investment strategy for your goal .

Develop — big plans, growth and mad momentum

81

The share market is volatile, and it can be risky. If you invest there,

you need to be prepared to weather the ups and downs, and generally

this means having time on your side (usually at least five to seven

years). If you’re saving up for a house deposit and you’re on track for

achieving this sooner than, say, three years, you might not have the

luxury of waiting for the markets to recover.

So you need to think about your investment strategy in a different

way. You might consider investing in a high-

interest savings account

or term deposit, which will provide a lower-

risk way to grow your

money. In Australia, you could also consider the First Home Super

Saver Scheme as a tax-

effective option to build wealth, without the

same risk as the share market, as well as some great tax benefits that

will further enhance your return.

But let’s say your goal is different. Along with many of our clients,

you might want to create a financial freedom fund that allows you

to reduce your work hours when you hit 45 years old to work on

your side-

hustle, spend more time with the family or take extended

breaks to explore the world. In that case, your investment strategy

will be different. You might need to consider a mix of investments

that provide both growth and income to fund your lifestyle.

Or perhaps you’re funding private schooling for your kids (chapter 4).

Private education can be expensive, so it’s important to start

planning and investing early. You could consider education bonds

or investment accounts that offer tax benefits and are specifically

designed for education expenses.

But here’s the thing: life changes. We all know that, and these days

the rate of change is a lot faster than it was for our parents. You might

set a goal today and find that in a year’s time your circumstances

Insufficient Funds

82

have completely flipped. Maybe you’ve had a phenomenal business

opportunity, found a new partner or decided to start a family. That’s

why your investment strategy needs to be fluid and flexible enough

to account for the guaranteed unknowns that life throws at us.

Let’s say you’ve been diligently saving for a deposit on a house,

but then you’re offered a dream job opportunity in New York and

you have to drop everything. We work with a lot of junior doctors

who find themselves in this sort of situation. To maximise your

career prospects early, the ability to be flexible around where you’re

living may be crucial. Tash and I have moved cities three times for

different reasons. The first two were career-

focused moves that paid

off big time. When this happens your investment strategy may need

to change. You may need to adjust your savings goals or put your

money into investments that can be accessed quickly (access to an

investment is known as liquidity).

Or let’s say you’ve been building up your financial freedom fund, but

then face unexpected medical bills over and above your emergency

fund (chapter  2), so you need to dip into those savings to cover

the costs. Your investment strategy needs to be flexible enough

to accommodate these changes then allow you to rebuild your

emergency fund without derailing your long-

term goals.

Whether you’re saving for a home deposit, funding private schooling

for your kids or creating a financial freedom fund, being able to

make this clear link to your goals ensures you stay motivated and

removes the emotion from investing, and when you hit the inevitable

potholes you are prepared, not stressed, and can adjust as you go.

The bottom line is this: investing without a plan is like driving

around a new city without your map app. Sure, you might stumble

Develop — big plans, growth and mad momentum

83

on hidden treasures, but more likely you’ll end up lost and frustrated.

When it comes to money, this is not cool and is the opposite of what

I want for you. This is how to make sure your investment strategy

stands the test of time and helps you achieve the life you want to live.

Debunking the tax myth

We all love our tax deductions, right! ‘I’m paying too much

tax — how do I reduce it?’ I have this conversation with my clients

all the time. Sadly, there’s a myth when it comes to tax deductions

that not everyone is aware of.

There are lots of opportunities out there that, for better or worse,

offer tax deductions as a ‘benefit’. We often see these tax deductions

mistakenly being used as the reason for making a significant

financial decision. This might be for an investment, a business trip,

a novated car lease package through work, a donation, personal

insurance or some other form of spending.

Let’s get one thing clear. When you get tax back through your tax

return, it’s because you’ve already spent the money …  and you only

get a portion of it back.

If you were already going to spend this money, then go bananas and

find every legal loophole to get that tax back. However, if you’re yet

to spend (to invest, donate or lease that car) and are weighing up

your options, you need to pause and make sure you’re acting for the

right reasons.

Table 3.1 (overleaf) shows the 2024/25 personal tax thresholds in

Australia.

Insufficient Funds

84

So if you earn $145 000, the $10 000 you earn above $135 000 is

taxed at 37 per cent. Therefore, on a tax-

deductible donation of $10,

you will receive 37 cents per $1, or $3.70 back when you do your tax

return. Effectively, you’ve lost (or in this case donated) $6.30.

The tax-

deduction conversation can sometimes go something

like this:

Investor chasing gold at the end of mythical tax rainbow:

‘Guess what! I’m buying an investment property, and it’s tax

deductible!’

Concerned friend: ‘Great! Where is it? Is it going to grow in

value and give you a good rental return?’

Investor: ‘Dunno, but I’ll get a better tax return each year!’

What they’re really saying is: ‘ Guess what! I’m going to drop a dollar.

But it’s okay, because I still get to pick up 37 cents!’

Table 3.1: 2024/25 personal tax thresholds in Australia *

Taxable income

Tax on this income

0 – $18 

200

Nil

$18 

200 – $45 

000

16%

$45 

001 – $135 

000

30%

$135 

001 – $190 

000

37%

$190 

001 and over

45%

*  

To avoid confusion I’ve omitted the Medicare levy of 2 per cent. Including this

levy you pay 2 cents’ additional tax per $1 earned at each rate 

— 

for example, 37c

becomes 39c tax if you earn between $135 

001 and $190 

000.

Source: © Commonwealth of Australia

Develop — big plans, growth and mad momentum

85

Not. Cool.

A tax deduction can help make an investment more affordable, but

if that investment doesn’t perform, you still lose.

I see this with new clients all the time. Many of us have fallen

into the trap of using the idea of a tax deduction as an excuse for

purchasing something. It’s like a discount in a way. The trouble is,

this type of behaviour will lead you into a false sense of security,

feeling like you have your finances under control. And that feeling

is dangerous if it leads you to make decisions based on false

assumptions like this.

Stop and ask yourself whether you’re really benefiting. If you’re not

sure, speak to a professional.

Let me shout this out one more time: if you’re tempted to do

something purely for the tax deduction, please don’t.

Investing, purchasing insurance, leasing a car or making any other

decision that involves spending to get a tax deduction? Do it because

it’s a good idea that you would have done without the tax benefit,

and now you can claim that spending back as a bonus.

I hope this helps clear up this myth and ensure you think twice

about chasing tax breaks that might not be all that helpful for you.

Remember that when you have a large amount of tax to pay, this

can only ever come about because you’ve made good money. I’m

not saying don’t go hard trying to legally retrieve as much of this as

possible, but do it with options that are still beneficial.

Insufficient Funds

86

Tax effectiveness — before you invest

you need this … 

Let’s dive deeper into investing and taxes in Australia. As you strive

for Sufficient Funds, choosing the right tax structure is key. In fact,

for many investors, getting this one step right can have a far more

significant impact on the benefit of investing than whether your

shares, property or otherwise generates a 1, 5 or 10 per cent return!

Let me break it down for you.

We all know that taxes can take a big bite out of any income we

make. This is true of investment returns too. If you’re not paying

attention to tax when you choose your investments, you could

be leaving a heap of cash on the table. For example, investing

in superannuation can be a tax-

effective strategy for long-

term

savings. Imagine you’re investing $10 000 a year for 30 years.

If your gross (pre-

tax) investment annual return is 8.5 per cent

and you invest that money in your own name at a 30 per cent tax

rate, you’ll end up with around $885 000 after 30 years. However,

if you invest that same amount in a 15 per cent tax environment

such as superannuation, you’ll end up with around $1.13 million.

That’s a difference of $245 000 just because you chose a more tax-

effective strategy!

The rule to remember: get your tax structure right upfront! It can

be super costly to make changes down the line. For example, a

transfer of ownership of an investment property or shares from

you to a spouse would be seen as a sale, and you would need to pay

capital gains tax (CGT) on any gains made on the investment at

the time of ‘sale’. Your spouse would need to pay stamp duty to the

relevant state revenue office for the portion of the property they

Develop — big plans, growth and mad momentum

87

are purchasing. This is why it makes sense to do your homework

or seek professional advice upfront to avoid a potentially costly

tax error!

There are several different tax structures available, each with its

own pros and cons. Let’s take a closer look.

1. Investing in your own name

First up, investing in your own name is the simplest option. Any

income or capital gains generated from your investments will be

taxed at your individual tax rate. This option is ideal if you’re just

starting out, but if you’re a high-

income earner, this can result in

a significant tax burden. For example, from the 2024/25 tax year

onwards, if you earn over $190 000 a year, you’ll be subject to the top

marginal tax rate of 45 per cent. This means any income or capital

gains you generate from your investments will be taxed at this rate.

2. Investment bonds (or insurance bonds)

Investment bonds, a lesser-

known product but widely used by those

in the know, are similar to superannuation in that withdrawals

become tax-

free after a certain point, usually 10 years, but differ from

super in that you don’t have to be retired to cash in. This can make

investment bonds a great option if you’re saving for the long term but

don’t want to be restricted by the rules of super or you have already

maxed out your concessional (pre-

tax) contributions to super.

Investment bonds pay tax on your behalf at a maximum of the

company tax rate of 30 per cent. However, some products specif

ically apply an approach where they can significantly reduce this

Insufficient Funds

88

rate, and this approach alone can make it incredibly attractive for

many investors.

Be aware that because of the tax benefits available, there are also

a  few rules around how much you can contribute (usually only

125 per cent of last year’s contribution) and the 10-

year access point

for tax-

free withdrawals.

Some of these products are widely used for saving for children’s

education. There can be additional tax benefits if used specifically

for education, and a number of our clients utilise this special

structure where appropriate.

3. Family trusts

A family trust is a legal structure where assets are held and

managed by a trustee for its beneficiaries. This option can be great

if you want to invest with your family or distribute income to those

in a lower tax bracket. The trust’s income is usually distributed to

beneficiaries based on their individual tax rates. This means that

if you have family members who earn less than you, you may be

able to distribute the income generated from your investments

to them, thereby reducing your overall tax liability.  Note this

is a strategy that should only ever be acted upon as a result of

good financial advice.

There are some downsides to using a family trust, however. One of

the main ones is the cost of setting it up and maintaining it. You’ll

need to engage a lawyer or an accountant to set up the trust, and

you’ll need to pay annual fees to maintain it. And it becomes another

entity for which you are responsible when it comes to reporting to

Develop — big plans, growth and mad momentum

89

the ATO. Additionally, there are some restrictions on the types of

investments you can make through a family trust.

4. Using a company

Investing through a company is another option to consider. This

structure can provide tax benefits, as the company tax rate is

generally lower than the individual tax rate. The current company

tax rate in Australia is either 25 per cent or 30 per cent, depending on

turnover and the percentage of total income for the company that is

passive income (significantly lower than the top individual tax rate

of 45 per cent). This means that if you invest through a company,

any income or capital gains generated from your investments will

be taxed at this lower rate.

However, there are some downsides to using a company. Setting up

and running a company can be costly and time-

consuming. You’ll

need to register your company with the Australian Securities and

Investments Commission (ASIC), and you’ll need to comply with a

range of legal and regulatory requirements. A company is also not

able to claim what is known as the capital gains tax discount. This

50 per cent discount applies to assets personally owned, but not

company owned, whereby you can claim a 50 per cent discount for

any asset you sell for a gain, as long as the asset was held for longer

than 12 months.

5. Superannuation

A lot of people see super as an investment, rather than as a tax

structure. Please understand that a tax structure is all it is. You choose

your investments within super, but it is not itself an ‘investment’.

Insufficient Funds

90

Super is how we all save for retirement and is one of the most

tax-

effective ways to stack your funds for the long term.

Contributions to super can be made concessionally (pre-

tax),

helping you to minimise tax on the way in, and investment earnings

inside super are also taxed at a lower rate.

The major limitation to super is accessibility. Generally, you won’t

be able to access your super until you reach preservation age, which

for most readers of this book will be 60, and after you have stopped

work. Additionally, there are limits on the amount of money you

can contribute to superannuation each year.

Investment — your third stack

of Sufficient Funds

Mad stacks sitting idle are better than no stacks at all. What’s

even better are mad stacks multiplying themselves over time. This

is your third stack of Sufficient Funds: Investment. Let’s look at

your options.

The share market

Purchasing shares — otherwise known as equities or stocks — makes

you a part owner of a business. They can be a very good long-

term

investment. They can also be traded fairly quickly if you need access

to your funds. You can benefit from future increases in share price

as well as from possible income in the form of dividends when the

company distributes any profits.

You can purchase shares directly via an online broker. Broker

options include bank-

owned firms like CommSec and nabtrade that

Develop — big plans, growth and mad momentum

91

historically have been more expensive, or other competitors in the

market that are offering very low or no fees, like Pearler, Selfwealth

or Sharesies. All these brokers give you the flexibility and control to

buy and sell shares at will.

Alternatively, you can purchase via a more traditional human

stockbroker, where you’ll generally pay a lot more per transaction

but also for the advice that comes with it.

You can also invest in share markets by using a range of different

structures that you may have heard of, the most common being

managed funds and exchange-

traded funds (ETFs).

Here, I’ll outline some more information on some of the more

popular options for investing in shares, including why these may or

may not be right for you:

Micro-investing

These mobile apps allow you to invest small amounts of money (as

little as 1 cent in some cases) into various investment options, such

as ETFs or individual stocks. The apps typically charge low fees and

can help people get started with investing even if they don’t have a

lot of money to spare.

There are numerous apps out there, and a simple search of ‘micro

investing’ in the app store will bring these up. Be sure to do your

due diligence to determine that whichever app you choose to

invest through is backed by an Australian company with an AFSL

(Australian Financial Services Licence). This means they are regulated

by ASIC and are required to protect your personal info. Checking

out the developer’s privacy policy is also key.

Develop — big plans, growth and mad momentum

93

Potential watchouts include:

•

Fees can add up . Most of these apps operate with monthly

fees, which are subject to future increases. These need to

be taken into account when you look at the overall value of

your investment. If you have an account set up, but aren’t

using it, the monthly fees may still be deducted.

•

Fewer options, less control . Not every share is available.

Micro-

investing apps may offer a limited selection of

investment options, which may not suit you, particularly if

you’re an experienced investor or have a specific desire to

stick to or avoid certain types of shares for ethical reasons.

Your investment carries the same risks as all other share

investments. The share market has safer and more volatile

shares. You choose your risk tolerance, but you don’t get to

choose specific shares.

•

Cool your swipe finger . It’s an app, not a game. In an

increasingly gamified world, having access to your share

investments with the swipe of your phone screen may

benefit some, but is a risk if you forget you’re playing with

real funds, especially if you see quick wins!

Exchange-traded funds (ETFs)

Think of ETFs as a way to pool your stacks so you have more buying

power, like chipping in with mates for holiday accommodation. You

can afford a more expensive place to stay and enjoy the benefits that

this brings, like access to more facilities or a better location.

Insufficient Funds

94

ETFs pool together funds from many investors to purchase a mix

of shares, bonds or other assets. As the name suggests, they are

traded on stock exchanges like individual stocks, and as such

they allow huge instant diversification across a range of asset

classes. Buying on a stock exchange means you use a stockbroker

as described above, and pay a fee (known as brokerage) for

each purchase.

Benefits of investing in ETFs include:

•

Flexibility . You can buy and sell ETFs in the same way as

you would shares in an individual company.

•

Diversify your portfolio . Achieving a higher rate of

diversification with ETFs than you would with direct shares

is just one of the advantages. ETFs enable diversification

across a wide range of asset classes (think cash, shares,

property, infrastructure), as well as regions (go global!)

and sectors.

Pitfalls that you’ll need to watch out for with ETFs include:

•

Risk is real . Although your investment may be more

diversified in an ETF than with single share picks, market

risk can be just as high. Again, take this volatility into

account and make sure you can afford the impact to your

overall investments should markets fall steeply.

•

This isn’t ‘choose your own adventure’ . You won’t have

as much choice or control of the underlying assets that

make up an ETF as you would with direct shares, where

Develop — big plans, growth and mad momentum

95

you are selecting exactly what companies to invest in.

As with micro-

investing apps, this lack of control may

not suit the more experienced investor or those with

specific preferences.

•

Yep, fees again . Fees for ETFs may be lower than some

managed funds, for example, but they still exist and you’ll

need to take them into account. You’ll also need to weigh

up whether the reduced admin cost is worth sacrificing the

service and expertise that comes with a managed fund.

Managed funds

Similar to ETFs, managed funds (mutual funds in America)

combine money from multiple investors to enable greater buying

power. With managed funds the investment is used to purchase

a portfolio of assets, which can include a combination of shares,

bonds, property and/or cash. As the name suggests, the fund is then

managed by a professional fund manager.

Managed funds are accessed either directly by applying to a particular

fund online via their Product Disclosure Statement (PDS) or

alternatively through a platform. This is a very handy tool commonly

utilised by financial advisers. A platform, also known as a wrap

account, comes with a fee, so this needs to be weighed up against

the cost of using a broker if purchasing similar ETFs, as previously

described. The winner will generally depend on how much and how

regularly you are planning to invest, as well as how many different

funds you’re considering investing in. A platform generally offers far

superior reporting, including tax reporting, which can be a huge time

saver for you as well as a cost saver when it comes to how much your

accountant needs to charge you to bring it all together!

Insufficient Funds

96

Benefits of investing in managed funds include:

•

Regular investment is often cheaper and easier . With ETFs

you pay brokerage for each trade so it may be suitable for

larger or irregular investment. There are changes coming

in this space so it is improving. The managed fund

version of the investment can work out cheaper than the

ETF version if you want to automate a regular, perhaps

monthly contribution towards your investments. As

discussed in chapter 2, automation leads to flow. When

it comes to investment, it also ensures you’re not second

guessing when to invest, as this is a fool’s game and leads

you away from the goal of keeping it simple so you can

focus on your strengths. If you invest regularly, set it up

automatically and touch it only if your strategy changes,

not because you heard the market was going to tank,

or otherwise.

•

Leave it to the pros . Managed funds, like ETFs, come

with one solid benefit that can make a big difference to

your peace of mind: they are professionally managed by

investment experts. No guesswork at your end, which

could save you time and brainpower once you’ve selected

your fund(s). This may or may not lead to better returns,

but it definitely reduces the decision making. If you’re

prone to procrastination or second guessing, or you’re just

generally a more nervous investor, this could be a good

fit for you.

•

Diversification . Like ETFs, managed funds offer you the

ability to stack your cash in a variety of assets, and this may

Develop — big plans, growth and mad momentum

97

reduce your investment risk overall. Although the mix of

individual shares or other assets within a managed fund

may not be free for the choosing, you may be able to make

a higher-

level decision around the type of mix you choose,

such as Growth (generally a higher proportion of higher-

risk, higher-

reward assets such as shares and property);

Conservative (a reduced amount of risk, with typically more

investment in cash or with fixed interest); or Balanced (as

the name suggests, a bit of both).

•

Increased access . If the idea of entering a foreign share

market sounds a little out of your league, you’re not

alone. You might baulk at the idea of investing outside of

Australia, but with the instantaneous flow of information

now available it’s actually riskier not to explore beyond

our shores. The Australian share market makes up a

very small percentage (less than 3 per cent) of the total

combined size of global markets and is dominated by a

limited number of sectors, for example, resources and

finance. A great way to access these markets is through

a managed fund. With experienced fund managers who

often focus solely on their small piece of the world,

you are lowering your risk and can benefit from these

harder-

to-

reach opportunities without having to be an

independent expert.

This all sounds like an easy option, but there are some drawbacks:

•

The pros aren’t giving it away . Okay, so professionals don’t

work for free. Fair enough. The fee you pay comes down to

the approach taken by the fund you invest in.

Insufficient Funds

98

•

Jesus, take the wheel . You’re not going to have the same

level of control with a managed fund as you could with

other types of investment. Don’t expect to be calling

up your fund manager and reading your shopping list

of demands after doing your own research. This is not

how it works. You sign over your ability to make those

micro-

decisions when you jump into a managed fund,

with your only real decisions being whether to stay or go

(that is, should you continue your investment or remove

your funds).

A note on ‘passive’ v ‘active’ funds

In simple terms, your options are either ‘active’ or ‘passive’.

Passive investment is where the fund you choose takes an equal

stake in every company listed on a particular index. An index is

essentially the entire market, or at least a large proportion of it.

An example of an index in Australia that you might be familiar

with is the ASX200, which is the top 200 stocks by size on the

Australian Stock Exchange.

You could choose to take a different approach to investing

on the ASX. For instance, you might choose an active fund

that holds only, say, 30 to 40 of the stocks available in the

ASX200. This fund is going to charge more than the passive

fund as there is more work involved. The aim of the active fund

is to beat the market, rather than simply riding with the entire

market. ETFs and managed funds are similar in that you can

choose either active or passive options. Your decision will

be based on whether you prefer a low-

cost approach, or you

believe that by paying a bit more you might be able to make

more as well.

Develop — big plans, growth and mad momentum

99

•

Complex and inflexible tax . Managed funds operate as

trusts and investors in managed funds are unit holders in

the trust. The tax structuring in this space can be complex,

but you also have no say in when assets are sold, which

means capital gains can be triggered at a time you don’t

want them to be. This isn’t a non-

starter by any means,

but it’s good to understand before you dive in. The same

applies to ETFs.

Direct shares

When investors purchase shares of a particular company via a

broker, either online or using a stockbroker as described earlier,

they are purchasing ‘direct shares’.

As the investor, you should have at least some general knowledge

of the company, be it a well-

known Australian company or one you

have been following. Shares have the potential to offer high returns,

but by investing in a single company you are depending on the

performance of that company.

If you know the company you want to invest in and have done your

research into its past performance and share forecasts from various

reputable commentators, you may be well equipped to jump into a

direct share investment. However, shares can fluctuate significantly

and, unlike with a managed fund, you don’t have professionals

watching your assets and making educated decisions.

Benefits of investing in direct shares include:

•

The stakes are high . There’s a reason why movie thrillers

have been made about stock trading and Wall Street. With

Insufficient Funds

100

the high stakes comes the potential for massive returns

from well-

performing companies, and with that comes

adrenaline, excitement and superyachts!

•

Welcome to the driver’s seat . Direct investment in shares

allows you to have ultimate control over which shares,

how many, and when to buy, sell and hold. Another

benefit is a small step towards more influence over

outcomes as a shareholder, where although you don’t

have a seat at the boardroom table, you may be invited

to shareholder meetings and have the right to vote on

certain company decisions.

•

A little somethin’ somethin’ . Dividends! A dividend is

where the company profits are shared with you, the

shareholder. Companies usually pay dividends once

or twice a year and, as I described earlier, this income

adds to the growth in value to give your total return on

investment. This can be a great strategy for building up

an ongoing regular source of income over time. Many

companies pay dividends to shareholders, which over

time and after years of consistent investment can build

to provide enough to supplement your income to the

extent that you can start to make those work/life shifts

to align with your definition of Sufficient Funds. (Note

that ETFs and managed funds also have an income

component, which is a proportion of the combined value

of all dividends paid by the companies held within those

funds.) Generally speaking, shares are likely to provide

a higher percentage of income after tax and expenses

than your regular residential property will, and for

many people nearing retirement who have accumulated

Develop — big plans, growth and mad momentum

101

a lot of property, shares now become a far more

attractive vehicle to rely on for ongoing income when

employment ceases.

Keep your eyes wide open when dabbling on Wall Street:

•

Be aware of the risk . You might find you have all your eggs

in one basket. The performance of one company can hugely

impact your investment, especially if you’re not spread

across a number of industries . As a result, direct share

ownership can carry a higher risk than managed funds

or ETFs. With high stakes can come equally dramatic

nose dives.

•

Google investment school might not cut it . Investing in

individual stocks can be complex and requires a certain

level of knowledge and skill. While you don’t need a

university degree to be able to understand the basics of

the share market, it pays to have good industry knowledge

and, even better, good business knowledge in the sector in

which you wish to invest. This improves your chances of

making sound decisions about the viability of a company

before plunging your hard-

earned stacks into it. If this is

definitely not your forte, you may be better off sticking with

an investment option where you have experts making these

decisions on your behalf.

Property

Investment property is everyone’s favourite asset class, right?

Property is a wonderful vehicle for long-

term capital growth. One

of the benefits but also the risks is that you’re generally borrowing

Insufficient Funds

102

(money nerd talk: borrowing to invest is known as gearing), which

means that with lending you’re accessing a larger asset than you

could otherwise afford to purchase.

Gearing or leveraging into an asset like property means your gains,

but also any losses, are amplified. So in theory you can make a lot

more over the long term out of doing it in this way, but again it’s still

a ‘growth’ asset, which means it still comes with similar risks, and

despite a lot of Aussies feeling like it’s safer than shares, over the

long term they have actually performed very similarly.

So is it still the favourite asset class? Well, it’s a tough call these

days. There are so many good ways to build wealth that don’t take

such a huge initial outlay. So for most young people, it’s certainly

not often their first personal investment purchase, as it used

to be.

Property is a lumpy asset (that is, while you can sell a small portion

of your share portfolio, with property you can’t just cut off the

living room and sell it if you need access to cash). It also comes with

responsibilities, which can be a hassle.

However, we wouldn’t be where we are without some very fortunate

growth in property values since we purchased our first home in

2009. Property investment is still a viable option for anyone looking

to grow long-

term wealth.

But first, unless you’re buying in Woop Woop, you’ll need to borrow

money to invest in property. So just making the purchase is the first

hurdle you need to overcome.

Develop — big plans, growth and mad momentum

103

In its simplest form, the lender (bank, credit union or building

society) will look at two different numbers to work out whether

they’re happy to lend you the money:

1. Your affordability . They will consider your income and

expenses to judge whether you’ll be able to make the loan

repayments each month.

2. Your equity (basically, the size of your deposit) . At the

moment in Australia you need at least a 5 per cent deposit,

but it’s generally recommended that you have more. You

also need to be able to cover stamp duty and your own legal

fees to have a solicitor review the contract.

If you already own your own home, you may be able to use the equity

(value minus loan amount) in it to draw a larger deposit.

You may be able to use a family member to ‘guarantee’ some of your

property loan if you don’t have the minimum deposit and they put

their home up to help you out. Speak to your mortgage broker to

help you with this.

A good mortgage broker can help you find the most appropriate

loan, often at a lower rate than offered to the general public, and will

do all the hard yards from application to settlement for you.

Mortgage brokers receive a commission on settlement, once all of

the work is done. This is paid by the lender themselves out of their

own profit margin, so it doesn’t cost you a cent. On top of this they

can offer their expert advice, complete all the loan paperwork and

negotiate with the lenders so you get exactly what you need.

Insufficient Funds

104

Generally, a mortgage broker will have access to many lenders. Our

team has nearly 50 lenders on their panel. They can shop around all

the big banks, but also access those lower-

tier and specialist lenders

if this is helpful. You’ll receive a comparison, generally of three of

the most suitable lenders and loan products, and you can then make

a decision on who you feel most comfortable with.

Just as with a financial adviser, you’ll want a mortgage broker who

listens to you, who you feel comfortable working with and who

answers all of your questions in a way that makes sense to you.

If you’re ever made to feel dumb, this is their problem not yours.

There are plenty available, so keep on moving until you find a good

fit for you!

Here are a few benefits to help determine if an investment property

is right for you:

•

If you can’t beat inflation, join it . If there is one risk

guaranteed to eat into the value of your hard-

earned

dollars, it’s the increasing cost of living. The good news is

that the Australian property market generally rises with

inflation. So, while you can’t do much about the rising cost

of a coldie (I was stung $18.50 for a pint last week!), there’s a

decent chance your big chunky assets are also increasing in

value at least at the rate of everything else around you.

•

Capital gains … ca-

ching! The most obvious reason to invest

in property is to benefit from long-

term growth in the

property market. Australian residential property increased

by 382 per cent over the 30 years to 2022, which is an

annual average of 5.4 per cent. So if you add rental income,

Develop — big plans, growth and mad momentum

105

you’ll see how property rivals shares for total returns

(growth plus income) over the long term.

•

Did someone say tax breaks?  An investment property can

attract a range of tax benefits, including deductions for

interest on your mortgage, property management fees and

maintenance expenses. All of these combined can make it

more affordable to hold for the long term. However,  never

invest in something, or make any financial decision for that

matter, just for the tax benefits! If it’s not growing, providing

a strong income, or both, it’s not working!

•

It exists IRL! Property is a tangible asset . Unlike stocks and

shares, you can see it, feel it, walk through it, make a video

and post it to socials … If you want to be able to see your

investment with your own eyes, property may be right for

you. The catch here is to not allow emotion to enter your

investment decisions. Just like investing in shares, this

is about the numbers (growth, income, tax benefits), not

about what it looks like and whether the tenant forgets to

mow the lawn!

•

Status (ew, did I really just say that?) . Yep, reflecting back

on your definition of Sufficient, having something to show

for your hard-

earned cash, and if you’re a closet ‘keeping

up with the Joneses’ type, an investment property might

just satisfy your deepest inclinations. If joining the ranks of

property owners gives you a sense of accomplishment and

pride, and it makes sense financially, then get stuck in!

•

Rental income . If you’re over the idea of lining someone

else’s pocket in the rental market, switching up the

Insufficient Funds

106

stakes and being the landlord yourself might be an ideal

component of your investment portfolio. While building

equity in your property you can also collect rental income.

This is supplementary income and may be the difference

between working that full-

time gig or dialling back the

hours to spend with family or on a side-

hustle.

•

Create a legacy for the next generation . Property can provide

a legacy for the next generation. By owning property, you

can pass down an asset that can provide financial security

and stability for your loved ones in years to come.

On the flip side, here are a few watchouts you’ll want to keep in

mind when deciding if investing in property meets your definition

of Sufficient:

•

You’re playing the long game . This means having patience.

You’ll need to be prepared to hold onto your property

asset for a number of years to see the potential benefits.

Property isn’t a liquid asset (you can’t get your cash out

unless you sell the whole thing), and it requires significant

costs to buy (stamp duty and legal fees) and sell (real estate

agent’s fee). Selling can take time. If you find yourself in

a financial situation where you need to sell your property

quickly, you may need to accept a lower offer, potentially

even lower than what you originally paid. If you’re relying

on rental income, there’s always the potential of a vacancy

that impacts cash flow, so be aware that rental does not

guarantee a continuous flow of income each month.

•

It’s a chunk of cash — like, a lot a lot! Property in Australia

is expensive. You will be committing a significant amount

Develop — big plans, growth and mad momentum

107

of your hard-

earned to get your foot in the door. This can

seem hard to reach for singles and even couples. It is not

unusual to see parents acting as guarantor on loans for

their adult children, and this comes with its own issues. The

financial interactions can be complex, not to mention the

emotional side of financially relying on parents as an adult.

•

Beware of the competition . You’re not alone in this … if it

feels like everyone’s doing it, that’s because they are! The

Australian property market can be highly competitive.

Recent years have seen record numbers of people inspecting

properties prior to sale and record bids at auction. All this is

not for the faint-

hearted. When it’s an investment property,

not your dream home, get your heart out of the game. If

you’re likely to fall in love with a property and make a dumb

move as a result, get someone else to help out. This is where

many of our clients work with a buyer’s agent.

A buyer’s agent (or buyer’s advocate) is a licensed real

estate agent who, instead of working for the seller, will for

a fee work for you. A buyer’s agent’s service can include

coaching and understanding your goals and objectives,

completing in-

depth research with access to paid data

sources, relationships with agents that allow early access

to properties or ‘off-

market’ opportunities, and negotiating

on your behalf. They will also work closely with your

mortgage broker to understand capacity for borrowing,

and your financial adviser to align with your overall budget

and longer-

term life plan. The benefits of this are usually a

combination of time and cost saving (net of the fee you pay)

as well as avoiding decision fatigue and making a confident

purchase. If going it alone, you need to be prepared to do

Insufficient Funds

108

your research, act fast and be strategic to secure the ideal

investment property.

•

Climb aboard the rates rollercoaster! Interest rates can

fluctuate quickly, and given most investors are borrowing

to make their purchases, this becomes a major part of the

cost. The market can be unpredictable as it responds to a

range of factors, including government policy and economic

conditions. Part of property investing is being along for this

ride, but make sure you’ve played out the scenario if rates

rise significantly, and know if you can afford the hike.

•

I’m not high maintenance … but my investment property

is! Unlike less tangible assets, when we’re dealing with

appliances, walls, roofs and doors, things actually break.

And then there are the tenants! You’ve heard the horror

stories, and thankfully this isn’t most people’s experience,

but still worth keeping in mind. The good news is that

property managers can take care of almost all repairs

and maintenance, as well as managing the tenants, for

a fee. Maintenance costs and insurance and property

management fees can add up over time, so run your

numbers upfront and always ensure you have sufficient

buffers in place.

The bottom line is the more research you do, scenarios you envision

and time you take to understand the numbers, the wiser your

property investment choices will be.

Hit us up at Sufficient Funds Home Loans for expert help in finding

the right loan and guidance on whether you have the right amount

of money to make this work.

Develop — big plans, growth and mad momentum

109

Crypto

We’ve all seen the hype around Bitcoin play out over the past decade

during the emergence of this alternative currency. Bitcoin launched

in 2009 and led the way for other cryptocurrencies, with thousands

of cryptos now in existence.

Essentially, crypto is a virtual or digital currency that can be used

as a medium of exchange.

It does not require government issue or control, or assistance

from financial institutions to process payments. Instead, it uses

special encryption techniques to keep data secure, store and create

‘monetary units’, and verify transactions within a decentralised,

digital public ledger (a blockchain).

While there are many cryptos in existence, not all of them are

active and most are likely to fail as an investment. This is a highly

speculative area and there is a risk that government regulation will

play a huge part in its future success or failure. Nevertheless, Bitcoin

has created multi-

millionaires almost overnight, and in recent years

has caused enormous pain for those buying in right before it fell

off a cliff.

I believe crypto will continue to grow as a major player in the money

world but the risk you take in picking the right one as an investment

makes it pretty tough to justify getting into with more than a very

small portion of your available cash.

Here’s a true story. In 2013 I watched Tim Ferriss’ Random

Show (check out episode 21 at around 36 minutes) and seriously

contemplated investing in Bitcoin. I didn’t. Today, if you’re after

Insufficient Funds

110

an eye-

watering Google search, type in ‘How much would I have

if I had invested $100 in bitcoin in … ’ and add any year from its

birth in 2009. In 2013, $100 would have bought me one Bitcoin,

which today (but maybe not tomorrow) would be worth $108 000.

Who’s counting!

So is it a no-

brainer to dabble in crypto? Here are some brief points

to consider when determining if cryptocurrency investment makes

sense on your path to Sufficient Funds.

Benefits of investing in cryptocurrency may include:

•

Bright shiny objects! It’s still relatively new. It’s a novelty.

It feels exciting. If this speaks to you, and motivates you

to save, then invest wisely, this could be a part of your

strategy. Sure, crypto has been around for a while now, but

in comparison to traditional investment options, it’s still

in its infancy. Making the move to invest now could mean

you’re jumping in on the first floor (the ground floor would

have been 2013!), before potential future growth, both in

profit and popularity. This is by no means guaranteed, but if

you are attracted to things that might go boom, and have a

healthy buffer to allow for volatility, it may be worth a crack.

•

Banks are for boomers … join the revolution! Okay, so

crypto is a sure-

fire way to break free from the clutches of

the traditional banking system. If, like me, you’re repelled

by the smell of rich mahogany desks and the sight of

fabric panel cubicle walls, this is one investment vehicle

that doesn’t require a visit to a bank or waiting on hold

for 45 minutes to speak to a human. Additionally, bank

fees and waiting for days for funds to clear are a thing of

Develop — big plans, growth and mad momentum

111

the past. For the forward thinkers, this digital asset is a

revolutionary way of investing and thinking about money.

•

Self-

serve . Crypto is bought and sold online where you

can make direct transactions without the need for any

intermediaries. You’re in charge of your own funds and

how to use them. With no bank involvement, and currently

without much government intervention, there’s no

overarching authority telling you what you can and can’t do

with your funds.

•

Embrace tech . This investment type is as modern as it gets.

We are on a tech exponential curve where understanding

and embracing tech is really the only option for future

generations. Our money world has already been upended

in recent years, with most of us now getting by day-

to-

day

without cash (remember coins and notes?) in our hands.

You already know what it’s like not to actually physically see

your money, so the leap to digital assets isn’t that great. If

you’re already fairly tech-

savvy or have a desire to not be left

behind, this type of investment may speak to your values.

•

Again, who doesn’t love diversification?  Our old mate

Warren Buffett famously said that diversification is for

those investors who don’t know what they’re doing, but

that was well and truly pre-

crypto, and long before the

digital self-

service fintech world we now live in. I like to

think of diversification of your investment portfolio as

being humble enough to admit we don’t always have all

the answers, especially given the exponential rate of tech

advancement. So, as with the other investment types

outlined above, not putting all your eggs in one basket is

Insufficient Funds

112

generally a smart move. Spreading your investments across

a range of options helps reduce the overall risk should

markets drop due to unexpected events (did somebody say

worldwide pandemic?).

Given cryptocurrency’s relative immaturity, the potential pitfalls

need to be weighed up carefully. FOMO is real and just because

someone else is investing in crypto doesn’t mean you should too. Do

your research and make an informed decision.

Here are a few of the more obvious watchouts of investing

in cryptocurrency:

•

It’s a good ol’ fashioned hoe-

down! … well kinda . It has to be

stated that some of this is cowboy stuff — it’s the wild west!

As for anything new, regulations are yet to fully catch up

to cryptocurrency investing globally, and with the rate of

tech development it may be a game of catchup for quite

some time. That said, a new Bill, the Digital Assets (Market

Regulation) Bill 2023, was introduced in federal Parliament

in March 2023 that, if and when passed, will see Australia’s

first specific regulations of the crypto market.

Until then, if something goes wrong, the pathway for any

resolution is unclear, so you need to be aware that a volatile

market combined with a lack of regulation makes crypto a

much riskier investment than traditional options.

•

Tax dodge myth . Although regulations may be taking a

while to catch up, it’s a myth that crypto is completely

private and untraceable. The ATO is cracking down on

crypto income, so declare or beware. Another myth is

Develop — big plans, growth and mad momentum

113

that earnings from crypto are not taxable. The ATO will

view this as income so be very careful if you’re cashing in

to ensure you speak with your accountant as to how this

should be treated.

•

It’s not liquid gold . On the flip side of this asset type being

completely digital and able to be accessed using a self-

service model, cryptocurrency is not always as liquid as

some more traditional assets. If you find yourself in a

position where you need to sell off your coins fast to access

cash, it can be difficult, as each sale still needs a willing

buyer and will depend on the users on the particular

exchange you’ve chosen to use.

•

Nerd alert — you’ll need to do your homework . Okay, the

learning curve is real! Be prepared for your brain to hurt

a little bit. Cryptocurrency is a whole new world, new

language, new financial ecosystem that you need to get

your head around. Concepts like wallets, exchanges and

blockchain are just the beginning. No wonder Parliament is

taking their time … hehe!

•

Danger is real, but fear is a choice! Don’t panic, but crypto

investment is considered risky business and it’s not for

the faint-

hearted. You need to be prepared (mentally and

financially) to take the risk. Markets can rise quickly and

fall in an instant. Potentially high rewards may require high

risks. It can be a bit of a rollercoaster — full of thrills as your

investment rises but also nauseatingly steep descents. You

may need to hang on through a few ups and downs, so if

adrenalin isn’t your thing, or you just like your money too

damn much, it may be best to stick to the carousel!

Develop — big plans, growth and mad momentum

115

or exchange is hacked, your entire investment could be lost.

There is little recourse in an underregulated environment,

so keeping your eyes wide open is essential.

So weigh up your risks carefully. If I choose to invest in crypto, I

commit only a very small portion of my total investable assets — an

absolute maximum of 5 per cent — and also make sure that it’s

money I won’t miss if it disappears overnight.

Superannuation — the fourth

stack of Sufficient Funds

Longevity experts are talking about innovations that are really

shaking up the way we view old age. Think stem cells to repair heart

damage and injections that could prevent Alzheimer’s. Although we

don’t have these yet, think about what your retirement years could

look like once some of the more common ailments are reduced or

even eradicated in the next decade or so.

A final word on investment

As you weigh up your investment options, make sure you keep

going back to your drivers 

— 

your definition of Sufficient Funds.

Remember that you don’t just have to choose one. Over time a

large portfolio of all asset classes can be the best way to manage

risk. Keeping your personal goals in mind and being self-

aware of

your investment knowledge and your appetite for risk will help you

make investment decisions that suit your individual preferences

and keep you on track to achieve your Sufficient life.

Insufficient Funds

116

How do you get your own Cayman Islands

bank account?

Wouldn’t you love to find:

1. a legal source of tax-

free income that you never have to

report to the ATO

2. a place where you can sell assets that have been growing in

value for decades, without capital gains tax?

Well … you know that boring place your parents talk about in

relation to their retirement savings? You know it, and I’m here for it!

Super is way sexier than you think!

Superannuation takes you as close to that illusive Cayman Islands bank

account as you’ll probably ever get. For most people, it’s their very first

investment account, opened in line with their first J.O.B, and when

they get started this early, they can pump it consistently for 40+ years!

The transfer balance cap and why reaching it is

a great financial goal

To access your super, you need to hit what’s known as preservation

age, which for most people is around 60 (as long as you’ve retired),

or 65 if they are still working. Until this time, they accumulate

assets in super under — wait for it! — the Accumulation Phase . Once

they retire, though, most people transfer their entire balance to the

Pension Phase . There is a tax differential between these two stages.

Any earnings and growth of your investments within super drops

from being taxed at 15 per cent during accumulation, to 0 per cent

when switched to pension. Hello tax haven — where’s my pina colada?!

Develop — big plans, growth and mad momentum

117

The transfer balance cap is the total amount of super you can

transfer into a tax-

free pension account. At the time of writing,

this limit is $1.9 million per person. This is reviewed annually and

increased in line with inflation in $100 000 increments. So if you’re

a couple who can save enough and you play it right, you can get

$3.4 million into this special haven, which could set you up for an

incredibly comfortable latter period of your life.

Without a crazy amount of risk and drama this type of combined

super balance for a couple would give you a tax-

free income of

$150 000 to $200 000 every year for the rest of your days. Do it right

and you’ll still leave a good chunk of it for your inheritance-

hungry

offspring, or a little extra philanthropy (chapter 5).

Superannuation in Australia is a phenomenal place to start your

longer-

term savings plans. True, for most of you this feels like

the extreme long term, and that’s okay. Our clients often wonder

whether they’re too young to think too much about super. But

after recently ticking over to 40 and feeling like it was not so long

ago that I was still 20 years old and driving around the US selling

Insufficient Funds trucker caps, I can tell you it will absolutely

sneak up!

There’s a difference between focusing all your excess cash from

your spending plan (chapter 2) to super, and contributing a small

percentage of your income in a tax-

effective way.

Be careful not to get too caught up in the chatter that the benefits

of  super won’t be around when you get there. The government

needs you to be as self-

sufficient in retirement as possible, and this

is something they put in place, and made compulsory for employers

to contribute to on your behalf, over three decades ago!

Insufficient Funds

118

Super is a phenomenal way to build a really solid nest egg for when

you need it later in life. It’s all done in a tax-

effective environment,

which means when you finally do get to access your super, what you

see is what you get. Unlike any other investments you build outside

super, which may be taxed fairly heavily when you sell them, this

pot of gold is all tax free once you hit the right age.

When it comes to strategy, we are always working with clients on

finding the right amount to invest in the super stack. Here’s how

I’d like you to think about your super. It’s not the only place for

‘retirement savings’, but it could be the cream on top.

Of course, it needs to align with your version of Sufficient Funds,

but ideally this includes creating huge future buffers if you have the

ability, while neither stretching yourself nor sacrificing life now.

With buffers full, ideally your story is not: ‘I’ll pay the house off

by the time I retire, and whatever I can get into super will fund my

remaining days.’ How about this instead: ‘I’m on track to pay the

house off before I’m 55, and I’m consistently piling mad stacks for

my future financial freedom fund (this allows me to work because I

choose to, early retirement, three-

month travel stints, volunteering,

family time) and I’m maxing out super contributions, which will

give me the ultimate freedom once I can tap into this.’

Ideally you are also building assets (read: shares, property and other,

as discussed earlier in this chapter) outside of super, and outside of

your home, so you have financial security and freedom way before

you get too old to enjoy it!

One major benefit of contributing to super is that it is essentially

‘forced savings’. Your retirement savings are for retirement and,

apart from a few early-

access options in very specific circumstances,

can’t legally be spent earlier.

Develop — big plans, growth and mad momentum

119

The benefit of forced savings is that the money is allocated to a more

profitable place before you can spend it. This is linked to the positive

behaviour you will have developed from chapter 2.

The super gap for women

Superannuation is an important part of financial planning for

retirement, but in Australia there is a significant gap between the

superannuation balances of men and women. This gap, known as

the superannuation gap or the gender super gap, recognises the

difference in the average superannuation balances between men

and women. According to recent studies, the superannuation gap

in Australia is significant, with women retiring with a median

superannuation balance of $146 900 compared to $204 107 for men,

resulting in a gap of 28 per cent.

There are several reasons for the super gap. Firstly, unfortunately

women still tend to earn less than men, which means they have

less money to put into their superannuation accounts. Women are

also more likely to work part-

time or in casual positions, which

offer lower wages and fewer benefits, such as superannuation

contributions. Additionally, women are more likely to take time off

work to care for children or other family members, which can result

in a significant reduction in their superannuation contributions.

Another reason for the super gap is that women are more likely

to work in industries with lower-

paid jobs or in occupations that

don’t offer the same level of superannuation benefits as other

industries.

There’s also a systemic issue with the superannuation system in

Australia that contributes to the super gap. The current system

Insufficient Funds

120

is based on a model in which employees receive superannuation

contributions from their employer, but this system does not account

for those who work in part-

time or casual positions. This means that

women who work in these positions are more likely to miss out on

superannuation contributions. The Australian Workplace Gender

Equality Agency reports that at every age fewer than 50 per cent of

women are in the workforce full time.

In our business over 70 per cent of our client base identify as female,

including many singles, and couples where the female is the driving

force in seeking advice. As a result, this is a conversation we are

encouraging with our clients. There is some very generic advice out

there for bridging the super gap, such as consolidating super to avoid

unnecessary fees and negotiate higher salaries. Fortunately there

are some really great strategies we often employ with clients to help

address this gap as individuals. Here are the most common four:

•

Government co-

contribution . Here you are able to make

a non-

concessional (post-

tax) contribution, currently up

to $1000, and the government will match this with up to

$500 contributed to your super fund. There is a low-

income

threshold but it can often be employed, especially in times

out of the workforce or when working part-

time.

•

Spouse contributions . This works for couples, where the

higher earner contributes money into the lower earning

partner’s super fund, and the higher earner receives a tax

offset for this.

•

Contribution splitting . Again for couples, where the higher

earning partner has already made concessional (pre-

tax)

contributions to their super fund and can then split up to

Develop — big plans, growth and mad momentum

121

85 per cent of these into the lower earning partner’s fund.

This can help to equalise your super balances over time

and is particularly beneficial when one partner is working

part-

time or casually on lesser income. We’ve employed this

option with many clients as part of their Money Action Plan.

•

Carry-

forward (or catch-

up) contributions . You will recall

Nicola in our client case study was contributing above her

concessional contribution cap to pump her super. She was

using up some of her ‘carry-

forward’ allowance. The same

strategy can apply when looking to bolster one partner’s

super balance. If you’ve been working part-

time, casually or

not at all recently, you’ll likely have a significant available

limit here as it builds up over five years. So as long as you

have the cash available, you can action this if you’re single

or as a couple. If partnered, it doesn’t matter whose bank

account it’s in or where it came from.

One common question from couples is, ‘If we have spare

cash to contribute to super and get a tax benefit for this,

why would we put it in my account when I pay less tax?’

This is a very valid point. However, what it doesn’t take

into account is the ‘transfer balance cap’ I discussed

earlier, where if one partner exceeds this and the other

doesn’t then you end up in an inefficient tax position,

post-

retirement, in perpetuity. It also doesn’t take into

account the financial insecurity the lower earning, often

female, spouse feels knowing that their partner’s balance is

going to be so much higher at retirement despite decades

of partnership in building this plan together. There is no

right or wrong answer here; however, it is an important

conversation to have.

Sufficiently Developed

You now know how to plan for growth and building mad

momentum. Specifically:

■

■

You have a good understanding of the four stacks of

Sufficient Funds: debts, savings, investments and super.

■

■

You’ve spent time thinking about which of the four

stacks you’re currently contributing to (remember, it’s likely

to be more than one).

■

■

You’ve completed a pre-

investment review of your

definition of Sufficient (mostly this was done in chapter 1,

but it’s absolutely worth recapping before making

investment choices).

■

■

You’ve taken the time to understand how certain tax

structures will and won’t help your end game and to

understand the pros and cons to investing using different

entities (such as individual vs family trust).

■

■

You now have a good understanding of the different types

of asset classes and the investment opportunities within

them, and you have begun to make decisions around

where to start stacking your hard-

earned.

Congrats! You are now on the way to creating your own mad

stacks! This is where true financial freedom begins.

Read on to understand when you may need to defend your stacks

from life’s ups and downs and how to do it!

122

Insufficient Funds

124

(chapter  3), but by the time you’re done with this chapter you’ll

also understand how to safeguard yourself and your family against

those bumps and bends in the road. I’ll talk about defending your

financial position: when to use your safety buffer; how to drop

everything when you need to; the importance of perspective; and

how to protect yourself against the unplannable with insurance.

Over the years, I’ve seen endless numbers of clients facing unforeseen

difficulties — from a serious medical diagnosis to the loss of a

partner in a tragic accident, from being laid off to experiencing a

relationship breakdown.

I’ve also witnessed clients benefitting from unanticipated events:

an unexpected inheritance from a distant relative; winning Lotto

(IRL!); a redundancy that has been positively life-

changing.

Because none of these people anticipated these events, they had to

change their plans and rethink goals, adjust timelines for reaching

their targets and decide what realities to incorporate into their

current situation.

As a lot of our clients are under 40 years old, one common and

massive change is the addition of kidlets to the party.

I want to acknowledge that, for a multitude of reasons, having

children is not on the path for everyone, but it is something I’m

asked to advise on every single week. So I’ll dive into the impact a

family has on finances and I’ll tell you how this has panned out for

me personally.

None of this means your definition of Sufficient needs to change,

but your plan for achieving it may need some tweaks. We may not

Defend — through life’s ups and downs

125

be able to predict how and when the spanners will be thrown, but

we sure as hell can be prepared to dodge them, or catch them and

put them to good use!

Using your emergency fund — remember

it’s not your money!

I’ve already covered the emergency fund, one of the foundations

of your Spending Plan. Speaking from personal experience, it feels

great to have a buffer tucked away. The kicker is there’s a good

chance you’ll need it one day.

In chapter  2, I talked about the concept of tucking away your

emergency fund and never thinking about it again. Imagine it’s not

yours! Because the reality is that if you’re seeing it as something you

plan to use for something else, it’ll play on your emotions. You built

this up and felt more and more secure as it grew. You might feel

scared that you’re accessing your buffer, disappointed that you’ve

reached a situation where you need it, but remember, as long as

you’ve always viewed this as not your own, as long as it was never

allocated to anything else, then — crisis averted!

At this point, you’re going to need to return to that key element we

spoke about before you even started to define your Sufficient life:

your mindset. Again, mindset is everything, but when you’re stuck

in a rut and having to access emergency funds, your mindset is going

to be challenged. It’s at moments like these that your crystal-

clear

focus on your values and your definition of Sufficient are going to be

critical. Go back and revisit what it is you truly value and remember

this: you’re not going to be in this rut forever. The  situation

Insufficient Funds

126

is temporary. So use your funds, make these hard-

saved dollars work

for you now to build the steps up and out of the rut. Then focus on

the next step: rebuilding your emergency fund.

Once you’ve used your emergency fund and things are starting

to get back on track, STOP! Remember Cruise Control: Your

Spending Plan ensured your excess funds from each pay flowed

into all the right places. In chapter 3 I talked about some of this

excess potentially going into investments or super or both. If you’ve

depleted your emergency fund, your priority needs to be rebuilding

it. Decide what you’re going to stop contributing to while you

rebuild your buffer.

Maybe you aren’t having that big trip this year. Divert your holiday

funds to the emergency fund. Perhaps you were saving for your third

child but the two you have are more than a handful and you’re not

ready to commit to Kia Carnival life (just yet anyway). Divert these

funds. You can also slow down on your investment contributions,

just temporarily, if you absolutely must.

Remember: emergency fund filled, then fun.

Be purposeful. Remember how frickin’ relieved you were to have

that buffer to call on when you needed it? Let that motivate you to

regain that original nice round number you started with.

Finally, congratulate yourself! As difficult as it was to go through,

this was made possible by your planning ahead and dealing with

a problem independently. Being financially secure is one of the

most common objectives we hear our clients talk about day in, day

Defend — through life’s ups and downs

127

out. Your focus on this has allowed you to deal with your actual

emergency, instead of creating a new, and possibly longer-

term,

financial problem. Cracking effort!

Adding kids, not zeros

Full disclosure: It’s important to note that I’m coming at this

incredibly sensitive topic as a male. If you spend a bit of time on

Reddit, you might be familiar with the acronym AITA: Am I the

asshole?

So, I fell asleep while Tash was in labour with our first child. AITA?

I like to believe I’m not the only partner who’s taken a snooze

during such a momentous event, but I do acknowledge the non-

childbearing privilege the act represents.

Now, while I’m never going to experience every aspect of the

following topics, what I can and will bring to this is deep personal

experience in a bunch of areas that include planning a family,

fertility issues, supporting my wife through pregnancy, major

pregnancy complications and extensive time in hospital, as well

as pregnancy loss. I’m a dad to two IVF kids who are now five

and six years old. We’ve had babies in intensive care, and day

care and school transitions are now relevant, and of course

I’ve been involved in financial planning around these topics for

hundreds of clients of Sufficient Funds over the past five or so

years. So while we’re here I also want to acknowledge that we’ve

been through some really tough times ourselves through all

this, I know this can be an emotional topic for a lot of us, as

well as a very costly one. I’m incredibly privileged to work with

countless young people in building financial plans around these

big moments, and my deep understanding of what people are

dealing with is based on my having been through it all myself.

Insufficient Funds

128

Some spanners are more predictable than others. If you know you

want to have kids one day, you at least know this is something to

prep for, but in my experience nothing prepares you for the life-

changing impact of bringing tiny humans into the world. Enjoying

the ride is all part of the experience, as they say.

Adding kids into the mix opens up entirely new realms of goals and

also financial needs. From medical costs, time off work, day care

and school fees, the list grows rapidly and the financial needs you

may have had as an individual or couple change just as fast.

Timing for your family plans might be rough estimates or fairly

specific, but I highly recommend your plan be flexible enough

to allow for the unpredictable nature of trying to conceive. We

definitely knew we wanted kids but we had no idea how hard the

process was going to be.

We started trying for kids when we were around 30 years old. It

took us about four months to fall pregnant. Easy, right?

Unfortunately not. At the end of a rocky first trimester we received

news that our baby would not survive and, devastatingly, we had no

option but to terminate.

This was October 2013. Tash was told to take a couple of months to

recover and after that it was up to us.

That Christmas we bought mountain bikes, something that had been

on our list for a while, and Tash organised a ride around northern

Laos to raise funds for Care Australia. We returned in April, fitter

than ever and thinking this would be the start of our next and more

successful round of trying to conceive. This plan, too, was way off.

Defend — through life’s ups and downs

129

Tash was diagnosed with endometriosis in October 2014. She had

likely lived with it for many years but like most people with endo,

she wasn’t diagnosed until she was in her 30s. Her diagnosis came

after an appendectomy, when her surgeon discovered advanced

deep infiltrative endo.

She needed multiple rounds of surgery to remove adhesions that

meant many of her organs were stuck together. The impact of endo

on fertility is well known and before we were at last able to welcome

our baby girl into the world, we undertook a four-

year fertility

journey that included IVF, Chinese medicine — even religious

charms and voodoo statues.

This journey took a lot out of us not only physically, mentally

and emotionally, but also financially. IVF and other surgery costs

were not something we had planned for. We needed IVF for both

our kids and each round cost us around $10 000. Each round of

endo surgery was another $5000. With the endo diagnosis, prior

extensive surgery and an IVF baby on board, we opted for a private

obstetrician and all the costs that came along with it.

At this point, our finances were less than stable. I had left my

corporate job and branched out into my own business. Not only was

it taking up a huge amount of my time, but in the early days cash

was scarce. We were just keeping our heads above water. We were

hugely thankful for our emergency fund but we knew we could have

been in a much better position had we been able to predict more of

this journey.

So many people who come through our MAP™ process are planning

for families either immediately or in the future. We dive into the

details and I’m in the fortunate position of being able to relate.

Insufficient Funds

130

Whether they’d like one or two kids or the whole footy team,

we work with them to plan for it. If family history, health issues

or sexuality point to the possible need for fertility treatment, we

include it in the plan.

Because what will eventuate in this space is, to say the least,

unpredictable you need to be confident your emergency fund is

ready and that you know how you’re going to pivot if the shit hits

the fan. The fertility journey and accompanying medical diagnoses

can be stressful, but having your money sorted will prove to be a

massive stress reliever.

We are so grateful things turned out as they did for us. We have two

healthy IVF kids, and while Tash still has ongoing medical costs

with endo, we know it’s an extra line in our budget and we roll with

the punches.

We estimate endo has cost us, on average, around $7500 a year

for the past decade or so. This cost doesn’t include IVF and

other fertility treatments and nor does it take into account lost

productivity. Because we know endo will be an ongoing cost for our

family, we have our ‘endo fund’ set aside. A recent Australian study

has estimated the average economic burden of endo to be around

$20 000 per patient per year. This includes health costs, productivity

costs and carer/household costs. This is a mind-

blowing amount

of money when you consider this condition impacts one in seven

people with a uterus.

None of us ever wants to plan for either acute or chronic illness,

but it’s a fact of life and as optimistic realists we recognise the

importance of a broad understanding of potential costs, and a

chunky emergency fund to boot!

Insufficient Funds

132

Trying to conceive

For a lot of people, this part is effectively free, and fun!

For others, like Tash and me, getting pregnant entails unexpected

costs, and budgeting for these can be very difficult if not impossible.

I’m a money nerd at heart but this is one area where the numbers,

as long as you have a rough idea of Sufficient, should not dictate

the decision. Starting a family might be the start of the single most

fulfilling part of your life!

You’ll want to be as well-

prepared financially as possible but in the

end, unless you’re swimming in personal debt and aren’t making

ends meet, you’ll move mountains to make this work. Don’t

overthink it; just be aware.

IVF

What we have learned in the course of our experience with

fertility treatment is that it is highly individualised. A ‘formula’

that works for one person or couple might not work for another.

As a result, timelines and budgets also fluctuate. In fact, our

client demographics vary widely so during our Defining Sufficient

sessions and annual check-

ins we’ve discussed and planned

financially for all options, including fertility treatments and donor,

surrogacy and adoption services. Costs vary for each treatment

option, and you may need to call on several. We got lucky and IVF

was our ticket to having two kids.

At the time of writing, the out-

of-

pocket cost for a cycle of IVF

at most private fertility clinics is a little over $5000. Medications

Defend — through life’s ups and downs

133

can cost a further $2000. In some states, pre-

fertility screening is

rebatable and there are government initiatives to help reduce other

costs. For example, since 2021 in New South Wales, eligible patients’

out-

of-

pocket costs for a total cycle at some public clinics can be

reduced to just over $1000. Public hospital waiting lists may apply in

some states at various times, so keep this in mind. Generally, you’ll

pay a little more for your first round, and a little less for subsequent

rounds, should they be needed. If attempts are unsuccessful and

should you have frozen embryos available, the costs of a round are

roughly halved.

You may be able to pay for IVF with super. Definitely seek advice

before even contemplating going down this path, but in general

terms, it is sometimes allowed under the condition of release

known as compassionate grounds. You will need to meet strict

requirements, including the provision of an invoice from a relevant

registered medical professional.

There are also some options around payment plans with fertility

providers that may be worth checking out. Of course, nothing like

this is ever free, so make sure it makes financial sense for you.

EGG FREEZING

I see many clients whose plans include having kids one day but not

right now. Egg freezing is the process of storing unfertilised eggs for

a later date. Frozen eggs can remain viable on ice for many years and

the process is becoming increasingly common. At present, Medicare

rebates (and some public hospital access) will only cover egg freezing

if there is a health risk to fertility such as endometriosis or cancer,

so elective egg freezing comes at full cost through private providers.

Insufficient Funds

134

SURROGACY

This can be one of the more expensive routes to parenthood because

added to the costs of IVF and other treatments are legal fees and

counselling. Commercial surrogacy is not legal in Australia, and

internationally it comes with a significant fee over and above medical

and other costs (potentially $100 000 to $150 000 or more). While

for many people that’s going to be completely out of the question,

for some it may be worth weighing up. The rules here are incredibly

complex. If thinking about this, all parties entering a surrogacy

arrangement in Australia should seek advice from an experienced

family lawyer.

ADOPTION

Finally, adoption is another pathway to starting or growing a family.

In NSW, for example, it costs around $3000. Inter-

country adoption

is also possible for Australians, with adoption arrangements in

place with 13 countries. Inter-

country adoption costs about $10 000,

not counting extra expenses such as travel and accommodation,

citizenship costs and legal fees. Some states have hardship policies

to help lower income earners access at least some fee relief.

Pregnancy

Note: If you’re planning to deliver at a private hospital and you

don’t yet have private health cover, you will likely face a 12-

month

wait on pregnancy claims. You’ll struggle to find a policy for

which that’s not the case, so make sure you have this kind of

cover in place before you become pregnant.

Defend — through life’s ups and downs

135

Ideally you’ve got eight months of pregnancy to go by the time you’ve

found out. This is your time to get saving if you haven’t already,

as while your pregnancy might be close to free, having a baby and

setting your home up for their arrival does cost. Keep reading for the

estimated costs, but this is your window to get financially prepped.

Whether or not you have any underlying health conditions, you

may or may not be able to work as usual while you’re pregnant.

Keep in mind that there may be some timing challenges as you’re

calculating anticipated income during these months.

Birth and setup

Costs range from around $3000 to $10 000. Remember, spend on

what you value most.

MEDICAL COSTS

Birthing costs will depend on where you plan to deliver. If you

choose a public hospital, and you have Medicare, then out-

of-

pocket costs are likely to be between $0 and $1500. Because of

Tash’s medical history, we chose a private hospital and our own OB/

GYN, and the out-

of-

pocket cost for each birth was about $5000.

That cost included multiple appointments and tests throughout the

pregnancy.

SETTING UP AT HOME

We received some very wise advice when we got pregnant, and now

pass it on to anyone who needs it.

Insufficient Funds

136

Public service announcement: Most expecting parents have

already heard the advice you’re about to give them so get

permission before you deliver it. Pregnancy is hard enough

without the repetitive onslaught of well-

meaning tricks and tips!

Initially there are four big items — car seat, cot, change table and

pram. Basically, the rest can wait! Table  4.1 indicates a range of

costs to plan for, based on your savings.

As you can see, the price range for this stuff is huge. I did a quick

search and found a car seat selling for $10 687 — I wonder if it self-

cleans number 3s? There’s also a $61 000 pram if you can spare

the coin, but I’m pretty sure your little bundle of joy would prefer

their parents read up on intergenerational wealth transfer than

be treated to an eight-

month spin in the Silver Cross Rose Gold

Edition (yes, it’s covered in actual gold!). You can go nuts with

this stuff.

If you land in the middle of this spending range, as we did, you’re

up for maybe $3000 for these big items, depending on how you roll.

Our $600 pram was so damn good we allocated more to really good

car seats for both cars to save time mucking around constantly

transferring seats between cars. As you know, time is money.

Table 4.1: baby setup costs

Item

Gumtree / second-

hand

IKEA / Big W Baller

Pram

From $0

$200

$2500+

Cot

From $0

$200

$1500+

Change table

From $0

$100

$1000

Car seat

Safety first. Don’t skimp here!

$150

$1000

Defend — through life’s ups and downs

137

Finally allow $500 for everything else. Most of which can be done

in the first few weeks so don’t feel the added pressure to have

everything purchased before baby arrives. You will want an excuse

to get out and about.

Finally, be ultra-

clear on things you would appreciate as gifts and let

your family and friends know. You might appreciate a pile of clean

towels, bibs and wipes or a baby monitor much more than a singing

cactus toy. This is the time to be specific about what you need.

Time off / parental leave

Current data indicates that 60 per cent of employers in Australia

offer approximately three months’ fully paid parental leave to mum,

and quite a few bigger businesses now offer, if not the same, at least

something to partners.

Increasingly, companies are contributing to staff super for some

portion of the time spent on parental leave. This goes some way to

bridging the very real gender pay gap. If this isn’t available in your

workplace, start to challenge things a little bit. Find companies who

do offer these benefits — ideally, direct competitors — and take it to

your management team. Start to campaign. You won’t be alone.

For primary caregivers who don’t earn ‘too much’ (less than

approximately $168 000 in the previous financial year) the federal

government also kicks in 20 weeks of parental leave pay based on

the minimum wage of approximately $17 500 before tax.  Recent

changes have included the ability to look at your household income

for the financial year, rather than just the income of the primary

carer, so if you personally earn ‘too much’, as long as your combined

income is no more than $350 000, you will still qualify.

Insufficient Funds

138

The good news is that if you are eligible, you can claim both, so you can

claim the work leave as well as the paid leave from the government.

‘Dad and Partner Pay’ was recently removed and is now combined

with parental leave pay (previously 18 weeks) for a total of 20 weeks.

This can now be shared fully with the partner, but is always at the

discretion of the birth mother or the first adoptive parent.

It’s important to remember this is basic assistance. It’s paid at

minimum wage, which does go up every year with inflation, but it’s

unfortunately not available to everyone. To be eligible you need to

meet the income and work tests.

Another recent change that’s been super helpful for a few of our

clients is in the flexibility of the parental leave system. You can

now take this leave in blocks as short as one day, and you and your

partner can spread it out between you, so long as you both qualify,

until the child turns two. This might work for someone who is self-

employed and needs to keep a business running, or someone who

can work from home. So, for example, you could work two to three

days a week and take the rest of the week as parental leave.

For those who aren’t eligible, you’re going to need to take this

into your own hands and set up your own savings buffers both for

starting a family and for getting back to work.

Finally, it may be worth asking your employer about fertility leave.

Although it’s not very common yet, there are companies (including

ours as a small business!) that are offering additional days of paid leave

for fertility treatments. If you find yourself in this situation, asking

may just be the nudge your employer needs to make this a reality.

Defend — through life’s ups and downs

139

YOUR BUDGET DURING PARENTAL LEAVE

Most of the birth mums we’re working with take six to 12 months

off for their first child and the partner anywhere from a week or

two up to about three months. It all depends on entitlements and

what you can afford. And on your work situation. I’ve been working

remotely, as you know, so fortunately or unfortunately for me, hehe,

I was there for every single little drama with both kids as newborns.

Jokes aside, I’ll cherish forever the time we spent together as a young

family and I count myself very lucky we could create the flexibility

that allowed this.

Depending on your budget, or more specifically your family’s

reliance on the income(s) of those taking parental leave, you may

need to save an extra amount prior to stopping work to get you

through. The quick and easy way to do this is to pull out the budget

you’ve already completed (see figure 4.1, overleaf), ‘Save as’ a new

copy, call it ‘Parental Leave’ and play around. For the most common

example of mum taking 12 months off, replace mum’s full income

with the employer’s paid leave plus the government leave (after tax,

remember), make frequency ‘yearly’ and work out how many pay

cycles you’ll be working since you’ll be off work for the full year.

Then scroll down to the bottom to see whether there is a positive or

negative result.

If the result is positive, you’ll be fine. If not, you can see how much

you need to save for the year (or however long you’ll be away from

work), on top of your birth and setup costs. Remember this is a

simple addition of a baby fund to the account structure we discussed

in chapter 2.

Defend — through life’s ups and downs

141

Living to your potential and smashing your big work dreams is

something I want for everyone, so absolutely keep striving for this,

and ideally you will find a balance that works. This goes for partners

too. We see lots of partners who, while they may not have shared

a lot of the child care early on for financial reasons, balance out to a

four-

day week or something more flexible once the primary carer is

back at work.

Insert day care! At the ripe age of six to 12 months, children are not

exactly self-

sufficient so being back at work means someone’s still

got to look after them. If each of you works four days, and if you

stagger the days you will be at home, then you only need three days

of day care or grandparent support!

Family day care or childcare?

•

Family day cares are generally cheaper, smaller operations

with fewer kids. They’re also likely to offer shorter hours,

similar to a school day. They tend to be more flexible than

childcare centres, so fees are usually quoted hourly, ranging

from about $8 to $18 per hour, with an average of $10.76.

•

Childcare (or long day care), as the name suggests, caters

more to pre-

and post-

work hours. Ours is open from

7.00 am to 6.00 pm, which means it’s easy to do an early

drop off and still get a surf or a ride in before getting

stuck into the day! Day rates generally start from about

$80 but more commonly are closer to $130 to $180+ before

the government subsidy, which, at the time of writing, is

90 per cent for households earning under $80 000, down

to 0 per cent for the ballers with a combined income of

$530 000 or more.

Insufficient Funds

142

We lived in Sydney for most of our kids’ day care years before, in mid

2021, we moved back to Newcastle, the city where the Insufficient

Funds dream had started nearly 20 years earlier! We had no family

support in Sydney, so for most of this time both our kids were in day

care four days a week.

Pro tip: If you’re expecting a second child, don’t plan to pull

your older child out of day care while you’re juggling a newborn.

At this age your child is making lots of little friends and learning

hugely valuable social skills, and your ‘spare’ time is better

spent sleeping.

Family can also play a huge part here. We’ve seen it all. Some

grandparents seize the opportunity to look after the kids, and

others can’t get far enough away! Each to their own. There is clearly

a financial benefit here. A day a week spent with the grandparents

saved us about $10 000 a year. Thanks, Nanna and Pa! This is due to

how the subsidies worked while we had two in day care. Thankfully

the government has since stepped up to heavily subsidise your

second, third and fourth child, if that adventure is calling!

This wraps up this stage of starting a family. The next challenge is

probably how to fund the next child or two, should you be planning

to grow your family further. There’s no doubt this planning is

really difficult because there are so many moving pieces and so

many unknowns. However, it’s an amazing period in your life

so  please stop, plan and get the money stuff sorted so you can

focus on the fun.

Defend — through life’s ups and downs

143

Schooling

Unless you’re planning to start with private schooling from day one

of kindergarten, the transition from day care to school should bring

some sweet relief to your bank account!

This is us right now, and so far it’s pretty damn good! Six-

year-

old

and five-

year-

old time is very different from toddler time so, new

parents, you’ve heard it before, but it does get better!

Then there’s the extra financial freedom. We dropped from four

days a week with two kids at day care to just one, and we saved

nearly $18 000 a year. Imagine what you could do with this!

For us, if we chose to take this saving and put it into super or an

investment account, we’d have more than $880 000 extra between

us by the time we were 60.

Or you might have a $1 million mortgage and choose to pay these

savings there instead. This would have you paying out the loan

11 years earlier and save you $290 304 in interest.

You could also seriously dial up the contributions to your travel

fund, or like us you could mix it up. What you decide to do is entirely

up to you, but this is where you should be crunching the numbers

and balancing this with these priorities. The last thing you want

is to second guess the decision or be stressing about which way to

turn and not realise the significant positive impact each decision

can have on the life you’re trying to live.

Insufficient Funds

144

Private vs public schooling

I’ve heard every argument under the sun for both sides from

people from all extremes of the financial-

capability spectrum. This

includes speaking at length with people who’ve sent their kids to

private school and acknowledged it probably wasn’t necessary or

worth the funds, and to others who really couldn’t afford it, worked

themselves to the bone to make it happen, and don’t regret a thing.

I went to public high school in Grafton, where we had two choices,

one Catholic, one public. My parents ‘offered’ to send me to

Churchie, a GPS school in Brisbane, for my senior years. I politely

declined, as any reserved teenager would when weighing up leaving

home, the soccer team and a good crew of friends for boarding

school with a bunch of city boys in blazers, more than an hour

from a beach.

Grafton schooling, regional and fairly rough, was good for me. I got

to interact with kids whose families came from all walks of life. It

toughened me up a bit and gave me a grounding in what matters,

and this is something I am truly grateful for. Byron Bay’s median

house price is over $3 000 000 for a number of reasons, and I think

one of them is that if heaven exists, it will look a lot like the NSW

north coast. It’s God’s country and will forever occupy a treasured

place in my heart.

While not too many people send their kids to private school from

kindergarten, it becomes a very real prospect once high school

comes around.

You can often find some middle ground, but annual fees for the

best of the best range from about $30 000 to $45 000 per child. Add

another $25 000+ if boarding.

Defend — through life’s ups and downs

145

Let’s say that, like my clients Rach and Greg, you live in a city so don’t

need the boarding option. You have two kids — one is two months

old and the other is two — and you plan to spend $30 000 per child

per annum, in today’s dollars, for their high-

school education.

There are three ways to handle this:

1. You have wealthy parents or grandparents who are so

insistent on keeping the family tradition alive that they

refuse your weak attempts at stopping them pulling out the

black AMEX.

2. You earn $400 000+ per annum. You may not have to save

in advance: you just cover it with your net income and still

live a pretty good life.

3. You start saving or investing as soon as your kids are born

and cash in and fund the investment through regular

withdrawals from your stacks.

Here’s how we did it for Rach and Greg:

•

Mapped out each year from today through to the end of

school for their youngest to ensure we were as accurate

as possible.

•

Recommended an investment bond. This product type is

very popular for funding longer-

term costs like education.

•

Started with a $10 000 initial investment, contributing

$10 000 in the first year ($833 monthly) and increasing this

contribution by 25 per cent each year, through to year 10

Insufficient Funds

146

and then stopping. This yearly increase aligns with expected

increases in income and with other goals, which include

paying out the home loan within 10 years.

•

You can see in figure 4.2 we made an investment return

assumption of 5.95 per cent after tax. The earnings are

taxed within the investment bond, which means tax is

paid at a lower rate than these guys are expecting to pay

personally throughout this time. Bonus!

•

This spreadsheet (see figure 4.2) shows how it looked

over 20 years.

•

You can see withdrawals of $30 000 per annum (plus

inflation) for the eldest child begin in year 11. They

double two years later, and drop back for the last two

years and then, HAPPY DAYS! $26 436 is left over for the

18th-

birthday parties and a family trip to Whistler!

My view on this big decision? It depends on the child. Some kids

will cruise through the most basic of public schools and their

natural talent and focus will see them scoring high results and

choosing whatever uni and whatever course they want. Some won’t

be cut out for any further type of academic pursuit, and this is also

fine. You don’t need to attend a private school or do a business or

science degree to have an incredibly fulfilling career or start an

insanely profitable business and make mad stacks if this is what

you’re seeking.

Insufficient Funds

148

On the flip side, some kids would absolutely benefit from the extra

nurturing, attention and individualised learning that is offered

by schools that cost more each month than a $500 000 mortgage.

There’s a strong argument to be made, too, for the networking

kickstart achieved by being connected at this end of the socio-

economic spectrum. In the end, make sure it’s affordable and focus

on what your child needs, not on what you, in line with however

many generations before you, believe is right.

Note: This advice is not individualised for you. It was personal

advice for Rach and Greg and their special set of circumstances,

income, tax and other needs. We created this solution for them

after spending a number of hours discussing their personal

goals. An education plan by itself isn’t worth much; it needs to

take into account everything else that’s going on. Make sure

you seek personal financial advice before investing in this type

of product.

Drop everything

I’ve already alluded to life’s unpredictability. As a financial planner,

I pride myself on being able to plan and help predict what lies ahead

for my clients, for myself and for my family, but it is really important

to note there are some things you simply cannot plan for.

Imagine this for a second (this isn’t one for the faint-

hearted).

It’s just past 5.00 pm on a Friday, a sunny but cold Sydney afternoon,

the end of the work week. Tash is 32 weeks pregnant with our son and

is just wrapping up at the office and about to head home. Suddenly,

Defend — through life’s ups and downs

149

and without any prior sign or symptom, she starts bleeding out.

When I say bleeding out, we’re talking litres. She assumes her waters

are breaking, but looks down to see her jeans and white sneakers

absolutely soaked with blood.

Super fortunately Tash worked less than 500  metres from Royal

North Shore hospital and with maternal instinct in overdrive she

decided that driving herself to the hospital with me on the phone

would be the quickest way to get help. By the time she pulled up

outside emergency, having busted a boom-

gate on the way through,

there were pools of blood in the car. As she trailed blood through

the emergency department, she was met by staff and swiftly moved

into a resus bed, where her clothes were cut off and a team of about

15 staff began to gear up.

By the time I got there with Ada, Tash had been prepped for

surgery and was about to be wheeled in. The attending OB/GYN

made a last-

minute decision not to deliver our baby there and

then and instead to wait to see how Tash responded to a blood

transfusion. Minutes later, she started to crash. The team called a

code blue and I was told to leave the room. Mercifully, she bounced

straight back and the bleeding finally stopped. The medical notes

record she had lost an estimated two litres of blood. Tash spent

the next month in hospital as we waited for the next haemorrhage

significant enough to make early delivery of the baby necessary.

We knew he would be pre-

term and we knew at this point there

were likely to be complications.

During this month I solo-

parented our 16-

month-

old at home and

met Tash at the hospital most days. I had just started Sufficient

Funds and I begged forgiveness from our very few clients for work I

couldn’t deliver on time.

Insufficient Funds

150

Eden was born by emergency C-

section at 35 weeks, but he was a

little trouper needing only a feeding tube and a two-week stay in

special care. We took him home and enjoyed a week of relative

normality. We thought we were in the clear, but it turned out he had

contracted a serious infection while he was in special care and he

and Tash were taken back to emergency by ambulance. His infection

didn’t respond to all the antibiotics pumped into his tiny three-

week-

old premmie body, and we were told he had an antibiotic-

resistant

strain of bacteria that had entered through his umbilical cord. Again

he fought through and was discharged, albeit with a very degraded

immune system, and we were finally truly in the clear.

We could not have anticipated any of this, but we were lucky to

have private health cover in place, which saved us an estimated

$58 000 in private hospital fees.

Mentally, perspective was our secret weapon. We literally had to

abandon all plans and any sense of control and roll with what came

our way. We had to make decisions daily, knowing that the next

day would be filled with new decisions that we had no ability to

influence. This taught us that no matter what situations come your

way, you always have the ability to choose how you respond.

Pandemics

To borrow from Nitya Prakash, 2020 was like looking both ways

before you cross the street, then getting hit by an airplane. The best

financial adviser in the world could not have predicted the events

of that year and their impact on lives around the world in the years

that followed. As the stock markets began to crash in February, the

instability of the situation began to emerge.

Defend — through life’s ups and downs

151

It seemed like everyone was living their own personal version of

Supermarket Sweep meets the movie Castaway , but of course

pandemic hell was more disastrous for some than it was for others.

Deep loss was felt globally as sickness and deaths mounted. Anxiety

levels were through the roof, permeating even the most resilient of

us. For some, the financial impacts included the loss of jobs and

businesses, and in some fields it was no longer possible to earn an

income at all. At the same time, for others, the pandemic offered

a weird way to squirrel away money that could no longer be spent.

Gone were the nights out, the restaurant dining, the holidays.

Even hair and beauty got the chop, though online purchases were

on the rise.

Protection

The metaphorical road to Sufficient Funds will have a few, perhaps

many, potholes. At times you’ll be cruising on the freeway; at others

your wheels will be spinning in the sand. Some will be completely

wiped off the road by a landslide, avalanche, flood or earthquake.

You may be prevented from working, and earning, by serious illness

or injury.  In such a circumstance, how long could you survive

financially without selling everything you own? Pause for a minute

to think about this.

For most people, once sick leave and any emergency fund runs out,

not being able to work stops their financial plan dead in its tracks,

and will likely lead to their selling assets and/or having to survive

on insufficient government assistance. This is not your answer and

neither is it a sound protection plan.

There’s always self-

insurance, right? Definitely. For some.

Insufficient Funds

152

For me, being self-

insured means having passive income from

investments or a business that can continue to run without you,

either of which will pay your living costs for the rest of your

life. This might sound a little dramatic, but as financial advisers

who do a lot of work in the insurance space, we’ve seen it all and

know this not-

at-

all-

sexy part of your financial plan is absolutely

key. Remember what we covered in the previous chapter. Any

investment you make is linked specifically to something that

truly matters in your quest for Sufficient Funds. Your protection

plan should be built around not having to sell these assets (read:

give up on your goals) for what is hopefully only a blip on the

radar in the grand scheme of your life.

What you need is something to kick in that will save you from having

to sell assets, because accident or illness necessitates expensive

medical care and/or significant time off work.

One of the best ways to protect your future self from the

financial distress that can arise from events like these is having

enough insurance to call on if and when needed. If health and

lifestyle history allow, and if they are able to factor a manageable

premium into their budget, we advise our clients to take out

four  different types of cover. Payments can generally be split

between a rollover from their super fund and a monthly or

annual premium from the bank account. Then they can move on

with living their epic lives.

Following are the four types of cover you should be considering and

what you should factor in when putting them in place.

Defend — through life’s ups and downs

153

Life (aka death) insurance

This pays out a lump sum when you die or are terminally ill.

The money goes to whoever you nominate as the beneficiary, or

beneficiaries, of your policy. This can help your family continue to

cover the bills and living expenses when you die.

You might want to cover:

•

medical, legal and funeral costs

•

paying out all debt, including mortgage(s)

•

leaving a surviving spouse and any dependants with

sufficient funds to enable them to at least get back on their

feet, or to cover some or all future costs

•

larger future costs, such as private school fees.

TPD insurance

Total and permanent disability insurance is a lump sum paid if an

accident or illness means you are unlikely to return to work ever.

TPD really sucks. Financially speaking it’s worse than death. This is

because you’ll never work or earn money again but you need to be

kept alive.

Examples of what you might want to cover include:

•

any outstanding debt

•

income support

Insufficient Funds

154

•

enough to purchase a home outright, if you don’t

already own one

•

payment for an in-

home carer or a nanny; an alternative

might be your partner, but in that case you will need to

replace some of their income

•

tax, if the policy is owned and paid for by superannuation,

as TPD is a taxable benefit if paid out through your

super fund.

Trauma insurance

This pays you a lump sum when you are diagnosed with a specific

illness, including cancer, heart attack or stroke. For young people the

most common by far is cancer. Trauma insurance can help support

you and your family and pay for medical or rehabilitation costs.

Examples of specifics you might want to cover include:

•

your choice of doctor, and travel to enable you to access the

best care available. I’ve seen someone need to travel to the

United States for care and return with a US$200 000 medical

bill. Private health and Medicare won’t cover this.

•

income replacement, either for you if your income

protection doesn’t pay (a doctor says you can still work,

even though it’s the last thing you’d like to be doing), or if

you are unable to obtain income protection

•

income support for your partner or someone else who may

need to take family time to deal with your trauma.

Defend — through life’s ups and downs

155

This is one of the most complex of all personal financial product

types, which means it’s an absolute minefield and a fairly treacherous

DIY adventure should you seek it out.

If you rely on your income and want to avoid being a drain on those

around you should something go wrong, discuss your options with

Income protection insurance

This pays you a portion of your income if you have an accident or

suddenly fall ill. It is paid to you monthly as taxable income, which

generally makes premiums tax deductible. This cover is usually the

most expensive of all, because it is the most commonly claimed. It

is also the most important.

Table  4.2 provides some additional information and rules for

different types of cover, including whether your super fund can pay

for it. Note these are averages for our clients and certainly not to be

taken as personal advice. You need to calculate your specific needs

when it comes to each cover type.

Table 4.2: life insurance structure, tax and premiums

Can my

super

fund pay

for this?

Is it tax

deductible

to me

personally?

Average policy

held by clients

in the 2023

financial year

Average

annual

premium

Life

Yes

No

$1 

375 

429

$836

TPD

Yes

No

$1 

538 

995

$1476

Trauma

No

No

$172 

489

$659

Income

protection

Yes

Yes

$6670 per month

(70% to 80% of

gross income)

$2018

Insufficient Funds

156

a financial adviser. They can help you factor these costs into your

budget and give you some peace of mind that, should the worst

happen, all will be okay financially.

Here are a few other questions we’re commonly asked:

WHAT IF I ALREADY HAVE INSURANCE WITHIN

MY SUPER FUND?

Unless you’ve applied directly to your super fund to increase your

cover, it’s likely you will have their default cover and that it will be

nowhere near the levels shown in the table above. The risk here,

for example, is that you are TPD’d and you have maybe $300 000

total cover. This gives you seven years on Australia’s minimum

full-

time wage, or three years at best if you need a full-

time carer

and don’t meet the myriad requirements to qualify for any type of

disability support.

It’s an okay fallback, but doesn’t take into consideration your

personal circumstances or needs. It mightn’t, for example, be

enough to support your family or to cover expenses in the event of

your death.

Also, certain types of insurance are not available through super,

such as trauma insurance.

DO I HAVE TO HAVE A MEDICAL EXAM TO GET INSURANCE?

That depends on your personal health and family history. One of

the forms we send clients helps us learn more about their health.

From this we can get an idea whether or not a potential insurer

might ask for reports from your doctor or require specific tests.

Defend — through life’s ups and downs

157

If you have a fairly clear personal medical history and no family

history of, say, hereditary illnesses, you might not be required to

provide any further information or test results.

WHAT IF I HAVE PRE-EXISTING HEALTH CONDITIONS?

CAN I STILL GET COVER?

Each insurer has their own list of items they will and won’t cover.

We can do some research for our clients to see whether there are

insurers that might cover them despite a pre-

existing condition;

in most cases we help them find cover with an exclusion or added

loading (higher premium) that offsets this risk.

Dot the i’s and cross the t’s: your estate plan

In our work with clients, we surround ourselves with teams of

professionals to ensure our clients are looked after in every aspect

of financial planning. Estate planning is another crucial step in

defending your stacks, and you’ll need to work with a good solicitor.

Everyone should have both a Will and a power of attorney in place.

A Will is a legally binding document that stipulates how your money

and other assets will be split and transferred when you kick the bucket.

A power of attorney, in its various forms, allows someone you trust

to make important decisions on your behalf if you are incapacitated.

Everyone knows someone who’s had some sort of family drama

around wills and the contested distribution of assets. The worst-

case scenario sees funds being wasted on legal fees to sort out

unnecessary conflicts.

Insufficient Funds

158

Here are two key steps to avoid this:

1. Make sure your Will is indeed legally binding. Don’t use

cheap online Will kits. Spend the money and have your Will

drawn up by an experienced solicitor.

2. Be transparent. If you can, have clear, open conversations

with your family (and friends where applicable) to let them

know your intentions before you die. This could save a heap

of confusion as well as wasted time, energy, bad blood

and money.

Did somebody say intergenerational

wealth transfer?

Baby boomers are beginning to check out (out of the workforce,

that is), and since they are the wealthiest generation in Australian

history, over the next few years a whopping $3.5 trillion will be

passed down to their kids, who are predominantly Millennials.

There was a time when inheritances were transferred only once

older relatives died but there is a growing trend for boomers to pass

on some of their assets before they die. This means they may be

around to see their beneficiaries rejoice!

The key to the success of this earlier wealth transfer is clear

communication and education. Boomers need to be open about their

assets and ensure they have a Will in place that details their wishes

Defend — through life’s ups and downs

159

(simple advice, but too many aren’t doing this!). And Millennials

need to be asking the right questions, including:

•

How will the wealth be transferred and in what form (for

example cash, shares or property)?

•

How much will be transferred?

•

When will it be transferred?

•

Who gets Nanna’s collection of 84 porcelain

elephant statues?

In other words, what has been taboo and unspoken needs to be

acceptable and transparent! Both the givers and the recipients

should seek solid financial advice about the intricacies of wealth

transfer and how to manage the tax implications. Ultimately, this

means more of the givers’ hard-

earned funds end up, as intended,

in their kids’ hands.

Sufficiently Defended

Chapter 2 discussed the ins and outs of your funds; now you’re

across the ups and downs of planning your financial future.

By the end of this chapter:

■

■

You know that a time will come when you’ll need to

access your emergency fund and you’re prepared for the

necessary shift in mindset that will require.

159

■

■

You’re prepped for potential life changes. If kids are on the

cards, you know how to add them to the balance sheet

and are aware of what funds you will need for all stages of

starting and growing your family.

■

■

If you face fertility issues, you now understand the money

aspects of this journey and you know how to establish

funds around this for peace of mind. If you didn’t know it

before, you know now that you’re not alone.

■

■

You’ve considered how long you could survive financially

were you to become sick or to suffer an injury that

prevented your working for the foreseeable future.

■

■

You know the types of insurance available, including life

insurance, TPD, trauma and income protection, and you

understand how crucial these are, at least until you’ve

achieved full financial freedom.

■

■

You have thought about your own Will, but you also

have a good idea of whether intergenerational wealth is

likely coming in hot! If so, you are equipping yourself with

the knowledge you will need to manage the funds. In the

interest of transparency, you are sharing what you have

learned with your parents and/or siblings. ( Hint: they

could benefit from this book too!)

You are now in the solid position of not only understanding the

ins and outs of your money and when and how to invest for

growth, but also knowing how to fortify your funds so you can

make it through the inevitable ups and downs of the rollercoaster

ride that is being alive! Take a deep breath. You’re now well on

your way to Sufficient Funds.

160

Insufficient Funds

162

Stay the course

Two of the most critical components needed to achieve your

Sufficient life are (a) having an awesome plan and (b) sticking to

it. Commitment to your plan is just as important as the plan itself.

Cruise control (chapter  2) will get you most of the way, but the

human factor can creep in — this is essentially you getting in your

own damn way.

There are a few tips I share with clients around how to avoid getting

in their own way, including making sure any plans have really clear

timeframes. If you want to have bought a house by a certain date,

write it down, say it out loud. If you want to hold onto an investment

for long-

term growth and are prepared to ride the waves of the

share market or the property market, stay the course and don’t be

spooked and jump out if you don’t absolutely need to.

The other key tip is having an accountability buddy. When we’re

talking finances this is usually a partner, sometimes a parent or

sibling. Whoever this is for you, you’ll need to be willing to share

your financial details and your plans. I also suggest sharing upfront

what you want your buddy to be spotting you for. Whether it’s

excessive online shopping that could put a dent in your spending

plan, or being a bit too loose on the reno budget that could see your

investment property returns deflate, they need to know what you

are capable of when it comes to sabotaging your own finances.

Another question I ask my clients is: on a scale of 1–10 how

committed are you to achieving these goals? There’s power in

articulating your answer, and if it’s less than 9, it’s time to take a

good hard look at your priorities.

Deliver — let it flow

163

Stay authentic

Your definition of Sufficient Funds needs to remain authentic. As

time goes by you may be tempted to look over your neighbour’s fence

and confuse one of their assets or achievements with something

on your list of priorities. This is one of those times when emotion

can override reason and the best way to stay grounded and keep

your head on straight is to go back to your definition of Sufficient,

and remember that it was built with your unique goals for your

authentic self.

It’s not always easy being me, or you. Well, at least not until we truly

figure it out and embrace it. In today’s online world it’s way too easy

to compare yourself with everyone else and forget who you really

are. It’s too easy to be lured into the trap of ‘fake it till you make

it’, when it’s true authenticity that is your competitive advantage as

well as your key to living a fulfilled life.

Once you find true authenticity you have a more accurate compass

for living your ideal life. But simply telling someone to be authentic

is not actionable advice, as it’s rarely that simple. As professional

snowboarder Travis Rice puts it, ‘If we want authenticity, we have

to initiate it. Self-

discovery takes us to the wildest places on earth.’

I struggled for a long time to find myself. School for me was about

doing anything to fit in. For the most part I was being the person

I thought everyone else would appreciate. Sound familiar? It was a

comfortable default mode. As a young person it’s not always easy

to find yourself, so I want to share a few lessons I’ve learned on this

ride so far.

Insufficient Funds

164

Trust yourself

You are unique. No one else in the world has your exact set of skills,

values and strengths. Your key now is to find these and amplify them.

Express yourself

Anyone who has met me in the past decade doesn’t usually believe

this, but I was very quiet at school. My mates in high school used to

joke around telling me to shut up, because I was so quiet. I slowly

forced myself out of my comfort zone and realised that I had a

lot to share.

One of my jobs at uni was selling wine by telemarketing. If you want

to learn how to express yourself and build a thick skin at the same

time, try cold-

calling random people to talk about something you

know very little about, with the goal of having them hand over their

credit card.

My first financial planning job involved sitting in front of people

who had been cold-

called and convince them of the benefits of

getting help with their money. Before anyone wants to talk about

money, they have to be able to trust the person they’re talking to.

If I didn’t come with honesty or true authenticity, I had no chance.

You learn a lot about others but also about yourself in this kind

of situation. My EQ developed as I came to better understand

the value of what I did as a professional as well as who I was as a

person. I also learned a lot about the problems people have with

understanding and dealing with money, which is exactly why we

built Sufficient Funds.

Deliver — let it flow

165

Know your worth and stay true to it

Where does the money fit? The net-

worth and self-

worth balance

sheet is an important consideration. For some, as you’ve defined

what Sufficient Funds look like for you, mad stacks are a critical

element. For others, knowing you’ve prioritised aspects of your life

that have less to do with money is key.

Net worth is the amount by which your assets exceed your

liabilities — your monetary value. Self-

worth, on the other hand, is

your sense of your own value as a person — think self-

esteem or

self-

respect. Factors that affect your sense of self-

worth are strongly

linked to what you value in life. They are many and varied for all of

us but can include the work you do, your mental and physical health

and wellbeing, your relationships, and your sense of purpose.

Prioritising net worth or self-

worth is different for everyone.

Different cultures place a higher importance on one or the other

but even within your family, individuals will be positioned along the

net worth to self-

worth continuum.

There is no right or wrong place to be on this continuum, but along

the way you may, for example, find yourself with more or less money

than you’d planned to have, and keeping a focus on staying true to

yourself may help keep you on the right track.

Get real

Take a moment to run through your goals and make sure these

are your goals. It’s so important to make sure you’re living your life

for you. It’s not about comparing your life with those of others or

Insufficient Funds

166

setting goals because that’s what you think you should be doing.

Identify your core values and make sure your plans align with them.

The only way you will be truly happy is if you can look back at your

achievements and know they reflect your true authentic self, they

were meaningful to you and you made them happen.

Find a Sufficient cause and make

a difference that counts

I’m hoping that while reading this book you’ve spent a lot of time

thinking about yourself and your personal situation. It’s like the air-

emergency rule: fit your own oxygen mask first. Now you can think

more broadly about how you can truly make a difference to others.

For many people I meet every day, ‘being the change you want to

see in the world’ is more than just an empty mantra. It’s a way of

life. Giving and giving back are concepts they want to include in

their weekly or monthly spending plans and, when it comes to time

commitments, their calendars. Others will have a strong desire to

share wealth by donating to charity. Don’t think you have to put this

off until you’ve reached a point where you have excess funds — for

example, once you’ve hit a salary of $150 000, or once you’ve paid

off 75 per cent of your mortgage. As I hope I’ve shown you in this

book, income or asset targets are rarely a good indicator of when

you’re ready for a certain action. It may be you could start smaller

but sooner, then increase your donations as your budget or asset

position allows. There are no simple answers here; it all comes

down to your unique set of values and the drive you have to make

a difference.

Deliver — let it flow

167

When I started out in financial planning, I had no idea of the

impact I would make on clients — perfect strangers tapping into

our service — but also on my nearest and dearest. I’ve been able to

help friends and relatives buy their first home, set themselves up

for retirement and plan for time off work as they’ve expanded their

families. The pure joy I get from this is a huge reward for me and

makes each and every day I work on my business significant for me.

Is making a difference to someone other than yourself one of your

key goals? If so, I want to show you how to implement two simple

steps to feel Sufficient in this space:

•

Identify the cause or causes that really matter to you.

•

Set up a regular savings plan to ensure you not only think

about donating your hard-

earned to the right cause, but you

actually do it!

When it comes to identifying the cause or the direction of

donations, it can be useful to think broadly about why you wish

to add donations to your overall plans for Sufficient Funds. The

following are overarching themes I see with my clients:

•

Make it truly meaningful . Let’s face it, when it comes

to justifying the hours we spend behind our laptops,

commuting (for those who still do) and sacrificing time

beyond the 9

to 5, we want to know that we are making

decisions and trade-

offs in exchange for something

meaningful. Some people place value on making a positive

difference in the world, finding meaning in their actions

beyond money-

oriented success, and they prioritise

Insufficient Funds

168

philanthropy and social impact as a way to contribute to a

higher purpose, something greater than themselves.

•

Align your giving with your clearly defined values and beliefs .

This is particularly true for those I see who are passionate

about causes like global warming and climate justice,

equality and human rights. These issues ignite a passion,

and the ability to channel funds towards advancing these

causes can be highly motivating. Giving to organisations

that support these values, with either time or money, can

mean making a change for the greater good — one person,

one hour, one dollar at a time.

•

Empathy runs deep . For many, especially Millennials and

GenZ, a strong sense of empathy and deep connection are

highly important catalysts linking intention and action. This

includes being acutely aware of those issues impacting all of

humanity. It also includes a need to not live this life on a solo

mission that is driven by self-

benefit and stacking up assets,

Scrooge McDuck–style. The sense of responsibility, the desire

to give to those less fortunate, is absolute and non-

negotiable.

•

Work, but do it for cause . Many people are increasingly

keen to align their careers with organisations that are doing

good work in the world. The rise of job candidates seeking

roles where they can be assured the organisation is socially

responsible and aligns philanthropy with its company

mission and values has led many companies to double down

in this space. The bonus here is you can be giving back

while you’re on the job, and in many cases doubling money

contributions to charities for which employers offer dollar-

matching fundraising donations.

Deliver — let it flow

169

•

Influencers for good . Social media and digital tech have

played a huge role in shaping an interconnected and socially

conscious world. Information at our fingertips has made

us more attuned to humanitarian challenges and more

connected to platforms and digital mechanisms for raising

awareness, amplifying messages and mobilising voluntary

action in response to influencer stimuli.

Nowadays, charitable donations take a range of forms. You may

still be approached by old-

school door-

knockers and cold-

callers,

and now a range of digital platforms can easily be shared or linked

through social media. This means that when it comes to making

decisions around donations, it can be hard to think purposefully

through all that noise. With more and more choices for where to

send your extra cash it can be hard to keep track of your donations.

In many cases donations are tax-

deductible, but it’s easy to get

caught up in the idea of donating for donating’s sake and in

the process spread your funds so thinly they lose any meaning

or efficacy.

When you donate to a charitable cause, use the same decision-

making process you do any time you spend money. Take the time to

pause and donate with purpose.

Note: You will recall from chapter 3 that tax deductibility alone

gets far more airplay than it deserves and should only ever be

viewed as a side-

benefit of something you are planning to do

anyway. Never decide to do something just because it’s tax

deductible. It varies depending on your tax rate, but it’s like

dropping a dollar to pick up 30 cents. The only way it makes

sense here is when it’s directed to a cause that truly matters.

Insufficient Funds

170

Where possible, when identifying the cause, keep it streamlined and

simple. Make a conscious decision to support one or two that have

true meaning for you, rather than a handful that you don’t necessarily

align with. Either way make sure it is a conscious decision.

For some it’s a no-

brainer; for others it’s a more considered choice.

You might feel pressure to choose the ‘right’ cause or to be able to

explain why you chose it. If you find yourself in a spin, here are

my top tips for identifying your cause. You may be able to clarify

your philanthropic goals, identify your priorities, and make well-

informed decisions on aligning your donations with your values

and your definition of Sufficient Funds. Ask yourself the following

questions (if you have a parent approaching a time when they

are considering where to transfer their wealth, and they want to

include charity as well as family, these questions might help with

that conversation):

•

What cause do I want to look back on in 10 years’ time and

feel I was right to support it?

•

Do I want to support something in my own backyard

or would I prefer to make a difference to a national or

global issue?

•

How soon do I want to be able to see the impact? Do

I prefer to support immediate relief efforts, long-

term

systemic change or perhaps a combination of both?

•

Do I need to see the results of my donations to motivate

me to save more for this cause? Reflect on the issues that

personally resonate and will drive savings in line with your

core values. Does the mission of a particular organisation

Deliver — let it flow

171

resonate on an emotional level so I feel motivated to

support their work wholeheartedly?

•

Do I prefer to help a stranger or someone I know? (No

one said you have to donate to an organisation; it may be

much more meaningful to you if you can personally see

the impact.)

•

Do I want to contribute to a variety of causes?

•

Is it important to me that the charity has good standing so

I can be confident my dollars end up where they will really

count? If transparency and accountability are key, check

out choice.com.au for a charity checklist and how to avoid

being scammed. You can do your own research by checking

out an organisation’s publicly available info. Look for details

on how they allocate funds, how they measure impact, and

how they report their results. Do they share evidence of

regular audits and financial info (as all nonprofits should)?

•

An organisation may be reputable, but how efficiently and

effectively do they deploy your donations? You could do a

deeper dive and compare their admin expenses and their

program expenses. Do they have a proven record of effective

programs and initiatives? Ideally you’ll want to donate to

organisations who invest a significant chunk of their budget

directly into programs rather than into admin costs.

•

How can my donation have the greatest impact? Sometimes

a few bucks here or there can feel like it won’t make much

difference to the big causes. A little bit of research can help

you find opportunities that extend your donations, such as

Insufficient Funds

172

dollar-

matching initiatives, in which a wealthy individual

or corporate organisation offers to match each donation. Or

think about collaborating with friends or colleagues to give

together to make a bigger impact.

•

Do I have the capacity to contribute more than money?

Depending on the organisation, you may be able to

contribute your time and skills towards volunteer efforts, or

pro-

bono work.

•

Do I want to establish a long-

term donation plan? Do I

want to make this a one-

off donation or am I happy to have

recurring donations direct debited?

Set up a regular donations plan

Okay, so you’ve made your decisions and know what cause or causes

you want to focus on. Now there are some logistics to figure out. My

list of top questions to ask includes the following:

•

How much do you want to donate?

•

Do you want to direct debit? As with savings in general

(chapter 2), if you don’t automate it and allocate funds

before they hit the spending account, will it really

happen? Even better, do you have pre-

tax options through

your employer?

•

Do you want to make a one-

off annual payment or regular

payments throughout the year? This will depend on your

Deliver — let it flow

173

individual cash flow. For example, if you receive an annual

bonus, would it be easier if your contribution came at this

time of year?

•

Have you thought about saving over a longer period — a number

of months or years — before making a signi

ficant contribution?

Whatever your answers, stay true to what drives you and your

definition of Sufficient Funds.

Keep motivated

Staying the course and staying true to yourself sound great, but

they will absolutely take energy and require you to stay motivated

around your goals, your plans and your definition of Sufficient.

Don’t expect motivation and encouragement to just show up when

you need it. You may have heard the line about it being too late

to build a relationship when you need one. The same is true for

building a source of motivation. So, in an era when motivation is

everywhere but you need to hit ‘Subscribe’ when it counts, here are

my recommendations for how to best channel the good energy and

make it work for you.

Curate your content

The information you feed yourself will have an impact on you. The

information you invite into your life each day shapes your world,

your thoughts and, eventually, your decisions. These days you have

so many opportunities to allow content to enter your brain space.

Insufficient Funds

174

Sure, it can be debated that data-

led marketing is pushing content

at you at a rate of knots, but there are still many ways you can

curate what you’re opting into. Whether it’s your socials, the

podcasts you listen to, the books you read or, IRL, the company you

keep. No matter your source of information, it can be a source of

motivation, so make sure it aligns with your goals and the elements

that make up your definition of Sufficient. There are apps that help

you unsubscribe from emails and other content that isn’t aligned

to your needs, while I encourage you to actively lean in to those

sources that do align. Scroll through your social apps and opt in to

anything that delivers information that positively aligns with the

direction in which you’re headed.

Find your motivator

I have spent my entire working life helping people figure out their

money stuff to achieve their goals. This is what makes me tick!

But even when it comes so naturally, sometimes I still need to find

the motivation.

Your motivator could be your partner, a close friend or family

member, a mentor or colleague. If you have such a person, hold on

to them tightly. If it is someone lifting you up in each and every

conversation you have, you’ve hit the jackpot and all I can say is you’d

better be giving back as much as you get because that’s a relationship

you want to hang onto. However, not everyone (probably not even

most people) can turn to such a person, for two simple reasons:

people hate talking about money, and it scares them to reveal too

much even to their nearest and dearest.

In Australia, we also have this really annoying knack of cutting

down tall poppies. Everyone is looking over the fence at the Joneses.

Deliver — let it flow

175

As soon as they start achieving big things there’s suddenly a target

on their backs. Makes heaps of sense, right?

These are my three key takeaways for helping you find a motivator:

1. Share. Share your money situation, your goals and your

definition of Sufficient Funds. Encourage those around you

to do the same, and assuming you find someone willing

to open up, over time you might just find yourself an

accountability buddy and someone who pumps you up and

keeps you looking ahead!

2. Go mentor hunting. Actively seek out a mentor. If you’re

lucky, you’ll already have the benefit of such a person in

your work life, but if not, think about setting out one or two

of your key goals. Find someone just beyond your circle to

reach out to, and ask them if they would be willing to be a

mentor. As my kids tell me, if you don’t ask, you don’t get,

so you need to get comfortable asking, which means getting

comfortable about articulating your goals. And think of

your circle as a circle. You’re not necessarily looking for

someone older, or someone who’s above you in career terms

or in terms of financial success. Think about those who

are one step across and one step below (sometimes termed

reverse mentoring). It’s naive to think that you can’t be

motivated by someone just because they aren’t already more

successful than you. And finally, commit. Don’t stand them

up, be gracious and grateful, and when it comes time for

someone to hit you up, pay it back in spades!

3. Don’t stress if you don’t have someone in real life.

We are absolutely surrounded by energising sources of

Insufficient Funds

176

influence, from famous motivational speakers to successful

business achievers to the resonant TikTok or Insta

influencer. Find someone, or something, that resonates and

subscribe! Again, automating is key. If you have this person

pop up on your social feed during your morning coffee

without even having to search, you are using social media

marketing to your advantage.

Whatever your motivator, you need to call on it regularly. Whether

it’s a chat with a friend or mentor, a flick through realestate.com for

your ideal location, a quick squiz at the latest Flight Centre deals or

some Insta inspo, find what stokes your fire and turn it up!

The only way you’re going to achieve your goals is by summoning

the necessary energy and enthusiasm. Go!

Redefine Sufficient

Hopefully you have now spent a lot of time and energy shaping

your definition of Sufficient, but remember it’s not a static concept.

From time to time, depending on what’s going on in your life

and in the world around you, you will need to review and update

that definition.

A good starting point is to revisit chapter 1 to ensure you haven’t

missed anything or let a few old habits creep back in. Remember that

you set your definition of what a fulfilling and successful life looked

like for you. But I also cautioned that this was going to be done

to the ‘best of your ability’ at that point in time with your current

mindset. Perspectives shift and we can only see so far ahead. This is

revealed to me over and over again in the work we do with clients.

Deliver — let it flow

177

We have three sessions with new clients leading up to when they

start to implement their Money Action Plan (MAP) ™ . Sessions are

usually about four to six weeks apart. We define ‘Sufficient’ in the

first one, then revisit it and dive deeper in the second. I can tell you

that when the second session comes around and we’re revisiting the

goals and values set in the first, something is always added in, taken

away or significantly updated —  and it’s only been a month! Twelve

months on, you’re likely to see some significant changes.

There’s so much of life to be lived beyond Sufficient Funds. This

is where the real magic happens. Everything is flowing for you

and you’re starting to build mad momentum. This is the point

at which you may be ready to work towards what we define as

Beyond Sufficient.

Here are some of the prompts we use with our clients when we

revisit their definition of Sufficient Funds to make sure their Money

Action Plan (MAP) ™ continues to deliver on what matters to them:

•

You’ve achieved epic milestones . Time to celebrate, if you

haven’t already! You got married, turned your side-

hustle

into a full-

time gig, bought the house near the beach, got

the sweet new EV, reached Mt Everest base camp (as a few

of our clients did this year), started a family, graduated with

an MBA. The list goes on and on, so revisit your original list

from chapter 1 and make the updates.

•

You’ve experienced a shift in your health or wellbeing .

Evaluate any updates in your own wellbeing. How are you

feeling generally? Any new health issues, or a problem

you’ve managed to overcome or move out of your life? Did

you start a new PT regime that is costing a bomb but has

Insufficient Funds

178

been a total lifesaver? I started getting into yoga — shoutout

to my teacher, Louisa, from Lunge! Louisa effortlessly

makes the connection between the work you’re doing in

class and the associated benefits to your body and mind.

I also started to learn more about the benefits of healthy

eating in conjunction with a good exercise routine, and

suddenly I was eating a lot more wholefoods and cutting out

a heap of sugar — cue the upgraded grocery budget!

•

You’ve started a new hobby . Are you like one of our clients

who recently got her helicopter licence? In her first Money

Action Plan (MAP) ™ , this was a costly one-

off goal that she

planned and saved for, but now she’s qualified, she has to

factor a whole new cost into her Spending Plan to keep her

flying and enjoying the fruits of her labour!

Do you need to free up more time to be able to take on

other hobbies you’ve been putting off? Do you need to

evaluate your work hours or how you’re spending your

weekends in order to do more of this? I juggle surfing and

mountain biking, and often find I’ve let one or the other

(sometime both) slip out of the routine. Surfing especially

is one of my happy places; it’s great for grounding me.

Stop and think about hobbies regularly and ensure you’re

allocating the right amount of time, and money, to keep on

top of these valuable pleasures.

•

Your family and relationships change . How much time did

you spend hanging with your besties this year? Have you

made the trip you said you would to visit an old friend or

distant relative? How many weddings might be coming up

this year, and where are they? Consider the evolution of

Deliver — let it flow

179

your friendships and relationships with family members.

There’s always a delicate balance here, but relationships are

a strong source of wellbeing, and they need to align with

your money plan.

On the family front you may have thought you knew what

you wanted your future family to look like, but has this

changed? Can you now see yourself having more kids, fewer

kids, are step kids now in the picture? Is the timing and

process of starting a family now looking a little different

from the way it did when you first defined it?

•

Your enthusiasm for your current line of work has changed .

Feeling stagnant at work? Perhaps a career change or a

new business is on the cards? Are you keen to explore and

develop your public speaking skills, or is it time to enrol in

a new course that will help you get the next big promotion

at work? Or have you graduated and sworn that you’ll never

pick up another textbook in your life? Guess what, you now

have a heap of free time. How are you going to use it?

•

Your desire to give back dials up a notch . I discussed this at

length earlier in this chapter so you can refer to this as you

review how your current actions and financial plan support

your philanthropic goals and desire for social impact.

As you learn and grow through life your perspectives shift

and your priorities change. With charities you might set

up a direct debit that runs monthly and becomes set and

forget. (Great automation! See chapter 2.) However, just like

your 14 streaming services, these can easily be forgotten,

and since your resources for giving are likely to be finite it’s

Insufficient Funds

180

important the causes you still really care about are the ones

receiving your hard-

earned.

•

You want to shift the scales of work–life integration .

Remember, a key element of achieving Sufficient Funds isn’t

about stopping work forever; it’s about enjoying the work

you do so you don’t feel the need to escape it. So work–life

balance becomes more about integration. Are you still

enjoying the work you’re doing? Are you getting enough

time outside of work to explore other joys in life?

It may seem like a pipe dream to take a break from work or

to shift from full-

time to part-

time in order to align the way

you spend the time you have and your values, but at some

point, when you can see your finances looking a little more

chunky, and your confidence creeps up, you may have a

different perspective on how you want to spend your days.

It’s a constant juggling act, and we have regular

conversations with our clients around ensuring that their

Money Action Plan (MAP) ™ continues to link back to their

highest priorities. If you get this right, everything flows and

life is good.

•

You need to turn to a contingency plan . This means your

emergency fund (chapter 2) or your life and income

protection insurances (chapter 4). Did you have to use your

emergency fund and wish it had been larger? Experience

guides our future decisions so a mishap can often lead to a

better decision next time. Your appetite for risk can change

temporarily or more permanently.

Deliver — let it flow

181

Did some extra funds sneak into your emergency fund as

you forgot to stop when you reached your ideal number?

These funds can now be reallocated. After we reviewed ours

recently we cut the emergency fund by 25 per cent as we

realised we were being overly cautious. We invested those

funds instead, and we’re now $15k better off due to this

tweak. It’s nice when things play out like this.

•

You have new experiences . Do you have the experience vs

things balance right (chapter 1)? What have you been able

to tick off that list? How did it make you feel? Do you need

to do more of the things you’ve been enjoying, or is there

something else that needs to be added now?

There are significant benefits to prioritising experiences

in your life. You create lasting memories, whether with a

significant other, your young family, or just a meaningful

memory that will stay with you personally as you navigate

the rollercoaster of life.

One of the biggies in this category is travel. There’s a reason

we refer to the ‘travel bug’ — it’s contagious and hard to

shake. Travel expands your world and that experience can

feed the desire to continue to explore. So someone who has

been comfortable with a yearly interstate trip but visited

Europe for the first time in the post-

pandemic European

summer craze, may just discover they now have three other

trips they’d love to take in the next two or three years. Time

to upgrade that savings plan and channel more cash to this

epic goal!

Insufficient Funds

182

Tash and I value travelling to new places, locally and

internationally, with our young kids. We believe there is

huge value in this for them. Even if they don’t remember

much, it still expands their world and their comfort

zones so it’s a priority in our lives. We also love going

back to places we’ve visited in the past and creating new

memories there.

Isn’t financial advice just for old people

who already have mad stacks?

So what does a financial adviser actually do? Our young clients

come to us for many reasons. Following are some of these:

•

You have money left over after each pay and you’re trying

to decide where it should go. You may have an overarching

goal of paying down the mortgage, for example, but have

you considered how investing these funds would impact

your financial position? What about benefiting from

30+ years of compound returns inside super?

•

You spend what seems like a lot on things most people

save up for, but that’s chill because you get paid again next

week. This is a sure-

fire predictor of major regret in a few

years’ time, when you stop and look back at your massive

cumulative income and wonder where it all went. You know

you should be keeping more of what you’re earning, and

now you’ve read the book you can see it’s possible, but if

you had someone holding your hand through the process it

would be far more effective than DIY.

Deliver — let it flow

183

•

You’re a first home buyer and you’re wondering how much

mortgage is too much, especially as the apartment you’re

about to buy might only work for child one, but you’re not

sure what impact income fluctuations will have as you

balance starting a family with the likely need to upgrade the

home again in five years’ time when child two may be on

their way.

•

You want to know you’re putting the right proportion of

your resources into each of the four stacks of Sufficient

Funds. Remember from chapter 3 that this involves

careful decisions around your approach to debt, savings,

investment and super. The only way to ensure you’re

contributing to the right stacks at the right time is to map

out your life over a number of years so you can understand

the impact of the infinite variations that will impact your

plan (chapter 1). This means you will not only understand

the impact your money decisions will have, but also ensure

you remain on track as you make the many ongoing

changes and tweaks that will be required over time.

•

You are dealing with moving pieces. You’re juggling work

fluctuations (babies, mini-

retirements), education funding,

big purchases (can I get the EV?).

•

You are at a crossroads. Perhaps you’ve already got the

house, but you’ve got extra funds, so where to from here?

•

You’ve received an inheritance (see chapter 4).

Now, some of these situations may not require you to engage a

financial adviser and, indeed, given you’ve chosen to read this book

Insufficient Funds

184

you may be well on your way to effectively managing your own

finances. Nonetheless, it may still be a good idea to seek input from

a professional for these reasons:

•

Expertise (We’re self-

admitted money nerds) . Financial

advisers are qualified professionals with expertise in many

aspects of personal finance. We have a deep understanding

of investment, super, tax and insurance strategies and can

help you wade through the associated minefields!

•

Access to tools, resources and platforms (We’ve got the

goods) . We have access to a world of sophisticated software,

analysis and projection tools and other resources that

are exclusively for professional use. Utilising these allows

us to build a Money Action Plan (MAP) ™ that gives you

full insight into the future impact of current financial

decisions.

•

Holistic approach (We do life and money) . We take into

consideration your entire money and life situation including

personal goals and risk tolerance, and money aspects such

as your budget, savings, investments, tax planning and

retirement requirements. From this a financial plan can be

created that ensures all of the above aspects are integrated

into a comprehensive strategy.

•

Coaching and behavioural guidance (We’ve got your

back!) . We’re all about epic, genuine relationships. As I’m

sure you’ve gathered by this point in the book, financial

planning for us is about way more than money. Having

Deliver — let it flow

185

someone relatable, with high emotional intelligence,

coach you through the conversations you need to have

around your life and the intertwined monetary aspects is

crucial. This is so important during the inevitable ups and

downs. When it comes to making rational and sometimes

emotional money decisions, a financial adviser can provide

guidance and help protect you from your own impulsive

spending habits and investment decisions.

•

On track with your stacks (We’re your accountability

buddy) . We all need someone to keep us on track, and a

financial adviser is an expert in this space. Support through

regular meetings and check-

ins can help you stay the course

and make timely adjustments to your plan.

•

Regulation and compliance ( We know, and play by, the

rules ). There are heavy rules that govern how we operate

as a profession. A financial adviser is legally obligated to

provide advice that is in your best interests.

•

Time saving (We’ve got the time) . Whether it’s

researching investment options, analysing market trends

and legislation changes, or making sure your Plan is fully

actioned (implemented), these activities are highly time

consuming. Even for the most money-

savvy individuals,

having someone take this major responsibility off your

plate can free up your time and brainpower to focus on

other aspects that meet your definition of Sufficient. You

do you, we do money.

Sufficiently Delivered

You have arrived at Sufficient Funds! Well, at the very least,

you’re getting close. You’ve defined exactly what your ideal life

looks like and have begun creating and implementing the plan

that will make it flow!

■

■

You’ve worked through Defining, Decluttering, Developing,

Defending and Delivering Sufficient Funds for you.

■

■

You have a good understanding of how to stay on

track and stay motivated, and how to tackle it all while

remaining true to your values as you pursue your personal

definition of Sufficient Funds.

■

■

You know that none of this is static, and that the meaning

of Sufficient Funds for you will evolve. You’re now fully

equipped to redefine Sufficient and understand some of

the circumstances that will lead you to it.

■

■

You understand when and how to seek professional advice

when you need help and guidance along the way.

You’re now a long way from Insufficient Funds and are well

equipped to bounce yourself right back, should you fall behind

or even if you find yourself in that position again. Remember that

success is in the journey. You now have all the tools you’ve built

along the way and, most important , the confidence to make your

funds work for you!

186

Insufficient Funds

188

In chapter  5, I took you through the financial planning process

and numerous examples of Redefining Sufficient as you achieve

milestones or as shifts occur in your life. Redefining Sufficient will

be a constant part of your life and will help ensure you stay motivated

and on track. This is a crucial element of being fulfilled. Remember,

you’re not striving for a permanent recliner beach chair from which

to gaze at the horizon. You’re seeking constant progress and its

associated sense of achievement. This is what brings happiness.

What if it’s not all rosy and I stumble or fall?

I want you to accept that life is going to throw you curveballs, and

to be prepared when it happens. If you’ve carefully followed each of

the chapters in sequence, you should be as financially prepared as

you possibly can be. Of course this won’t eliminate the emotional

toll resulting from an unanticipated event such as a death in the

family, a medical emergency or a business collapse, and this is where

building a strong support network around you can help.

Here is our vision for what our clients will achieve:

They will define, achieve and reach beyond Sufficient Funds. They

will have the confidence and clarity to create a lifelong shift from

hopes and dreams to reality. They will create abundant wealth,

and have the time and health to enjoy it.

The key here is the reach. The stretch. I want you not only to achieve

Sufficient, but to reach beyond Sufficient towards Abundance. In

chapter 1, I proposed that your goals need to be big enough to give

you the motivation to chase them down. As Richard Branson once

said, ‘If people aren’t calling you crazy, you aren’t thinking big

enough.’ Remaining on track is one thing, but constantly pushing

Think bigger: Beyond Sufficient

189

your limits and challenging yourself to think bigger is a whole

different ball game.

If you think about achieving Sufficient Funds as reaching Everest

base camp, Beyond Sufficient means summiting the mountain.

Pushing your thoughts beyond your original definition of Sufficient

will not only motivate you to stay on track; it will increase your

chances of achieving those initial goals and more.

This is often where the original list of goals for five years, 10 years

and beyond becomes a serious focus. You’ve nailed all the small

stuff — now it’s time to really dream.

In money terms, don’t focus on what your stacks will look like at the

end of the month, the quarter or even the year. What does Sufficient

Funds look like for you in 10 or 20 years’ time? Think about those big

life goals; give yourself permission to dream and get set to smash them.

This is where it gets really wide and varied. To get you thinking,

here’s a short list of life goals from our clients as well as from our

own experience:

•

Full financial freedom, meaning we can choose to never

work again without sacrificing lifestyle

•

Spending every northern hemisphere winter in a debt-free

house in the foothills of powder-mecca Niseko, Japan, with

your very own onsen

•

Becoming engaged in true philanthropy — for example,

setting up a scholarship fund for children in an area where

you spent time working many years ago